<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cruell subtilty of ambtioin [sic] discovered in a discourse concerning the King of Spaines surprizing the Valteline / written in Italian by the author of the Historie of the Counsell of Trent ; translated by the renowned Sir Thomas Roe, Knight ... with his epistle to the House of Commons in Parliament ...</title>
            <title>Discorso sopra le ragioni della resolutione fatta in Val Telina contra la tirannide de' Grisoni &amp; heretici.. English</title>
            <author>Sarpi, Paolo, 1552-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9079</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12383666</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12383666</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60796</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62179)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60796)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 227:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cruell subtilty of ambtioin [sic] discovered in a discourse concerning the King of Spaines surprizing the Valteline / written in Italian by the author of the Historie of the Counsell of Trent ; translated by the renowned Sir Thomas Roe, Knight ... with his epistle to the House of Commons in Parliament ...</title>
                  <title>Discorso sopra le ragioni della resolutione fatta in Val Telina contra la tirannide de' Grisoni &amp; heretici.. English</title>
                  <author>Sarpi, Paolo, 1552-1623.</author>
                  <author>Roe, Thomas, Sir, 1581?-1644.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 101 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Lee ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Roe's translation first published in 1628 as: A discourse upon the reasons of the resolution taken in the Valteline against the tyranny of the Grisons and heretiques. Cf. DNB, v. 49, p. 93.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Paolo Sarpi. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Irregular pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Valtellina Valley (Italy) --  History --  16th century.</term>
               <term>Graubünden (Switzerland) --  History --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60796:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Cruell ſubtilty of AMBTIOIN, DISCOVERED IN A DISCOVRSE CONCERNING the King of <hi>SPAINES</hi> Surprizing The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ALTELINE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written in <hi>Italian</hi> by the Author of the Hiſtorie of the <hi>Counſell of Trent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated by the Renowned Sir <hi>Thomas Roe</hi> Knight, Many times Embaſſadour in Forraine parts, with his Epiſtle to the Houſe of Commons in <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shewing the onely way in Policie to counterplot the deſignes of promoting Unjuſt Intereſts of STATE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Lee,</hi> at the <hi>Turks Head</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet</hi> next to the <hi>Miter</hi> and <hi>Phaenix.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60796:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60796:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KNIGHTS, BARONS AND BVRGESSES of the Houſe of Commons, aſſembled in Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hings compared, though con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, or alike in nature, doe illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate one the other: <hi>Contrario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; ſimilium eadem eſt ratio.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iuſt. Inſt.</note> And therefore, to diſcerne the ſtrengths, counſels, and ends of diuers Kingdomes, the ſtraigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt rule is compariſon of their actions, gouernment, and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: All <hi>Monarchies</hi> and <hi>Republiques</hi> which haue an end propoſed, whether to emarge, or preſerue their Dominion, moſt effectually worke to their own ends, becauſe ſuch operation is naturall;<note place="margin">Polib.</note> 
               <hi>Is qui nouit quanam ſint vniuſcuinſque Rerumpublicarum principia natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, etiam incrementum et florentiſsimum ſtatum, ac mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationem, &amp; finem poteſt cognoſcere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A wife and rationall Hiſtorian comparing and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring diuers Common-wealths, why one ſubſiſted, and others decayed; and how the one preuailed vpon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60796:3"/>the other; examined the formes and inſtitutions, their deſignes, and ends, and what was poſſible to be bulk vpon them. That of <hi>Plato</hi> he eſteemed vncapable of compariſon, other then as a Statue to a man, which had excellent art, without life. <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Thebes</hi> were not vnderlaid to be are any aduerſitie: But when they were moſt like to riſe, the temperature of their policy was inſufficient to allay the abundance and increaſe of humours, &amp; the growth was too ſudden and heauy for the foundation: when they began to ſhake, their root had no earth. The <hi>Lacedemonian,</hi> to ſubliſt of it ſelfe, to oppoſe forraine violence, to need nothing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otique, to liue in peace, was in all perfection inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>Caterùm ad parandum ſibi in vicinos dominatum,</hi> to extend their Empire, euen their owne foundation was an impediment. A bleſſed ſtate, if Ambition were baniſhed the world; but defectiue to abſolute ſafetie: For, no defence is ſecure, that cannot offend. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as ſoone as that State began to affect conqueſt, and to raiſe Armies, they found in their conſtitution, that the Lawes made to keepe them happy, were too narrow to hold others in ſeruitude:<note place="margin">Plato.</note> and their vntried felicitie blinded their iudgement, to ouer-value their owne abilities. <hi>Qui vitam inſtituiſſet contra naturam, meritò etiam contra naturam fato functus eſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Polib.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Carthagenians</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> had larger ends, &amp; a broader foundation, like abilities and aptitudes to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect them, which were <hi>Imperium mundi.</hi> And though all Common-wealths doe <hi>conuenire in aliquo medio,</hi> yet they which deſigne quiet poſſeſſion of their owne, and vſurpation of the Eſtates of others, are at both ends vtterly repugnant.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60796:3"/>
            <p>The reaſons why the <hi>Romans</hi> preuailed vpon <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi> being alike inſtituted, are another conſideration,<note place="margin">Polib.</note> the manner of building, the conſtancy, vertue, and goodneſſe of Inſtruments are great differences. In theſe the <hi>Romans.</hi> excelled: and perhaps in the youth (for euery <hi>State</hi> hath an Infancy, a mature, and a decrepit age) and conſequently ſooneſt arriued at their ends. But that wherein moſt effectually they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed, was in Counſels; in which they had aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in the forme of their gouernment: For the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>Carthage,</hi> in all deliberations, had too much au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, which bred delay, and hindered ſecrecy; whereas in <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Senate</hi> and <hi>Optimati,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacit.</note> experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and wiſe men, onely reſolued. <hi>Imus ad bellum, non omnes Nuncios palam audiri;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Polib.</note> 
               <hi>non omnia conſilia cunctis praeſentibus tractari, ratio rerum, aut occaſionum velocitas patitur. Victoria conſilijs, &amp; ratione perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe Conſiderations a Conſequence is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, that when any two great Kingdomes fall into a warre, that which will preuaile, muſt conſider the ends of the other, and the wayes and meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are proſecuted, and to them muſt apply all induſtry, and direct oppoſition. In the ends, as there is great difference, ſo there is great aduantage by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: becauſe actiue things, <hi>etiamſi agendo repatiantur,</hi> weare-out paſſiue, though of equall ſtrength and hardneſſe, as the iron that ſtrikes, in time batters that which ſuffers. <hi>Common-wealths</hi> that deſigne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and are alway attentiue to watch occaſion, get ground vpon the modeſt, more by vigilancy then force: and fraud, which is a terrible inſtrument, doth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60796:4"/>euer accompany Ambition. Counſels vanquiſh Armes, as ſpirituall things are predominant vpon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall, and as fire diſſolues the faſteſt metals: &amp; thoſe Counſels are moſt preualent, which are vnited in one head, and iſſue from one fountaine.</p>
            <p>Therefore riſing and encreaſing Empires are dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, if they once grow great, and muſt be reſiſted in their ends, and in their counſels: ſingle defence is not ſufficient: troubleſome neighbours muſt be made paſſiue, to abate their reputation, which the ſpirit of action preſuppoſeth.</p>
            <p>To apply theſe premiſſes, hauing read with pleaſure the following Diſcourſe of the Reaſons of the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in the <hi>Valteline;</hi> and being at leaſure, eyther to ſleep, or waſt in mine owne meditations, I thought it would be a good recreation, and not vnacceptable to my loyall Countrimen, to teach it to ſpeake as plaine <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as it doth truth; and finding the whole ſcope of the Author (an Authour of great worth, and greater works) to be an information to the World, of the dangerous encreaſe, and ambition of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria:</hi> and, if poſſible, to read the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> a leſſon, not to bee learned, but vnder a Rodd of Iron, <hi>that in time neceſsity would open the eyes of all Princes, to oppoſe his ſecret proiect of Vniuerſall Monarchy;</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued that ſome profit might be gathered out of this forraine Garden.</p>
            <p>I wil ſuppoſe that this Theame is ſufficiently hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; and that there are few practiſed in the world, who will deny it. The witneſſes are great and euident; <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> vniuſtly vſurped; <hi>Sicily</hi> ſurpriſed by treaſon; <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> by breach of Contract; <hi>Millan</hi> held by Intruſion;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60796:4"/>
               <hi>Nauarre</hi> by excommunication of the lawfull Prince; <hi>Portugall</hi> oppreſſed by the Sword;<note place="margin">Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lag.</note> and the Pope re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to iudge either competently, or as Arbiter, the pretences of <hi>Parma &amp; Braganza,</hi> when it was poſſible in temporall Cauſes, his ſpirit might erre in not ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Spaine:</hi> The <hi>Valteline</hi> poſſeſſed vnder the colour of <hi>Religion; The Palatinate</hi> and the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Clene</hi> ſeiſed by <hi>auxiliars,</hi> and kept for Debts forced vpon the Proprietaries, which they deſired not to borrow: <hi>Weſell</hi> ſtollen in a truce; and the <hi>Rhyne</hi> paſſed ouer vnder the fauour of a Treaty; <hi>Embden</hi> attempted; <hi>Venice</hi> conſpired; <hi>Piemont</hi> aſſaulted; <hi>France</hi> twice cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted into Combuſtion, with holy leagues and open Armes: and <hi>England</hi> practiced, and inuaded; And to bee able to doe any, or all theſe, a ſcelerous peace ſought with the <hi>Turke,</hi> to whom, in truth, <hi>Spaine</hi> is only a true friend. Theſe are ſuch a Cloud of witneſſes, as no modeſty will oppugne them.</p>
            <p>Which being now manifeſt to the world, and that it is expected euery wiſe Prince and <hi>State</hi> will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, <hi>nune mea res agitur,</hi> I alſo haue preſumed to warne <hi>diuiſos ab orbe Britannos;</hi> who being ſeparated from Generall Commerce by the Sea, which is our wall, true Information may bee kept out, as well as Enemes.</p>
            <p>To which purpoſe, without any malignity or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling offence, I muſt looke one age back; For in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Alas, the Kings of <hi>Caſtile</hi> were good Neighbors, and were content not to bee ſupplanted by their owne Moores, mingled with their Subiects, both in houſe and bloud.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60796:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi> hath been the ſpeciall and moſt advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious marke at which this new <hi>Monarchy</hi> hath aymed, ſince <hi>cupido dominandi</hi> outgrew Conſcience, and all lawes of Iuſtice; <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Queene</hi> of the Sea, and <hi>Lady</hi> of Traffique being conquered, halfe of the whole is done. <hi>England</hi> hath more hindered this vnnaturall growth, then all <hi>Europe;</hi> it is then out of queſtion, that the wiſedome of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which neuer erreth in the way of greatneſſe, loues and hates no kingdome ſo much, as <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Don Iohn</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> had wonne the famous battaile of <hi>Lepanto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Raphael Pereg.</note> and therein laid to himſelfe a foundation of advancement, and had gotten poſſeſſion of the Citty of <hi>Tunis;</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Councell, foreſeeing the riſing <hi>Starre</hi> of a new <hi>Monarchy,</hi> though in their owne Princes bloud, rather reſolued to raſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy that Towne; and accordingly gaue order to the <hi>Generall.</hi> But hee, who had higher thoughts, fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, and ſollicited the <hi>Pope Pius quintus,</hi> to intercede with the <hi>Catholique</hi> king, that the Title of that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome might bee conferred vpon him, to erect a freſh <hi>oppoſite</hi> to the <hi>Ottoman Empire.</hi> The king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> iealous of any Concurrent, vtterly refuſed this honor to his owne Brother: and ſuddenly, to exerciſe his great mind vpon ſome ſubiect of his priuat ſeruice, ſent him <hi>Gouernour</hi> into <hi>Flanders,</hi> where hee was as like to breake, as riſe; The young Prince, whoſe fahers bloud boiled in his veynes, diſcontent to bee ſhut vp in ſo narrow a Compaſſe, fell vpon a net. practiſe, to conquer <hi>England,</hi> and procured ſo farre with the ſame Pope, that he dealt earneſtly with the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60796:5"/>Catholique King, to conſent to that Enterpriſe, and to contribute Aydes for the Execution, in fauour whereof his <hi>Holineſs</hi> had already granted him <hi>Bulls, Breues, Money,</hi> and the <hi>ſecret Inueſtiture,</hi> though this Proiect in the manner was not acceptable to King <hi>Phillip,</hi> that the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould giue that away, without firſt conſulting with him, which hee had embraced in his owne thoughts, yet he yeelded and promiſed to aſſiſt <hi>Don Iohn</hi> in the Inuaſion of <hi>England;</hi> So much more hee thirſted to depriue a <hi>Chriſtian Prince</hi> of an antient Inheritance, then to keepe a great Kingdom, opportunely ſeated to annoy the <hi>Turks,</hi> from his friends, the <hi>Ottomans;</hi> I will not Phyſically conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture what bloud begat this Counſell; but propoſe it, as a worthy and great Conſideration.</p>
            <p>The attempt of the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Medina,</hi> and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible <hi>Armado,</hi> was a fruit of the ſame root; But that the ſword might not ſeeme to cut through all Iuſtice, to corrupt the minds of the ignorant, and to ſatisfie the doubtfull and ſcrupulous, a counterfeit booke; vnder a counterfeit name, was publiſhed,<note place="margin">Dolman.</note> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſing the ſeuerall titles of <hi>England,</hi> and ſeeming to giue euery one their owne right, it cunningly inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates, that the reaſons of the <hi>Infanta Iſabella</hi> were more pregnant then all the reſt, which could not come into queſtion vntill Sixteene Princes ſucceſſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly raigning, were condemned for Vſurpers, one of whom her father had married and by her taken the title of <hi>England.</hi> But God fought for vs; <hi>Tonante in coelis lehouah, &amp; Excelſo edente vocem ſuam, grande,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal: <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; prunae igneae: ita emittens ſagittas ſuas, diſpergit, &amp; fulgura iaculans, fundit illos.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60796:6"/>
            <p>When fained Titles were fooliſhneſſe before God and men, and the Chariot wheels of the Enemy were taken off, outward force not prevailing, <hi>Religion,</hi> and the defence of that, as the laſt refuge and Sanctuary of Ambition, was taken vp, and a holy pretence aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to practiſe <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi> To this end, the Earles of <hi>Deſmond</hi> and <hi>Tyron</hi> were thruſt out, and maintained in defection, againſt their naturall Prince; and as ſoone as their actions were worth the avowing, Aids, and Supplies were openly ſent from <hi>Spaine,</hi> and that Kingdome doubly inuaded, by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie, and Armes. But <hi>Kinſale</hi> is a famous ſepulcher of their honor: that Climate perhaps hauing as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall an <hi>Antipathy</hi> to Cholerique complexions, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truders, as to noyſome and venemous beaſts.</p>
            <p>I purpoſe not to enumerate priuate and clandeſtine minings and machinations: Theſe three notorious examples will proue the general Aſſertion, <hi>That Spaine doth aſpire the ſubiection of Europe by the firſt aſcent of England:</hi> yet to ſhew more clearly the wiles and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Counſells, where with this Deſigne is proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it will be no vnprofitable digreſſion, to reveale to the world the Negotiations of this Monarchy with the <hi>Ottomans,</hi> when eyther it hath beene in want, or fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, or preparing for ſome new Attempt; <hi>Catholique waies, which the Lyon hath neuer trode in the Deſert, nor the Vulturs eye ſeene in the wilderneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is one of the Vaine-glories of <hi>Spaine,</hi> that they hold no correſpondence, nor euer made any peace with the great Enemy of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> calumniating and reproaching all other Princes and States, who, for vtilitie of Trade, maintaine a Civill Commerce with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60796:6"/>them: But wiſe men will diſcerne the fallacy, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene thoſe, who, according to the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the lawes of God and Nations, doe onely traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique &amp; communicate the abundancies of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, with Infidels; and others, who will haue no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change nor intercourſe, but vnder the condition of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding the world, and oppreſſing, by mutuall conſent, of all Princes. And ſuch a Peace and opportunitie the <hi>Spaniard</hi> hath offered, and ſought of the <hi>Emperour</hi> of <hi>Turky:</hi> And if this be not ſufficient, to returne the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominie caſt vpon others; Let it be weighed vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and it ſhall appeare, that all the correſpondence and trade of all the Princes in amity with the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> together, doth not bring to him halfe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and ſecuritie, as the diſſentions and Intruſions of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> wherwith they keepe all <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> in continuall feare, or warre. Wherby that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemie liues in ſafety, and at eaſe, watching ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantages vpon all, indifferently.</p>
            <p>About the time that <hi>Phillip</hi> the ſecond (the holy League to depriue <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of the <hi>Crowne</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> failing him) in the Reigne of <hi>Mehemet,</hi> Grand father of <hi>Morat</hi> now liuing, a certaine rich <hi>Portugall lew, Don Aluaro Mendes,</hi> reſident in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> pretending occaſion to ſend another of his Tribe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Iehuda Serfati,</hi> vpon priuate affaires (but practiſed by the Miniſters of <hi>Spaine</hi>) into that Country; as ſoon as he arriued at the frontire, by the Kings order he was created an Ambaſſador from the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> and conducted in that qualitie to the Court, and a Counſel held, in what manner to giue him audience; His name was already changed to <hi>Don Gabriell di Bona Ventura,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:60796:7"/>his Inſtructions drawne by a <hi>Iunto</hi> for the purpoſe; and thus hee was ſhewed abroad, defrayed by the King, and his Meſſage publiſhed, that hee was imployed to offer Peace and friendſhip from the <hi>Turkiſh Emperour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When this Scene was acted, he was ſent backe with true Letters of <hi>Don Chriſtofero di Mora,</hi> and the <hi>Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Catagna,</hi> to the great <hi>Vizier,</hi> and for his better ſecuritie, a ſafe Conduct and Credance was giuen him, ſigned by the King <hi>Yo el Rey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Paſſing by <hi>Sicily,</hi> by Catholique Order, Forty Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Slaues were deliuered him, to preſent at the Port, in earneſt of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Ottoman</hi> amitie; Letters alſo of credit for good ſummes were furniſhed, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able him to ſpend, &amp; procure anſwer from the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> and fauour of the <hi>Vizier, Mufti,</hi> and other of the great Officers.</p>
            <p>With which Orders and Armes being arriued at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> he vſed all meanes, with all men, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce an acceptance of the Peace, vrging and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating the earneſt affection, and deſire of the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> to conclude it.</p>
            <p>But this practiſe being diſcouered by the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors reſident at the Port, and others not too well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to <hi>Spaine,</hi> the falſhood was made appeare: and <hi>Don Gabriel</hi> by the great <hi>Vizier</hi> was clapt in priſon, as a Counterfeit and Impoſtor.</p>
            <p>In a few moneths this <hi>Vizier</hi> was diſplaced, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other aduanced to his Office, and, as it is a common rule with them, to runne a contrary courſe to their fallen Predeceſſors, without examining the merits or cauſes: this <hi>Iew</hi> was ſet at libertie, and all his actions and Letters approued, as true and authenticall; And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60796:7"/>thereupon Petition made to the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the Negotiation; and by the counſell of the new Miniſters, it was admitted, and accepted, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer granted to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> that ſeeing hee had ſhewed ſo much affection to peace, and to enter into a fineere Correſpondence with the Port, eſpecially by the charitable liberty of ſo many <hi>Mahemetans</hi> freely preſented; that the Gates of the <hi>Ottoman Empire</hi> were alway open to whomſoeuer did ſeeke their friendſhip: and that Ambaſſadors might ſecurely come to treat and conclude it.</p>
            <p>With theſe Letters to the <hi>Catholique King,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to <hi>Don Chriſtofero di More,</hi> and the <hi>Secretary Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagna</hi> from the <hi>Vizier, Don Gabriel</hi> was diſpeeded with two Meſſengers of the Port, by the way of <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachia</hi> to the confines of the <hi>Empire,</hi> purpoſing to take his iourney through <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Rodolphus</hi> being then in warre with <hi>Sultan Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemet,</hi> he was ſtayed, and examined on the Borders; To free himſelfe, he fained that he had Letters to the <hi>Emperour;</hi> whereupon all his papers were ſeized, and ſent to <hi>Prague.</hi> His <hi>Imperiall Maieſty</hi> very diſcontent, and iealous of ſuch Treaties betweene <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky,</hi> without his communication, and in ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncture; gaue order, that the <hi>lew</hi> ſhould be brought to <hi>Vienna,</hi> and kept in cloſe Priſon, vntill he had ſome advice from <hi>Madrid.</hi> The <hi>Catholique</hi> King, finding <hi>diu non latêre ſcelera,</hi> to ſaue the honor of his priuate Deſignes, denyed the fact, forſooke and proteſted the poore <hi>Don Gabriel,</hi> who miſerably there ended his life, <hi>con aſſai mala-ventura.</hi> It may be collected, that the Spaniſh ends of this Treaty were ſuch as durſt not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60796:8"/>abide the light, ſeeing they might not bee truſted to the neareſt friend; and it was iudged great modeſty, to be aſhamed, and the part of a good <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſecret practiſes with <hi>Turkes,</hi> by the mediation of <hi>Iewes,</hi> but of an ill Maſter, to leaue and aband on his Seruant. Such Veſſels in the hands of Princes are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for honor, or diſhonor, as their intereſts counſell them.</p>
            <p>In later times, the extraordinary Ambaſſadors of the <hi>Emperour,</hi> treating at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> the frontire Affaires, and accidentall Breaches, another ouerture was by them made in the name of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the beſt argument vſed was, that the world knew but two great and <hi>Imperiall</hi> Families, <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman,</hi> who if they were reconciled, might make ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diuiſion of <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt:</hi> The reſt, it is more hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie to conceale, then Chriſtianitie to negotiate.</p>
            <p>This laſt yeare a <hi>Bologneſe</hi> was ſent from the Vice-King of <hi>Naples,</hi> in purſuit of the ſame Deſigne; and counterfeit Letters printed in <hi>Spaine,</hi> with a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of impoſſible preſents, pretended from the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> to beg peace, and ſpread abroad, to add reputation to his Armies; as if the world would trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at a ſmoake: And though this Engine returned fruitleſſe, yet <hi>Spaine</hi> is not hopeleſſe. They know the eaſe and aduantage they ſhould draw, by ſecuritie on this ſide, to haue all their Gallies at libertie, to ſhut vp the <hi>Straights,</hi> to hinder traffique, and to ſuccour <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noua;</hi> and their Garriſons of <hi>Calabria</hi> and <hi>Sicily</hi> free, to be imployed in their other neceſſities. And here it cannot be ouer-paſſed, that while <hi>Spaine</hi> did negotiate this Peace, doubting not to effect it, the ſame inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60796:8"/>were imployed with monies and Letters, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the <hi>Coſſacques</hi> (though in preiudice of the Peace of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> allyed to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> by a double mariage) to inuade the <hi>Boſpherus,</hi> that the Armado of the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> might neceſſarily be kept in the blacke-Sea, for defence, whereby the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> by a fine Art, doth enioy halfe the fruits of the Peace, without obtaining it: Theſe are a modell of the wayes and counſels of the <hi>Spaniſh Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> enuied his Brother the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of a <hi>Mahometan</hi> kingdome; and treat vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with the <hi>Turks,</hi> without reſpect or knowledge of the <hi>Emperour;</hi> If he ſollicit the ſeeds of a warre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Poland</hi> and the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> vnder the colour of a peace, without care of the vtilitie of that Crowne ſo neerly to him allyed: It may be concluded, that <hi>ambition of vniuerſall Monarchy, is onely able to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh all obligations, both of Religion and blood:</hi> Becauſe, <hi>Si violandum jus eſt, imperij gratia violandum eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eurip.</note> 
               <hi>alijs rebus pietatem colas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the firſt ſtep to this ſole Empire be the Conqueſt of <hi>England,</hi> as the Deſignes of the Enemy, from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome leſſons are beſt taught, and their Counſells to their owne ends doe clearly demonſtrate, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of diuers <hi>Iunto's</hi> haue laid for a foundation: It is happy for <hi>England</hi> to fore-ſee the blow, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide timely to preuent it: and not be bound to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduantage of making a deſperate Bett, when the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſhall call, and the game irrecouerable.</p>
            <p>Theſe Demonſtrations admitted for true, the next Conſideration will be, by what meanes moſt effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and virtually to worke a iuſt defence; Wherein if
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60796:9"/>the Ends, Counſells, and Wayes, whereby <hi>Spaine</hi> hath in few yeares aduanced, bee obſerued, they will reflect a true light vpon the contrary, how they may be humbled.</p>
            <p>The end of <hi>Spaine</hi> is <hi>Vniuerſall Monarchy,</hi> confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to the <hi>Romans</hi> in all; but the noble contempt of <hi>Treaſons:</hi> Herein, and in Counſells, they haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of vs. It muſt then be concluded to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this end, wee muſt reſolue the like, and purſue it with the like wayes, and Counſells, (except onely the wayes of <hi>Darkeneſſe</hi>) to take from them thoſe ranke parts, which nouriſh this Concupiſcence.</p>
            <p>To diſcouer the right line of this oppoſition, it may be enquired, what <hi>Spaine</hi> did aduance in the laſt warre, in the bleſſed dayes of the <hi>glorious Queene Elizabeth,</hi> either vpon <hi>England, France, Germany, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly,</hi> or <hi>Holland,</hi> and the totall ſumme ſhall be found nothing. Whether they loſt in <hi>Flanders,</hi> or of their owne, is not the queſtion, for the warre was in the end defenſiue, and hee is beaten, that aſſailing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quers not; But that the <hi>Indies</hi> were not able to ſupply, nor appeaſe the mutinies of his Souldiers, nor to pay the Intereſts of <hi>Geneua,</hi> and that they had loſt all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and ſought peace on all ſides <hi>precariè, Hoochstrat,</hi> the <hi>Electo's,</hi> their <hi>Bills proteſted, their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailng Fryars, their owne Ambaſſages</hi> and the <hi>World,</hi> are irrefutable witneſſes.</p>
            <p>To account what they haue gotten in theſe latter yeares of <hi>Peace,</hi> onely by <hi>peace,</hi> beſides the daring ſo bold an Act, as to expell many Millions of inborne Enemies, and thereby raiſing another <hi>Indea</hi> of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for a deſigned warre, at the ſpring tyde of their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60796:9"/>full Coffers, would, if it lay together, make a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent eſtate for a-moderate Prince. Somewhat in this point hath beene touched in a generall enumeration, but particulars do fully inſtruct. <hi>Alarache</hi> in <hi>Barbarie,</hi> to ſtrengthen their South Coaſts of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and to helpe to ſhut vp the Streights of <hi>Gibralterra; Acon,</hi> vnder the <hi>Imperiall</hi> Coulours depriued of the libertie of Conſcience, the <hi>Reformed Magiſtrates</hi> baniſhed, and the Citie reduced to their <hi>Deuotion;</hi> The <hi>non Plus Vltra</hi> of the <hi>Rhyne,</hi> 40 yeares defended, ſlipt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer; and thereby <hi>Weſell,</hi> the Retraict, and Sanctuary of our <hi>Religion,</hi> made the <hi>Spaniſh Garriſon; Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> and the Inheritance of the <hi>Heyres</hi> of <hi>Cleue</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed vnder the title of protection, and kept as a pledge; The <hi>Palatinate</hi> diſtributed to their <hi>Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants,</hi> but the Ports and Fortreſſes of Importance held in hoſtage; And thus <hi>Holland</hi> ſurrounded; The <hi>Valtoline</hi> blockt-vpp; The <hi>Crownes of Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungary</hi> intailed, and the <hi>Nobility</hi> ſpoiled of their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge of free Election; The <hi>Euangeliques</hi> vniuerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exiled and oppreſſed; And all <hi>Germany</hi> trembling vnder the example: <hi>Theſe are the fruits of a Spaniſh peace.</hi> If the ſlumbring Lyon bite ſo mortally, what ſhall hee doe, enraged after his purſued <hi>Prey?</hi> And if in <hi>peace,</hi> contrary to the nature of <hi>peace,</hi> ſuch achieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are obtained, that the ſhip of <hi>Spaine</hi> runne in the night ſo many leagues, while the Pilot ſeemes to ſleepe; It is euident, in <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>Warre</hi> they haue one end of Conqueſt. <hi>Sapiens non ſemper it vno gradu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
               <hi>ſed vna via.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe examples. wee muſt learne <hi>bellum vtiliter inire, &amp; proſequi.</hi> I will not preſume to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60796:10"/>where the <hi>Spaniſh Empire</hi> is moſt ſenſible and weake; but exhibit ſome generall rules, that Riuers are onely to be preuented of their waters, by ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or diuerting their fountaines. <hi>Aegypt</hi> depends vpon the courteſie and payes tribute to the King of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> to giue leaue to <hi>Nilus</hi> to water it. The body is ſooneſt reduced to a conſumption, by deſtroying the <hi>Liuer,</hi> the <hi>Indies</hi> of blood; And then demonſtrate theſe <hi>axioms</hi> by a fewe <hi>Roman and Spaniſh Parallels,</hi> what they did, and what they ſuffered, and leaue the application to Actine men.</p>
            <p>That Princely People had no <hi>Indies,</hi> but their <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; Rome</hi> and the <hi>Senate</hi> was all; while they caried their Armies abroad, they had no returnes but victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and triumph, and they could looſe nothing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept men, that ſold their liues dearely. But when their <hi>Emuli</hi> the <hi>Carthagenians,</hi> diſcouered by their Inuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Sicily,</hi> that their ambition had no limits, and conſidered that while they fought for their owne ground, they could get nothing, but blowes; They reſolued to ſend <hi>Haniball</hi> to the Gates of <hi>Rome:</hi> where he reduced that <hi>Empire</hi> to nothing, but a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of braue old men, prepared to dye in <hi>Maieſtie.</hi> Eighteene yeares this glorious Captaine trode on the ſpoiles of <hi>Italy,</hi> and doubtleſſe had finiſhed that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and in that day,<note place="margin">Hor.</note> in which he turned to <hi>Capua</hi> had ſapped in the <hi>Capitoll, Si quemadmodum ſciret vincere, ſie vti victoria ſciſſet.</hi> From whence grew the prouerbe <hi>Capuam Hanibali, Cannas fuiſſe.</hi> We muſt not truſt in errors, nor hope this Courteſie of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</p>
            <p>When the young <hi>Scipio</hi> reuiued the hearts of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60796:10"/>
               <hi>Romans</hi> by vndertaking the Prouince of <hi>Spaine,</hi> where his Father and Vncle, and ſo many <hi>Legions</hi> were buried, he found three Armies greater then his owne, to oppoſe him. <hi>Vulgaria emnia conſilia, &amp; quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum venire in mentem cuiuſuis poterat, omiſit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Polib.</note> To fight with all at once was impoſſible; to beginne with one deſperate; the other two were at his back, entire, <hi>vincendo, vinceretur.</hi> And fortune muſt not be often tempted; But when he fell vpon the conſideration, that new Carthage was the fountaine from whence all the diuiſions were ſupplied, the Port, and harbour of ſuccours, he reſolued, <hi>omnes vnà aggredi;</hi> by taking that City, to dry-vp the ſtreames at the ſpring head; Thus the Enemies retraict &amp; ſtorehouſe became his, <hi>tota Regio in vna vrbe ſuperata eſt,</hi> and he changed the face of the whole warrc, by one deliberation, and was victorious without the vncertaine tryall of <hi>Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, dubium an vtiliori faelicioriue concilio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, when there was no other way to retire <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niball</hi> out of <hi>Italy,</hi> this fate of <hi>Carthage</hi> vndertooke to tranſport the warre to their own doores: and then, hee that neuer refuſed to fight, treated, ſought peace, and almoſt confeſſed that he was vanquiſhed; then he made that pittifull oration, the moſt inglorious of all his Acts: <hi>Si nunc eſſet integrum, optaturum ſe fore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hanib. ad Scip.</note> 
               <hi>vt neque Romani quicquam vnquam eorum quae ſunt extra Italiam, nec Carthagenienſes, eorum, quae extra Affricam concupiſcent.</hi> To this moderation muſt <hi>Spaine</hi> be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. <hi>Haniball</hi> knew hee might ſafelier haue loſt all his battells within the <hi>Alpes,</hi> then one at the gates of <hi>Carthage:</hi> In them he aduentured nothing, but the ſuperfluity of youthfull blood, which <hi>en gaijetè de
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60796:11"/>coeur,</hi> ſought their deſteny in the field of honour. But now the Common-wealth was at ſtake, and they plaied their <hi>Altars, Liberties, Wiues, and Children,</hi> at one game; <hi>Haniball,</hi> to auoid this deſteny attempted <hi>Italy,</hi> to waſt <hi>Rome</hi> at their owne charges. But <hi>Scipio</hi> had learned that wiſedome of him, which himſelfe could not vſe, and finiſhed at once a double warre: and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> imitating the one part, ſhewes vs the way to take the other; <hi>Spaine,</hi> while it was a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Kingdome threatned no body, and in <hi>Spaine</hi> litle is to be gotten, where me ate muſt be ſupplied, and a victorious Army may ſtarue. Therefore, that not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the roote, it muſt bee ſought from whence this c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills of ambition ariſeth: and as in naturall Bodies, there are other parts, beſides the head and the heart, which being cut off, or wounded, cauſe deſolution, ſo it is poſſible to find a way to weaken that Monſter, which cannot bee killed at one blow.</p>
            <p>Great preparations at mighty expences giue too great warning, are ſubiect to many accidents and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard too much reputation. And if one <hi>State</hi> know any one <hi>Deſigne</hi> that may much annoy the Enemy, it is like the other is not ignorant of their owne weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. Wiſe Gameſters play not all at a Caſt, the <hi>By,</hi> often helpes the <hi>Maine.</hi> Therfore, both rule &amp; exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hath taught vs, that <hi>Spaine</hi> is more eaſily waſted, then any part of their <hi>Chriſtian Dominion</hi> conquered, while the ſtreame of money is open, and vndiuerted. But if this long and ſure courſe threaten alſo a reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall Conſumption, yet that warre in <hi>Europe</hi> will bee moſt profitable for vs, which ſhall be made nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt our owne Kingdome, both for the keeping our
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60796:11"/>forces vnited, and at hand, and for the eaſineſſe of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies in all Euents; and out of <hi>Europe,</hi> by a Roiall Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is not impoſſible at one ſtroke, to behead the <hi>Indies,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To oppoſe them in their Counſels we muſt firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue what they are,<note place="margin">Pierre Mat.</note> 
               <hi>Eſpagne practiquant touſiours ſa vieille maxime de ſe maintenir par la querra de ſes voiſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sedition, ſeparation, and diſunion are the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous weapons wherewith they prepare to themſelues eaſie Conqueſts, and theſe Arts haue their firſt effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vnder the pretence of Treaty, then is the <hi>Spaniard</hi> moſt to be ſuſpected, becauſe they know how <hi>hoſtibus prodere prima belli tempora,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacit.</note> and if they can raiſe any iealouſie, or variance, to remoue any one, all are weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; <hi>rebuſque turbatis, malum extremum diſcordia ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsit.</hi> The contrary then, which is a firme and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant League, is onely powerfull, and able to arreſt them. In the Colleagued warre of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths of <hi>Greece</hi> againſt the vnited power of the <hi>Spartans,</hi> ſome of the Confederates, who lay next the danger, beginning to wauer, this ſentence of their common ſafetie was giuen,<note place="margin">Pelib.</note> 
               <hi>vnicam ſpem ſupereſſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo omnibus, agniſui longum tempus poſsidendi, ſi Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minondae conſilio vſi, omnium temporum, omniumque rerum ſocietatem ſinceram in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er ſe colant:</hi> To hope to diuide <hi>indiviſihile</hi> is loſt labour, the Deſignes of <hi>Spaine</hi> are one, vnited in the head, <hi>in genere generaliſsimo,</hi> the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which cannot be diſtracted. They haue no other maine and important adherent, but the Pope, and his Eccleſiaſticall Dependents, and theſe alſo make but one, and meet in the Center, concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60796:12"/>in common and mingled ends. And they greatly erre, who ſuppoſe, that it is euer poſſible to finde a Pope vnpartiall for <hi>Spaine,</hi> or to fauour any other Prince againſt them. Let <hi>Vrban</hi> the Eighth ſerue for an example, rais'd and fed by <hi>France,</hi> yet fallen to their enemies, <hi>per ragione diſtato.</hi> One freſh and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnant inſtance will diſcouer both this vnitie, and the aduantage of Spaniſh Counſells. When the Treaty of <hi>Madrid</hi> for the liberty of the <hi>Valteline</hi> was not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and roundly preſſed by the <hi>French,</hi> ſome diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties remaining, to prolong the poſſeſſion, the Forts of that Vally were, by conſent, deliuered to the Pope, <hi>tanquam communi Patri in Depoſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſeemed very equall, but the <hi>French</hi> were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-reached; For they hoped vpon the iuſtice of their Cauſe, and that a ſentence would timely be giuen for them, which was impoſſible: For the <hi>Spaniard</hi> was content, that the Depoſition ſhould remaine for euer to his vſe; and he knew that the Pope, by accepting it, was engag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d neuer to ſurrender to the <hi>Griſons,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>ſpirituall</hi> Father could neuer deliuer his Children (behold another title) to the ſubiection and will of Heretiques: and if the <hi>French</hi> ſhould at laſt vſe force, his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> was doubly intangled, both in honor and conſcience, to vnite with <hi>Spaine,</hi> to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his Depoſitation. This the <hi>French</hi> did not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, and fel vpon a diſaduantage to recouer it from the Pope, a matter of dangerous conſequence. Who, at laſt, takes Armes in the Cauſe, as the World knowes. But when both the Pope and <hi>Spaine</hi> ſaw ſuch a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſtorme, and Colleguation, and foreſaw, that there was no remedie but to loſe it by Armes, which being
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60796:12"/>victorious, might quarrell with <hi>Millan,</hi> or finde new obiects of their diſdaine, they reſolued rather to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render it, and to ſeeme to yeeld to Iuſtice. But who muſt doe it? The Pope by no meanes can conſent to deliuer part of his flocke to wolues, ſo his Ambaſſage proteſted in <hi>France,</hi> therefore, by ſecret conniuence and agreement, the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> doth ſuddenly ſeale the old Articles, and makes the Tranſaction before <hi>Barbarini</hi> ſhall arriue, to ſaue the Popes honor: For a temporall Prince may <hi>ſaluâ conſcientiâ</hi> reſtore <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques</hi> to their temporall rights, which the Pope, a higher pretender, ouer ſoule, body and goods, cannot doe. By this cunning they hope to ſeparate the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vnited, the quarrell being, in outward appearance, ended; and by this Intelligence it is euident, that the <hi>Spirituall</hi> and <hi>temporall</hi> ſerue one another, and take turnes, and ſhift Intereſts, for mutuall aduantage. But if examples proue not <hi>categorically</hi> let it be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the <hi>ſpirituall</hi> and <hi>temporall Monarchies,</hi> affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> haue ſuch mutuall intereſt and affinitie, and are ſo woven one within the other, that though natural affection, or other reſpects of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, may for a time retard, &amp; perhaps ſtriue againſt an open declaration, yet when neceſſitie exacteth a reſolution, the eſſence and myſtery of the <hi>Papacie</hi> will preuaile: It muſt forſake father and mother, and cleaue to this double ſupremacie; for <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> muſt ſtand and fall together.</p>
            <p>To proceed, when the <hi>Romans</hi> firſt tranſported their Legions into <hi>Greece,</hi> they were called in by diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to reſtore that ſhew of liberty to a part, which they abſolutely tooke from all <hi>Greece.</hi> Separation and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60796:13"/>diſunion by them fomented, opened a Port to a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, which vnited, was like their <hi>Phalanx,</hi> not to be broken. And certainly this day, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> haue more hope to diuide the Princes colleagued, then to vanquiſh them: To which vſe, they haue two dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Inſtruments, <hi>Money</hi> for the <hi>Traitor,</hi> and a <hi>Pope</hi> for the <hi>Conſcience.</hi> It is obſerued, that <hi>Spaine</hi> will buy Treaſons dearer, then other Nations doe Faith; <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſcelus externum cum laetitia habetur.</hi> And another noteth,<note place="margin">Tacit.</note> that with a bit of parchment, the Pope will reduce any Kingdome to him diſobedient, to the State of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> when the true King <hi>Iohn Albret,</hi> and Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> were expelled,<note place="margin">Pierre Math.</note> 
               <hi>l'excommunication du Pape Iules</hi> 1. <hi>aquant eu plus de forces que les armes de Caſtille.</hi> And they are not aſhamed to glory with <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> another oppreſſor, that the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries gotten with words, are more ſweet then thoſe of the Sword: For euery Souldier can fight, and ſhare the honor, but Arts and deceits of Treaties, are onely proper to the Prince and his Counfell.</p>
            <p>I will not enter into a ſearch of the Treaties of <hi>Spaine,</hi> nor how they are maintained; I will not cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure Equivocation, nor rip vp our owne wounds: onely I may haue leaue to note, that anciently ſome States were branded, there was prouerbially <hi>Fides Punica,</hi> and <hi>Faedus Locrenſe;</hi> and therefore I admoniſh all good Townes, which capitulate to haue no Citta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell built within their walls, to prouide, that none bee built vpon them.</p>
            <p>By what blood, I know not, the Kings of <hi>Spaine</hi> are become heires vnto <hi>Francis Sforza</hi> Duke of <hi>Milan,</hi> of whom, when <hi>Lewes</hi> the Eleuenth of <hi>France,</hi> preſſed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60796:13"/>by the Confederate warre <hi>du bien public,</hi> wherein his brother, the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Caralois,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Bretagny</hi> were engaged, deſired aydes of money, hee ſupplied the King with a good Counſell,<note place="margin">Comines.</note> to agree to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conditions, with any of the League, to disband, or to ſowe a iealouſie among them; preſeruing onely his Armes entire, with which, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were ſeparated, he might humble them ſingly, at his pleaſure; adding, that Princes loſt no reputation, when they attained their ends. The Hiſtory is vulgar, and the ſucceſſe of that aduice, was, the flight of the Duke of <hi>Berry,</hi> the ſtaine of <hi>Charles of Burgundy,</hi> and the beggery of <hi>Bretagny.</hi> I am perſwaded, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted the Doctrine, and would come to an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with any of the Leagues, to diſunite them: and the Breach once made is not eaſily repaired. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in this Coniuncture, they would (if honour would ſuffer it) conſent to make a generall <hi>peace,</hi> vntill Armes were depoſed; But here is the preſent danger, to looſe an opportunity, not to bee recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in many yeares. The Counſell of <hi>Spaine</hi> doth know at how great expence of time, and charge of Ambaſſages, theſe Leagues haue beene compoſing; which once diſſolued, and lulled aſleepe in ſecurity, would ſlowly returne to the preſent perfection. Therefore there is great Caution to be vſed, in giuing eare to the Enchantments of a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Treaty: For ſome lye nearer puniſhment, ſome make eaſier Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, but all ſingly, ſhall feele the reuenge of their particular Intereſts, in the generall offence;<note place="margin">Polib.</note> 
               <hi>Occaſione <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nim inuitati, eos vlium ineunt, qui per occaſionem tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum ipſis nocuer ant.</hi> The truce that <hi>Amilcar</hi> gaue
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60796:14"/>the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem.</note> when the <hi>Inſubrian</hi> and <hi>Alpine Nations</hi> hung ouer them like a Cloud, <hi>Vine patriam retinere ſine periculo potuiſſent,</hi> did more aduance their future <hi>Empire,</hi> then the three Battailes of his ſonne <hi>Hani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball</hi> did hinder it, becauſe hee gaue them leaue to grow, and to haue no Enemy but <hi>Carthage;</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue reſolued, <hi>there is no ſafety in any ſudden ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,</hi> nor profit in accepting waſted Countries, vntill ſome ambitious blood bee let out, and the <hi>Spaniſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls</hi> conſumed, and that <hi>Nation,</hi> and all the World brought to know, that it is poſſible to reſiſt their greatneſſe,<note place="margin">Polib.</note> and to abate their pride, and that in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they are truely humbled. <hi>Hoc igitur, ſi quid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liud qui Remp: regunt ſolicitè obſeruandum memine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint; vt quos animos efferant qui in gratiam poſitis ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micitiis redeunt, aut nouam amicitiam ineunt, ne igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent quando temporibus cedentes, quando victis animis pacis conditiones amplectantur: vt ab illis quidem, ſeu temporum ſuorum Inſidiatoribus, ſemper ſibi caueant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſeeing the end of all iuſt war is a good and ſafe <hi>peace, qua nihil pulchrius, nihil vtilius,</hi> &amp; the meanes thereunto treaty, and the aſſurance thereof, publique faith; when it ſhall be neceſſary to negotiate a recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with <hi>Spaine,</hi> Let it be accepted for a Rule, and foundation, that the one part is neuer ſecure what the other would haue, <hi>eſſe dolum, quia credidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hoſtis,</hi> and when all reaſons of <hi>State</hi> are narrowly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and outward Counſells waighed with <hi>vtil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>honeſtum;</hi> yet there is a ſecret fit to bee reuealed, That the Kings of <hi>Spaine</hi> haue a <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which may approue, or annull all that is, or ſhall bee tranſacted, and dormant diſpenſations, which haue
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60796:14"/>reference to Contingences <hi>in ordine ad ſpiritualia,</hi> to continue or diſſolve all Concluſions: and this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traict is formed like waxe, to take the Impreſſion of the preſent aſpect and neceſſity of affaires.</p>
            <p>In the laſt treaty betweene <hi>France and Spaine,</hi> in which <hi>Amiens</hi> was ſurpriſed, when King <hi>Phillip</hi> ſaw the vigorous reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth to recouer the Townes in <hi>Picardy</hi> by the ſword, and that he had giuen expreſſe Command to the <hi>Preſident de Silerye</hi> to conſent to no Conuention, ſo long as one foote of ground vnſurrendered, remained in the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> conſidering, that the bounds of that Prouince were the entrance into <hi>Artois,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pierre Math.</note> and that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Armies extend their pretences with proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, eſpecially the Title of <hi>Soueraignty</hi> inuiting, and iuſtifying that progreſſe, he conſulted firſt, his <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> for the reſtitution, who, loath to remit any thing of their ſtiffneſſe, interpoſed the reſpects of honour, and ſo it was neceſſary, not to confeſſe ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to keepe them; but the wiſe King, knowing, to contend might draw the quarrell into the bowells of <hi>Flanders,</hi> reſoluing both to preuent the occaſion, and to ſaue his reputation, called his <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> to deliuer their opinion, who concluded, that hee could not by the Lawes of Religion vſurpe, nor dye with quietneſſe of ſoule, if he reſtored not to euery man his owne: and ſo thoſe places were piouſly ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendered, which could not ſafely be maintained; But Conſcience extended no further, then preſent que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            <p>When the ſame <hi>Catholique</hi> King found it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for <hi>Spaniſh</hi> reaſon of <hi>State,</hi> that his own braue and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60796:15"/>eldeſt ſonne ſhould dye, Nature, and honour both, contended againſt the <hi>Sentence;</hi> but obligations were pretended and found, aboue humanity, as the Act was without humanity. The <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and to theſe a <hi>Iunto of Diuines</hi> were added, to reſolue the render Conſcience of a Father, whether hee might with ſafety of Conſcience pardon his owne Child of offences not yet fully publiſhed and therefore for euer ſuſpected.<note place="margin">Idem.</note> Theſe <hi>Ephori</hi> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with weeping eies, <hi>que le ſalut deſon peuple, luy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoit eſtre plus cher, que celuy duſon filz,</hi> and the gea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt fauour the Prince could obtaine, was to chooſe his death, that which was preferred and enioyed by <hi>Caeſar; &amp; facinus intra gloriam fuit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before <hi>Alua</hi> appeared neere <hi>Portugall</hi> with his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, the Duke of <hi>Oſſuna</hi> and <hi>Don Chriſtofero di Mora,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cones.</note> were imploied to buy a party for the <hi>Catholique King,</hi> and they promiſed mountaines of Gold, to withdraw ſome of the Lords from <hi>Don Antonio.</hi> When the kingdome was ſetled, theſe did demand their recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, and pleaded their Contracts in the name, and by vertue of the Kings order: Who remitted them, not to the Counſell of <hi>State,</hi> for they muſt iuſtifie their owne Acts, but to that of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> Who gaue ſentence, that if the Crowne belonged to <hi>Don Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio,</hi> they could not rightfully conferre it vpon <hi>Phillip.</hi> If <hi>Phillip</hi> were the true heire, the Petitioners could not ſell their Allegiance to their owne Prince, for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, ſo that both wayes they were iudged Traytors, and their expected reward was changed into a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pardon. I conclude, Nothing is ſure, without the approbation of this Court of Conſcience; Nothing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60796:15"/>ſo vnſure, as what Law, or equitie is the rule thereof. Therfore, that Peace onely will be ſecure with <hi>Spaine,</hi> which the two Counſells of State, and Conſcience ſhall together reſolue, to be profitable, becauſe neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie.</p>
            <p>To reduce this Diſcourſe to a briefe Concluſion, If right iudgement of all <hi>States</hi> ariſe from their ends; If their Counſells direct the way to diſcouer them, and both being diſcerned to affect Conqueſt, muſt be actiuely oppoſed, leſt they preuaile vpon a ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring modeſtie; If the ends of <hi>Spaine</hi> are apparantly <hi>Vniverſall Monarchy,</hi> and all their Counſells, by Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations, infamous, and vnchriſtian, or by practiſes of fomenting Treaſons, and diuiſions among their neighbours, are directed to attaine that end; If the Pope muſt be alway obſequious for the affinity of their common ends; If there be no ſecuritie of Peace, but in their pouerty: What other reſolution can bee propoſed, then that a liuely warre muſt bee tranſported to that part of the Dominions of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which being ſeparated and cut off, the ancient mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, and naturall conſtitution of that Kingdome may returne, to bee glad to liue in Peace, and cate quietly their owne Figs and Oliues. And becauſe in great diſeaſes, as well blood and ill humours muſt be diuerted, as the main Cure intended; ſo it wil be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, more for expedition then neceſſitie of health, to imitate other States in thrift. <hi>France</hi> in times paſt, had <hi>Scotland, England, Burgundy,</hi> and <hi>Navarre; Spaine</hi> their owne <hi>Moores</hi> and <hi>Barbary;</hi> euery king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome had a back-friend vpon their Enemies. Such may be found vpon the weakeſt ſide of the Houſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60796:16"/>of <hi>Auſtria, Port d'Atras,</hi> drawne from their owne Confeſſions, that though the <hi>Palatinate</hi> be conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Hungary</hi> &amp; <hi>Bohemia</hi> will neuer be ſecure vntill the Hills of <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> be made the Bulwarke of their Empire. But this would be too large a Digreſſion.</p>
            <p>There remaines onely of my purpoſe, to preuent a Queſtion; why I haue choſen to dedicate, by this Epiſtle, the enſuing Tranſlation, to you moſt worthy Senators of the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons.</hi> For this boldnes may be ſubiect to various miſinterpretations. No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will ſuſpect me of ſo great arrogance, as that I hope to teach you any thing you doe not know. But ſeeing your owne wiſedome did firſt foreſee the neceſſity of a warre with <hi>Spaine,</hi> and your owne zeale to the honour of your King, did counſell to vndertake it, I thought ſuch forraine Meditations as theſe, concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with your owne thoughts, might alſo animate and nouriſh in you a ſpirit, and generous Reſolution, vigorouſly to maintaine it. You know how much of the good ſucceſſe of great Actions depends vpon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and they haue aduanced much, who haue gotten opinion. As <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> make their iudgments vpon the firſt minute of time in Natiuities, ſo doth the world prognoſticate of the happy ſucceſſes of Princes, by the firſt coniunctures in their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and their firſt actions abroad: Therefore <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandum famae, nam vt prima ceſsiſſent, fore vniuerſa.</hi> You know,<note place="margin">Tacit. Idem.</note> Monies are the ſinewes of warre, <hi>Neque arma ſine ſtipendijs, neque ſtipendia ſine tributis, haberi queunt.</hi> If you now reſtraine your liberall hand, you expoſe your Prince to diſhonor, and your Country to Conſumption. It is Time onely that will macerate
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60796:16"/>
               <hi>England,</hi> when without traffique and exchange, and that eſpecially of <hi>Germany,</hi> our owne treaſure muſt be exported to pay forraine Armies. <hi>Qui citò dat, bis dat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and it is ill husbandry to doe that ſparingly, which cannot be well done but at once and ſpeedily. It will be time to be thrifty in the members and particulars, when the Head and the whole <hi>State</hi> is ſafe. And if you deferre vntill a lingring warre hath exhauſted you, Remember that which remaines will not ſuffice, becauſe <hi>ſera in fundo parſimonia; non enim minimum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem.</note> 
               <hi>ſed &amp; peſsi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nam remanet.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Seruant <hi>Philo-Britannicos.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:60796:17"/>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:60796:17"/>
            <head>THE REASONS OF the Reſolution lately taken in the <hi>Valteline</hi> againſt the Tyrannie of the <hi>Griſons</hi> and the <hi>Heretiques.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He miſeries of the vnhappy <hi>Valte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line,</hi> are now at laſt ſo notorious; ſo intollerable are the barbarous op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and tyrannies, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants thereof doe ſuffer, as ſlaues vnder the <hi>Griſons,</hi> their pretended Lords and Superiours; that they ought certainly to ſtirre vp great compaſſion in the mindes, and for their reliefe alſo, the force of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and people farre remoued; And ſeeing this, contrary to all expectation and equitie, is not to them adminiſtred; now, that of themſelues, with the meanes giuen them almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from the hand of God, they haue procured to free them from ſo ſharp a bondage, they might beleeue, that for their iuſtification in that action before the World, there nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded no other diligence: Neuertheleſſe, ſeeing the malice of peruerſe Miniſters, the tongues and infernall pennes (with which Tyrants ſerue their owne occaſions) haue too great credit with the vulgar, to obſcure any truth, how cleare ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, to calumniate Innocency, and to procure hatred, it hath beene thought fit, to publiſh this Treatiſe, by which all men may be informed briefly, and truly, that what they haue done, is not onely right, by all <hi>Diuine</hi> and <hi>Humane law,</hi> but
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60796:18"/>worthy to be approued with high praiſes, of men iudicious, intelligent, and well affected to <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> and to be protected by all States and Princes.</p>
            <p>Omitting therefore colours, and artifice of words, proper to thoſe miniſters, who ſtudy nothing, but to deceiue: Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one doth know, that all which a Subiect can pretend, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in <hi>Soule, Life, Honor,</hi> and <hi>Goods;</hi> Of all theſe, nothing remained to the miſerable <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>altelines,</hi> wherein they were not extreamly oppreſſed, and tyrannized.</p>
            <p>Concerning the <hi>Soule,</hi> it is ſufficiently knowne, that the Inhabitants of that Vally were anciently bred, and nouriſhed in the <hi>holy Roman Catholique faith;</hi> That therein, are many beautifull Churches, dedicated to the bleſſed <hi>Virgin,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Saints,</hi> fauoured by God with graces and miracles, and therefore frequented by the deuour concourſe of ſundry Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to the great comfort and benefit of the People, who were by the <hi>Catholiques</hi> to them admitted, in them to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate <hi>Maſſe,</hi> and <hi>Seruices,</hi> for the health of their foules, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the holy <hi>Roman Rite.</hi> But now theſe <hi>Barbarians,</hi> giuen vp in prey, to the moſt peruerſe Profeſſors of euery Hereſie, and particularly of <hi>Caluiniſme,</hi> haue ſo with all their induſtry wrought, that this poyſon hath ſlided, and infected the whole Valley; from whence it may more eaſily ſpread into the bordering parts of <hi>Italy.</hi> And although firſt they did not apparently ſhew to take from the People, the vſe of their ancient religion, yet their actions manifeſtly were thereunto addreſſed; ſeeing by their Decrees, they gaue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to the Heretiques, to prophane the old <hi>Catholique Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> with their Preachings, and Burialls; and doe take away the reuennues left to <hi>Catholique Churches</hi> for Maſſes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offices, which they transferre to <hi>hereticall</hi> Miniſters; That they inforce Catholiques to built them Churches; That they extinguiſh wholly Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction, depriuing the <hi>Catholiques</hi> of the publication of Indulgences, and Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lees, and of Entrance into Orders, taking away all their Goods; and from the Paſtorall Cure of their Biſhop, Not ſuffering any to obey him, nor that he ſhould come to viſit or
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60796:18"/>comfort them; That they permit the Heretique Miniſters o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly to treade downe the <hi>Sacraments</hi> of the <hi>Catholique</hi> Church, and if any oppoſe, hee is ſuddainly, and barbarouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſhed in life and goods; That they exclude out of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ally,</hi> almoſt all the <hi>orders</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> admitting on the other part, indiſtinctly, hereticall Miniſters, of all Nations; That they erect <hi>Seminaries</hi> and lately hereticall Colledges, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning them the profits, tithes, Canonryes, and Benefits taken from the Curates and <hi>Catholique</hi> Church. Of all theſe, there are paſſed <hi>Decrees, Statutes,</hi> and open <hi>Edicts;</hi> And of Caſes particular, there are publique Acts, whereof the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is too freſh, and renewed by moſt cruell death inflicted on <hi>Catholiques,</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> men, in the moſt Infamous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner imaginable. Now what elſe is this, but to vſe manifeſt Tyrannie ouer the ſoules of the <hi>Catholique</hi> Subiects, to take from them thoſe helpes wherewith they aduance their <hi>ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and their way to <hi>Heauen,</hi> and to enforce them to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a new Religion which leads them downe to <hi>Hell?</hi> The cauſe too much declares it ſelfe, there is no neede of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter exaggeration to make it manifeſt, and to ſhew it more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable.</p>
            <p>In the reſt, to demonſtrate the wretched eſtate of the ſaid Vally, it ſhall ſuffice, ſimply to repreſent the maner of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment vſed many yeares paſt; it ſhall be ſufficient to ſay, that it hath beene giuen onely to him that would offer moſt money, without any the leaſt Conſideration of abilitie or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts neceſſary to ſuch a charge; and that the <hi>Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> ſent in apparance to remedy the forepaſt iniuſtice, were of the ſame quality, and ſometimes worſ; Inſomuch that both the one, and the other had for their ayme, and thereto onely did attend, to get their charges, and to heape vp, by all imaginable meanes, ſo much Gold that therewith they might returne to their owne houſes enrich't for euer.</p>
            <p>From hence it proceeded, that the liues of poore Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents were a thouſand waies enſnared, and often taken away with open iniuſtice, at the inſtance of their Enemyes, who with great ſummes of money bought them, and ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>imes
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60796:19"/>after ſharpe Impriſonment, and other torments, hardly were diſmiſſed naked, by the price of all their ſubſtance, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained openly to the Officers without any ſhame, in ſo much ſecurity, that the miſerable oppreſſed, both in life, and goods, durſt not thereof lament.</p>
            <p>By the ſame meanes, the eſtate of the Subiect in Ciuill Cauſes was alwaies in great danger: For the Magiſtrates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing publiquely mercenary, it often happened that ſome did looſe by an vniuſt ſentence dearely bought of the Aduerſary; and others, to preſerue them againſt Iniuſtice, were forced to preſent a great part to the Iudge.</p>
            <p>No Sentence although confirmed &amp; paſſed in Iudgement, whether Ciuill or Criminall, was euer ſecure; becauſe the <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> to dig out money, did renew the trouble to the part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty acquitted, and for a new price did often racall without any reſpect, that which of others, though iuſtly, had beene iudged.</p>
            <p>Safe-Conducts were broken at their pleaſure, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique faith with vaine pretences violated, to depriue life, that by ſuch death, they might enrich themſelues. Lawes and Statutes were not now with arts, and Stratagems deluded, but openly deſpiſed, and trodden vnder foot, as if all had beene freely giuen to them in prey.</p>
            <p>Orphans and Widdows, and others of that Condition, ſo much recommended, both by diuine and humane law to the protection of Princes, and Magiſtrates, as vnable to helpe themſelues, by infamous meanes; did remaine whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expoſed to the auarice of rauening wolues, to the extreame griefe and compaſſion of good men. On the other part, it often occurred, that thoſe wicked men, which had offended others, in life, goods, and honor, being fallen into the hands of Iuſtice, in ſtead of exemplary puniſhment, were for great bribes, ſometimes by vniuſt Iudgement abſolued, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vnder couler of feined eſcape, let free out of priſon to the great oppreſſion and affliction of thoſe, whom they had wronged.</p>
            <p>There were ſeene numbers of infamous perſons, gracious
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60796:19"/>with the officers of Iuſtice, and by them rewarded, onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſerued as Inſtrumets, many and many wayes, to betray the life and goods particularly of Catholiques; From whence did often follow the deſtruction and ruine, now of one, now of another family, alwayes of the moſt ancient, and honorable of the Valley.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, who ſhall well conſider that which the <hi>Sicilians</hi> did for three yeares ſuffer in the <hi>Roman</hi> Common wealth, vnder the gouernment of the infamous <hi>Verres,</hi> ſhall find that the vnhappy <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>altelines</hi> haue endured much more, a longer time from the hands of ſo many, worſe then <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erres;</hi> and perhapps ſhall not find, any other gouernment ſo infamous, and which ſo well reſembles that, as this of the <hi>Griſons</hi> in the Vally, which ſhould more clearely be manifeſted, if it were here ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to repreſent all the Caſes, and their circumſtances one by one, as it was for <hi>Cicero,</hi> handling his Cauſe for ends far different from ours.</p>
            <p>That which makes our Caſe more full of compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is, that when the miſerable oppreſſed, haue attempted the refuge of their <hi>Superiors</hi> for remedy againſt ſo many Tyrannies, and Acts of Iniuſtice; the officers themſelues, haue oppoſed with <hi>ſeuereſt</hi> baniſhments, and impriſonments, thoſe, who for the publike good intermedled, and when it hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, that all Impediments vanquiſhed, the Procurators of of the Vally haue arriued at the Community of the <hi>Three-Leagues,</hi> and haue informed particularly their many, and exceſſiue grieuances; in the end, after hauing receiued, in diuers places, ſuch affronts, that ſcarcely Slaues could ſuffer, they haue reſted deluded, without effect, or any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion.</p>
            <p>Theſe things without doubt, are ſufficient to take away all hope, euer to find, vnder that gouernment, any caſe of ſo many miſeries. But there are other accidents thereunto ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, whereby the Subiects are brought into vtter deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The <hi>Aſſembly</hi> in the towne of <hi>Toſana,</hi> is already noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, which was applied to nothing elſe but the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of good, and <hi>Catholique men,</hi> as well <hi>Griſons,</hi> as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>altelines.</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:60796:20"/>In the <hi>Diett</hi> there called, many baniſhments, and many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall Condemnations were decreed, amongſt which was that againſt <hi>Nicolo Ruſca</hi> Arch Prieſt of <hi>Sondrio,</hi> a Prieſt of moſt innocent liſe, and a true <hi>Martyr</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> tormented and put to death, with all cruelty, and poſſible infamy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other fault, then being a good <hi>Catholique,</hi> &amp; a prieſt. Now theſe Iniuries and Cruelties hauing neceſſitated ſome <hi>Catholique</hi> Communities, to ſeeke redreſſe of ſo many cuill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, vſing their vtmoſt force; they obtained that theſe <hi>Sentences</hi> being reuiewed, were, as barbarous, and moſt vniuſt, reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. But a little time the remedy laſted, becauſe thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſtirred vp by the fury of their Miniſters, and which more imported, moued by the practices and monies of that Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Potentate</hi> (who <hi>per ragion d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtato</hi> makes any thing law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, how contrary ſoeuer to the honour of God, and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his holy <hi>Catholique</hi> faith) returned to reaſſemble in the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Tauos,</hi> where, in their new <hi>Diett,</hi> they haue not onely reconfirmed all the cuills of that of <hi>Toſana,</hi> but added others, making <hi>Heads</hi> of the Perſecution, &amp; Executioners of their Arreſts againſt <hi>Catholiques,</hi> the ſame hereticall Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and by this occaſion their tyrannicall gouernment is ſo viſibly eſtabliſhed, (particularly by the Aſſiſtance and purſe of that <hi>Potentate,</hi> the principall Cauſe of ſo many cuills to the <hi>Chriſtian Common Wealth</hi>) that the Subiects can expect no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but a declination to a worſe Condition, and ſuddainely to arriue at the height and extremity of all cuills, now already approaching.</p>
            <p>Admitting what hath bin already co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pendiouſly deliuered, yet in ſuch maner, that the Reader can neuer apprehend the degree, whereto their tyrannicall gouernment was truely aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended, that ſeeing, as was in the beginning ſaid, all diuine and humane law did permit the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>altelines,</hi> to withdrawe themſelues by all poſſible meanes from ſo great a <hi>Tyranny,</hi> it will appeare ſo cleare to euery one, that it will bee too much vanity to heape vp reaſons, proofes, and authorities, in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in it ſelfe vndoubted, euen when it were diſcuſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene true Subiects, and Vaſſalls, and their naturall and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60796:20"/>
            <p>But now by ſo much more ſhall it appeare lawfull, when two things ſhall bee conſidered; the one, that the ancient <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulations</hi> of the Valley with the <hi>Griſons</hi> (following the end hereof) doe ſhow rather a confederation between them, then a true ſubiection; and doe ſpeake in ſuch ſort, that the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> exerciſed by them in the Valley, is diſcouered to bee a meere vſurpation; particularly, the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>altelines</hi> doe binde themſelues to the <hi>Griſons,</hi> with limitation to things lawful &amp; honeſt; beſides, the obligation is made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyntly to the Biſhop of <hi>Coira,</hi> and the <hi>Three-leagues;</hi> where now, theſe <hi>Tyrants</hi> hauing <hi>de facto</hi> excluded with <hi>Sacrilegious exulation,</hi> their Biſhop, haue alone v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urped that, which neither to them, nor him, was granted. The other thing is, that whatſoeuer the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>altelines</hi> yet haue done, hath beene proſecuted onely with Intelligence and helpe of the founder part of the <hi>Griſons</hi> themſelues, and nor to rebell againſt their <hi>Lords</hi> (for ſuch certainly the <hi>Three-Leagus</hi> neuer were) but ſimply to reduce themſelues to the true State declared in their <hi>Capitulations,</hi> ſo far forth as the mutations, alterations, and other Accidents would permit them.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Agreements between the Biſhop of <hi>Coira,</hi> and the Community of the Three Leagues of the one part: and of the <hi>Valtoline</hi> of the other, in the yeare 1513. Which appeare by the indented Inſtrument at <hi>Iant</hi> of the <hi>Griſon League,</hi> kept in the Rolls of <hi>Coira.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PRimò,</hi> quod homines vallis Tollinae, &amp; Communitatis Tily ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lint, &amp; debeant Renerendiſſime Domino Epiſcopo Curienſi, &amp; tribus Lighis, perpetuis tempor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bus, in omnibus &amp; ſingulis licitis, &amp; honeſtis parere, &amp; obedire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secundò,</hi> quod praelibati homines vallis Tellinae, &amp; Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis Tili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſint, &amp; eſſe debeant, noſtri Vlz: Reuerendiſſims Domini Epiſcopi Curienſis. &amp; omnium trium Ligarum cari, &amp; fideles Confaederati, &amp; tales permanere &amp; pro tempore quo neceſſe fuerit,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60796:21"/>ad Dietas noſtras vocari, in Concilsjs pariformiter ſeders, &amp; em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulere omne id, quod eis Communitatibus magis expediens viddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: &amp; quando ad Dietas ſic, &amp; pront ſupra, vocabuntur, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> debeant de quolibet Tertierio, &amp; Communitate Tillij, vnum mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere Conſiliarium.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertiò,</hi> quod homines vallis, Tellinae &amp; Communitatis Tilij, gaudeant &amp; vtantur coru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priniligijs &amp; antiquis conſuetudinibu, ſiſaltem fuerint de iure laudabiles &amp; Deoconſonae.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quartò,</hi> quod praelibatus Reuerendiſs. D. Epiſcopus Curieuſis, &amp; omnes Lighaeſint &amp; eſſe debeant, dictis hominibus vallis Tellina &amp; Communitatis Tilij, adiutorie &amp; conſilio erga Caeſaream Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itſtatem &amp; Ducatum Mediolans, aut alibi, vbicunque oportuerit, &amp; liberi fiant à taleis, &amp; ſimilibus, vti homines trium Ligarum.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quintò,</hi> quod homines vallis Tellinae, &amp; Communitatis Tilij teneantur, ſingulis annis dare, &amp; ſoluere Reuerendiſſimo Epiſcope Curienſi, &amp; omnsbus tribus foederibus, Tainenſes mille, in promptis denarijs, perſoluendos per quemlibet, ſeu quoſlsbet, habentes bona in dicta Valle ad ratam bonorum ſuorum, exemptum, &amp; non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptum.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:60796:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>TO THE MOST MIGHTY</hi> CATHOLIQVE King of Spaine D. PHILIP THE THIRD.</head>
               <head type="sub">Sacred, Royall, Catholique Maieſtie:</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Manifeſt printed in the name of the <hi>Valteline,</hi> wherein the Reaſons of the Reſolutions, lately by them taken againſt the tyra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny of the <hi>Griſons,</hi> and <hi>Heretiques,</hi> are alledged, hath giuen great ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll to all w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>emen, who ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily doe comprehend from whence, and why it was put to the <hi>Pirſſe,</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>altelines</hi> hauing no notice at all, much leſſe any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Whereupon, hauing propoſed, ſeriouſly to diſcourſe and to bring to light, that truth, which others doe endeanor to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap vp in darkneſſe; I haue thought it an act of Iuſtice, and of no little ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uice to your <hi>Maitſtae,</hi> whoſe minde truly reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60796:22"/>it may be feared, leſt it become deceiued with a falſe apparance of Pietie and Religion, with which the Deuill, a perpetuall enemy of Princes well enclined, vſeth oftentimes to transforme himſelfe into an Angell of light, and to offer his help, as a guide, in the right path of Iuſtice and honeſtie, to no other end, but to draw them without diſcouery, into the crooked way of iniquitie and tyranny. But the better to ground my Diſcourſe, I will beginne ſomewhat high, and imitate that good Architect, who purpoſing to build a ſtrong Tower, by how much he deſigneth to raiſe the top, ſo much lower he layeth the foundation.</p>
               <p>That of <hi>Religion, (ô Sacred, Royall, Catholique Maieſtie)</hi> is certainly a very powerfull obiect, the which, though ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and diſguiſed, euer raiſeth a great commotion in the mondes of them, who there of make profeſſion. For this cauſe many Princes of the world, eyther by the counſell of ill mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, or through the greedineſſe of their owne deſires, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they embrace <hi>Prouinces, Kingdomes,</hi> and <hi>Empires,</hi> and yet not ſatiated, when they want all other iuſt title to make warre, and to ſeize by violence, that which they cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend by Iuſtice, ſuddenly they take the pretence of <hi>Religion,</hi> vnder which Cloake, they doe not onely ſeeke to couer their vniuſt Actions, and to make them appeare lawfull and holy, but therewith they inuite all men to fauour their attempts. Many times alſo with an affection of holy zeale, with true and vnfained Religion, with moſt iuſt and honeſt Titles, they vndertake ſome Enterpriſes truly holy: But the Deuill, who ſtill practiſeth to draw poyſon from the faireſt flowers, and ſerueth himſelfe with good, for an inſtrument of euill; in the end reduceth that very Religion to proper intereſt; that zeale of Pietie hee conuerteth to zeale of Ambition; and the moſt iuſt Titles, hee vſeth to the ſeruice of Tyrannicall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy. Therefore, where ordinarily the queſtion of the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of <hi>States</hi> is handled, a iuſt Prince ought very well to conſider, if hee haue lawfull cauſe, and honeſt right to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe them; and where hee knowes no other Title, then that of Religion, much more hee ought to be aduiſed, that it bee
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60796:22"/>not a faire and honeſt Couer, of a foule and wicked Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Pedro</hi> the tenth King of <hi>Aragon,</hi> and third of that name, hauing raiſed the greateſt forces in his power, paſſed therewith into <hi>Affrica,</hi> to make warre vpon the <hi>Moores,</hi> the ancient enemies of our <hi>Chriſtian Religion:</hi> For which holy purpoſe he receiued great Aides of money from S. <hi>Lewis</hi> the moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King of <hi>France:</hi> What more worthy action could be haue vndertaken? Who would haue found occaſion to blame him? yet vnder the herbe lav hid the Serpent.<note place="margin">Ioſephus Boufi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Hiſt. Sicil. par. <hi>1.</hi> li. <hi>8.</hi> Genzale de Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſcas Hiſt. Pontif. par. <hi>1.</hi> lib: <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>45.</hi> M. Anton. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel. p. <hi>2.</hi> Encad. <hi>9.</hi> li. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> This King had ſometime before ſent into <hi>Sicily Iohn Precita,</hi> who offended by <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Anioy</hi> his Lord, deſired to be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, diſguiſed in the habit of a Fryar, to ſtirre the mindes of that Nation to rebell, who, for ſome ill vſage did ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues diſtaſted with the <hi>French</hi> Gouernment. <hi>Iohn Precita</hi> effected his buſineſſe: The Rebellion of the <hi>Sicilians,</hi> and the deſtruction of the <hi>French</hi> followed. King <hi>Charles</hi> armed for the recouery of his loſt Kingdome, and the Rebells to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him: In the meane while <hi>Poter</hi> of <hi>Aragon</hi> (that ſcarcely hauing touched the Coaſt of <hi>Affrica,</hi> was retyred to <hi>Sardinia</hi> to be nearer <hi>Sieily</hi>) obſeruing the time, and occaſion of his deſigne fitting, ſuddenly went to <hi>Palerme,</hi> where hee was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with great ioy and gladneſſe, and publiſhed, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed King of the <hi>Siciltans,</hi> who flocked to him from all parts of the Iſland. See now your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> with what inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and curſed Art, vnder the colour of Religion, the King <hi>Don Pedro</hi> faining to haue taken Armes againſt the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> tooke that Kingdome from a <hi>Chriſtian King,</hi> and <hi>foedary</hi> of <hi>Holy Church;</hi> and which is more, with the help of that Gold, which he had receiued from the moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King, right Brother of King <hi>Charles.</hi> Whereupon the bleſſed Pope <hi>Martin</hi> the fourth, a man of renowned ſanctitie (of whom, as the <hi>Spaniſh Pontificall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iglieſcas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> and other Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries doe report, were ſeene many miracles after his death) did excommunicate and depriue him of his Kingdomes, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue his Subiects of their Oath of Allegiance, giuing power to any Prince to perſecute him, as a common Enemy. Perhaps
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60796:23"/>the holy Biſhop thought that, with this rigour, the King <hi>Don Pedro</hi> would be brought to acknowledge his error, and to reſtore what he had ill gotten: But it proued without any fruit; for hee which made it lawfull, vhiuſtly to vſurpe the rights of others, did little feare Eccleſiaſticall cenſures for their reſtitution.</p>
               <p>And what more <hi>Catholique,</hi> and more pious Enterpriſe could bee imagined, then that of <hi>India,</hi> for the enlargement or the <hi>ſacred Goſpell?</hi> What iuſter title, then that which the higheſt <hi>Biſhop Alexander</hi> the Sixt did grant to the <hi>Catholique</hi> Kings <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> and <hi>Iſabell,</hi> in the new world; ordeyning them as <hi>ſupreme Emperors,</hi> ouer thoſe Kings and Infidell Kingdomes? But after, what thing was more vniuſt, then the Conqueſt of the immediat Dominion of thoſe Countries? I call it a Conqueſt, to enter with warre, to ſubdue the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, before they were allured with the peacefull voice of preaching, and to take away the life of lawfull <hi>Lords,</hi> and Naturall Princes, to vſurpe their <hi>States,</hi> notwithſtanding they did not hinder the <hi>promulgation</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were ready to receiue the holy <hi>Faith.</hi> And it is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine truth, that when alſo they were not conuerted whilſt yet they did not oppoſe the progreſſe of <hi>Chriſtian Religiou,</hi> they could not be, by the way of warre, ſubiected: that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary to the will of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Specioſi pedes E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelizantium pacem;</hi> And much leſſe could they bee ſpol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of their Dominion, ſeeing the ſame <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when he came into the world, did declare, that the empire alſo of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> is iuſt, &amp; lawfull, commanding euen his own <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to pay tribute to <hi>Caſar.</hi> Neither is it to bee beleeued, that the <hi>Pope,</hi> when hee granted to the <hi>Catholique</hi> Kings, the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign <hi>Empire</hi> of the <hi>Indies,</hi> had any thought to preiudice the immediate Dominion of <hi>Gentile</hi> Princes, becauſe he could not doe it. The which the great <hi>Atabal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a,</hi> King of <hi>Peru</hi> did know by the onely light of nature, to whom <hi>Friar Vincenze di val verde,</hi> made the moſt ſottiſh and abominable oration to reduce him to the holy <hi>faith,</hi> that could be imagined: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Curious things which he ſpake, this was one.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:60796:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>El Papa, que ey biue, did a nueſtro potentiſſime Rey de Eſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Emperader delos Romanos, y Monarca del mundo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jglieſcas p. <hi>2.</hi> lib. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>26.</hi> Sect. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>la con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſta deſtas tierras: El Emperador embia agora Franceſco Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caro à rogares ſeays ſu amigo, y trsbutario: y que obedezeays al Papa, yrecibays la feè de Chriſto, y creays en ella; porque uereys como es ſanctiſſima, y que la que vos agora teneys es mas que fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa. Si eſto todo no hazeys, ſabed, que os hemos de dar guerra: yos que braremos los Idolos; y os for çaremos a que dexeys la Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſtros falſos Dioſes.</hi> That is.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Pope</hi> this day liuing, hath granted our moſt mighty King of <hi>Spaine Emperor</hi> of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and <hi>Monarch</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> the Conqueſt of theſe lands: now our <hi>Emperor</hi> doth ſend <hi>Franceſco Piſaro,</hi> to deſire you to be his friend, and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butary: to obey the Pope, to receiue the faith of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to beleeue therein, becauſe you ſhall ſee, that it is moſt holy, and yours moſt falſe. If you doe not all this, know, that wee muſt make warre vpon you: wee will breake your Idols, and enforce you to leaue the religion of your falſe Gods.</p>
               <p>Who euer heard a holier and wiſer Sermon?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Como ſiel hijo de Dios, que murio per cadauno dellos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Veſceuo di Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appa nel lib del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la deſtructione di India.</note> 
                  <hi>ouiera en ſu lcy mandado, quando dixo,</hi> Euntes docete omnes gentes; <hi>que ſe hizieſſen requerimientos à los inficles paciſices, y quietos, y que tienen fus tierras propias; y ſi no la ricibieſſen, Iuego ſin etra predication, y dotrina, y ſi no dieſſen a ſi melmes al ſenorie del Rey, que nuvca oyeron, ni vieron, eſpetialmente cuya gente y men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaieros ſon tan crueles, tan deſapiadados, y tan horribles Tirannos, perdieſſen per el meſmo caſo, la hazienda, y las tierras, la liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tad, las mugeres; y hijos, con todas ſus vidas, que es coſa abſurda, y eſtulta, y digna de todo vituperio, eſcarnio y infierno.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is:</p>
               <p>As if the Sonne of God, who dyed for euery one of them, had commanded in his holy Law, when he ſaid, <hi>Goe and teach all Nations,</hi> that onely intimation ſhould be made to peaceful and quiet Infidels, which had their proper Lands; and if they did not preſently receiue the Faith, without other preaching, or inſtruction, and ſhould not ſubmit themſelues to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of that King, whom they neuer ſaw nor heard, whoſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60796:24"/>meſſengers are ſo cruell, ſo impious, and ſo horrible Tyrants; that they ſhould loſe, for this onely Cauſe, their goods, lands, liberty, wiues, children, and life; which is a thing vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, abſurd, &amp; worthy of all reproach, infamy, &amp; it Hell ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Thus, wiſely ſpeaking of the ſame matter, though vpon another occaſion, diſcourſeth the Reuerend Biſhop of <hi>Chiap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa,</hi> a principall Citie of New <hi>Spaine</hi> in the <hi>Indies,</hi> called Fiyat <hi>Bartholmy dalle Caſe,</hi> by Nation a <hi>Spanyard,</hi> by birth a <hi>Siuili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> but zealous of Iuſtice, and a friend of truth, in his books of the deſtruction of the <hi>Indies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But returning to our Subiect; The King <hi>Atabaliba</hi> was iuſtly ſcandalized, and grieuouſly moued, at this ſo learned preaching, that anſwering to euery point, amongſt other things he ſaid theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obedecer al Papa no me eſta bien;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jglleſcas vbi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> 
                  <hi>porque dene de ſer loco; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſdà lo que no es ſuyo, y me manda dexar el Reyno que yè heredè de mi padre, y quiere, que yo le dè à qui en no coneſco.</hi> That is.</p>
               <p>To obey the <hi>Pope</hi> is not good for mee, becauſe hee muſt needs be a foole, ſeeing he giueth that to another, which is none of his, and commands me to leaue that Kingdome, which I haue inherited from my father, and would, I ſhould giue it to one, that I know not what he is.</p>
               <p>He could not certainly anſwer more wiſely, according to the Propoſition; which was alſo falſe; Seeing the <hi>Pope</hi> was not ſo void of Iudgement, to haue granted any ſuch conqueſt to the <hi>Catholique</hi> King, or any other, eſpecially by the way of warre, as the holy Preacher with threats, did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme; being in it ſelfe, vniuſt and wicked: And therefore the aforementioned <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Chiappa</hi> carneſtly defending the truth, did ſend vpon this matter thirty propoſitions to the Royall Councell of <hi>India,</hi> printed in <hi>Cinill</hi> in the yeare 1552. In the 23 whereof, he thus ſpeaketh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Soiurgallos primero por guerra,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Veſcoue di Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appanelle. <hi>30.</hi> prepoſitions.</note> 
                  <hi>es ferma, y uia centraria de la ley, y yugo ſuaue, y cargalegera, y manſedumbre de Ieſu Chriſto. Esla propia, que lleuè Mahoma, y lleuaron los Romanos, con que inquietaron, y robaron el mondo. Es la, que tienen oy, los Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, y Meres, y que comenca à tener, el Xarife. Y per tanto, es
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60796:24"/>iniquiſſima, tirannica, infamatiua del mellifluo nombre de Chriſto, cauſatiua de infinitas nuebas blasfemias contra el verdadero Dios, jeentra la religien Chriſtiana; Come tenemes longiſſima experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, que ſe hàeche y oy ſe haze, en las Indias, porque eſtimande Diet, ſer el mas cruel, y mas iniuſta, y ſin piedad, que ay en los Dioſes; y per conſiguiente es impeditiua de la Conuerſion de qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſquiera Infielcs. y que ha engendrade impoſſibilidad de que ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas ſean Chriſtianos en à quel orbe, gentes infinitas.</hi> That is.</p>
               <p>To ſubdue them by warre, is a forme and way contrary to the law, to the ſweet yoke, to the eaſie burthen, and to the meekneſſe of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> It is the ſame which <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and the <hi>Romans</hi> did hold, wherewith they did diſturbe and violate the world; it is the ſame which at this day the <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Moores</hi> maintaine, and the <hi>Verif</hi> doth beginne to practice; and therfore it is moſt wicked, tyrannicall, infamous to the glorious name of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the cauſe of infinite and new Blaſphemies againſt the true God, and <hi>Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as we haue by long experience knowne, to haue beene, and yet, vſed amongſt the <hi>Indians;</hi> For they haue an opinion of God, that he is the moſt cruell, the moſt vniuſt, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs of all other gods. And by Conſequence, it is the hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Conuerſion of all ſorts of <hi>Infidels,</hi> and hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an impoſſibiltie, that multitudes of People ſhould euer become <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the laſt propoſition whereof, he concludes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>De todo lo ſuſodiche en fuerça de conſequentia neceſſaria ſe ſigue, que ſin persuycio deltitulo, y ſenerso ſoberano, que à los Reys de Caſtilla pertenece, ſobrea quel orbe de las Indias, todo lo que en ellas le hà echo, anſi en lo de las insuſtas y tirannicas conqusſtas, como en lo de los repartimientos, y en comiendas; hà ſido nulla y de ningun valor, nefuerça de dereche.</hi> That is.</p>
               <p>From all the fore alleaged matters, it is neceſſarily infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that without preiudice of the title, and Soueraigne Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, which appertaines to the Kings of <hi>Caſtile</hi> in that world of <hi>India,</hi> all that hath beene done, as well concerning the vniuſt, and Tyrannicall Conqueſt, as the <hi>Diuiſions,</hi> and <hi>Commenda's,</hi> is void, of no value, and vnlawfull.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:60796:25"/>
               <p>And in the ſeuenth Rule of his <hi>Confeſſaries,</hi> the ſame good Prelate vitereth theſe words:
<q>Todas las coſas,<note place="margin">Veſcouo di Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appancl Conſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtienario.</note> que ſe han echo en todas eſtas Indias, aſſi cula entrada de los Eſpanoles en cada provincia dellas, como en la ſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion y ſeruidumbre en que puſieron eſtas gentes, con todos los nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dios y fines, y todo lo demas, que con ellas, y cerca dellas, ſe ha cohs, ha ſido contrà todo derecho natural, y derecho de las gentes, y tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bien contra derecho diuino; y por tanto, es todo ininſto, imque, tirannico, y digno di todo fuego inſernal; y por conſeguiente, mille, enualido, y ſin algun valor, ni momento de derecho.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That is:</p>
               <p>All things which haue beene done in theſe <hi>Indies,</hi> as well in the Entrance of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to euery Prouince thereof, as in the ſubiction, and ſeruitude to which they haue redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced this People, with all the meanes, and ends, and all that beſides, which therein, or concerning them, hath been done, is againſt all Law of Nature and Nations, and contrary to the Law of God; and therefore it is wholly vniuſt, wicked, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall, and worthy of Hell-fire, and by conſequence an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilated, inualid, of no force, nor iuridicall power.</p>
               <p>Certainly <hi>(Sacred Maieſtie,)</hi> The Aſſertions of this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late are ſuch, that they ſtrike horror onely in hearing, and almoſt reſemble open Maledictions of a minde ſubdued to Paſſion: But who ſhall diligently reade all his workes, and ſhall conſider diſtinctly euery circumſtance, ſhall clearly know, that theſe are apprehenſions of truth, expreſt with an holy zeale, free from all paſſion, or intereſt, onely in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of right.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friar Bartholomy dalle Caſe</hi> ſpent the moſt part of his life in <hi>India,</hi> Forty nine continued yeares (as himſelfe affirmes) hee ſaw that which therein was done; and Thirty ſoure years he laboured in the ſtudy of holy Lawes, to be well inſtructed in the knowledge of Iuſtice.</p>
               <p>He affirmeth nothing which he doth not learnedly proue.</p>
               <p>All his works were directed to his owne King, and the Royall Councell: before whom more then once hee appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in perſon, to entreat of this Buſineſſa. Who can then
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60796:25"/>beleeue, that hee durſt ſay that which was not apparant truth? Men vſe not to ſpeake ill of Princes to their owne faces. Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the fact, or of the Law cannot be obiected to him, ſo much practiſed, and who had ſo long ſtudyed theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Argument of affection, or of paſſion, cannot be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a Prelat of moſt exemplar life, who renounced his Biſhopricke, onely to aſſiſt in the Court of his Prince, in the defence of a People, from any intereſt in him as farre remoued as our world is diſtant from theirs. From whence of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity it muſt be ſaid, that onely the loue of truth did moue him, and the inuincible reaſons wherewith he maintaines all his Aſſertions, doe moſt clearly demonſtrate it. So that your Maieſtie, who is as much a louer of truth, as of God; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering with a ſetled minde, all the fore-alleadged diſcourſes, will in the ſinceritie of your conſcience, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> beginning was declared; That Enterpriſes vndertaken onely for Religion, are often reduced to proper Intereſt, and that Titles, Dignities, and Authorities, granted, with moſt holy zeale, by the Vicar of Chriſt, haue beaue peruerſly abuſed.</p>
               <p>It is very true, that this good Prelatate hath indeauoured to excuſe the <hi>Catholique</hi> Kings, by ſaying that the aboue mentioned <hi>euills,</hi> were againſt their Intentions, clearely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in many orders, and holy inſtructions, giuen to thoſe crooked miniſters, who obſerued no part of them.</p>
               <p>But this excuſe is not admitted of wiſe men, yea rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed with moſt ſtrong Reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe it hath not beene found, that the Catholique Kings did euer puniſh any of thoſe Miniſters (vnleſſe perhaps ſome for Rebellion) notwithſtanding their wickedneſſe was manifeſt vnto them, which the foreſaid Biſhop doth more then once affirme.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe ſo many iniquities by them committed were neuer retracted; in particular, the Diuiſions of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menda's,</hi> vpon which the ſaid Author doth exclaime, euen to the Heauens.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, becauſe the immediate Dominions are encorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60796:26"/>vniuerſally and particularly with the Supreme Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and this is euident in fact, all faculty being taken from them, which had it to chooſe their Prince; and the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, from them, to whom the eſtates by ſucceſſion did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine; of whom ſome miraculouſly eſcaping aliue, in that deſtruction of the <hi>Indies,</hi> (lamentably by this Biſhop deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed) were tranſported into <hi>Spaine,</hi> leſt by the loue of their Naturall Subiects, they ſhould aſpire to recouer that, of which againſt reaſon, they were depriued. And yet to this day, the <hi>Iſſue</hi> of that great <hi>Motez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ma Emperor</hi> of <hi>Mexico,</hi> doe liue in the Court of your <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> prohibited vpon paine of life, to goe out of <hi>Caſtile</hi> From which moſt true reaſons, the wiſedome of your <hi>Maieſtie</hi> may eaſily compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, how little the aforeſaid excuſes doe pruaile, and how great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Catholique</hi> Kings haue to render to God, of the vſurpation of the immediate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the <hi>Indies</hi> vnder pretence of amplifying the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> faith.</p>
               <p>The religious zeale of the King <hi>Don Phillip</hi> the ſecond, father of your Maieſtie, cannot inconſiderately bee ouerpaſt; when, inurted by the <hi>Pope</hi> hee tooke Armes againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, King of <hi>France:</hi> The cauſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was in queſtion, againſt a publique <hi>Heretique</hi> and Enemy of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> It was expedient that the facred <hi>Catholique</hi> King, Protector of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhould abandon his owne Affaires of <hi>Flanders</hi> to defend that of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The which <hi>Hereique</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (the fruit of perfect vertue, which is rarely found among Princes of the World) did beget, in many, wonder, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulity, and in others, it cauſed too malitious ſuſpition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Algunos</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Biſhop) <hi>que juzgauan la virtud agena por la malitia propia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bauia Pentif. par. <hi>3.</hi> vita di Griger. <hi>14.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>no querian creer, que el zelo de Rey Catholico fueſſe tan grande, che deſamparando ſu bazienda propia, con tan gran coſta fueſſe a remediar la agena.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is,</p>
               <p>Some, who iudge the vertue of others, by their owne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice would nor beleeue, that the zeale of the <hi>Catholique</hi> King could be ſo great, that leauing the care of his owne buſineſs, hee ſhould, at ſo immence Charge, relieue the neceſſitie of others.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60796:26"/>
               <p>Behold the wonder, and the incredulity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Otros</hi> (as after followes in the hiſtory) <hi>que no bien conocian la Religion y Chriſtianidad del gran Filippo II.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bauia p. <hi>3.</hi> vita de Innocentie <hi>9.</hi> C. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>fondauan en eſta jornada un gran edificio, diziendo, que ſe queria hazer Rey de Francia; ò ponelle de ſu mano; aſſegurandoſſe enſus Eſtados comar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canos; y ſasando à bueltas no pequeno interes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is,</p>
               <p>Others that did not well vnderſtand the <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianitie</hi> of the <hi>Grand Phillip</hi> the ſecond, did from this vndertaking lay the foundation of a great building; ſaying that he deſired to make himſelfe King of <hi>France,</hi> or to place a King of his owne dependance, hereby aſſuring his owne neighbouring <hi>States,</hi> and drawing to himſelfe no little ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage.</p>
               <p>Behold the malice, and that truely very great, againſt that moſt innocent <hi>Monarch,</hi> who did clearely ſhow, to haue no other intereſt, nor further deſire, then that the <hi>Catholique</hi> Religion ſhould not be vtterly ruined, as it was freſhly threatned in the Kingdome of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what cannot the <hi>Deuill</hi> doe? <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Heremits</hi> are rarely ſecure, much leſſe Princes in Courts. Scarcely hath <hi>Henry</hi> begunne, inſpired by the holy Ghoſt, to ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſefe willing to be reduced to the wombe of <hi>holy Church,</hi> to be truely a moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King; when the <hi>Catholique</hi> fell vpon a Councell, by no meanes to conſent that hee ſhould bee King of <hi>France.</hi> And yet to him the Rights of that Kingdome did appertaine; nor for other cauſe was the oppoſition, but for being an <hi>Heretique;</hi> whence the impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being taken away, it was moſt vnruſt any longer to withſtand him. But it was whiſpered in the cares of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique</hi> King, by certaine <hi>Machiauells,</hi> rather then <hi>Diſciples,</hi> that the Coronation of <hi>Henry</hi> might bring ſome danger to his Maieſtie for the kingdome of <hi>Nauarr,</hi> and the County of <hi>Burgondy,</hi> vpon which <hi>States</hi> the Crowne of <hi>France</hi> hath pregnant pretenſions; and that his Maieſtie had caſt away in vaine, ſo much Gold, and ſpent ſo much blood of his people in that warre.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:60796:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60796:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:60796:28"/>
               <p>Therefore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>La tarde antes</hi> (ſo ſaith <hi>Rauia</hi>) <hi>que hizieſſe la abſolution,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pontif p. <hi>4</hi> vita de Cle. <hi>8.</hi> Cap. <hi>56</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>el Duque de Seſſa Ambaxador del Rey Catholico, de ſu parte, hiza al Papa proteſtacion, que la abſolucion, que ſu ſantitad penſau a dar à Enrico, no perjudicaſſe al derecho de ſu Rey en lo teccan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te al Reyno de Nauarra, y Contado di Borgona, ui a los gaſtos que hauia echo en la conſeruation della feè Catholicho, en el Reyno di Francia, y a inſtantia y requeſta del: y que no penſaua dexar las armas haſta cobrallos. O yo el pontifice atenta mente la preteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cson; y tomò della el Duque inſtrumento publico. Auertiò an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes à ſua Santitad, de algunos inconuenientes che temia, hauian de reſultar de la abſolucion, que tenia determinado dar à Enrico.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is,</p>
               <p>The Euening before the Abſolution ſhould be giuen, the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Seſſa,</hi> Ambaſſadour of the <hi>Catholique</hi> King, on his behalfe proteſted to the <hi>Pope,</hi> that the abſolution which his Holines intended to giue to <hi>Henry,</hi> ſhould not preiudice the Reaſons of his King, in that which concerned the Kingdome of <hi>Nauar,</hi> and the County of <hi>Bourgundy,</hi> nor in the expence which he had made for the Confernation of the <hi>Catholique</hi> faith in the Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> at his inſtance and requeſt, and that he determined, not to depoſe Armes, vntill he had recouered them. The high Biſhop attentiuely heard the Proteſt, and the <hi>Duke</hi> tooke thereof a publique inſtrument, hauing firſt aducrtiſed his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> of ſome inconueniences which hee feared might reſult from the Abſolution, which was purpoſed to bee giuen to <hi>Henry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Proteſts did appeare, to men of ſound iudgement, ill grounded prentencos, &amp; the alleaged inconueniences falſe foundations of that great Building, which thoſe malicious aboue mentioned did figure to themſelues. They ſaid it was requiſite to the ſtrict <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> which the <hi>Catholique</hi> King profeſſed, (all humane Intereſt depoſed) to aduance with all his ſpirits, the conuerſion of <hi>Henry,</hi> and to exhort the high Biſhop, affectionately to receiue the prodigall Sonne, ſeeing he was returned penitent to his fathers houſe, and to take in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Armes the ſtrayed ſheepe, which hee had now found,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60796:28"/>to carry him to the Sacred ſheepfold of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> They did blame, as a work very little <hi>Catholique,</hi> but rather as a ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the <hi>Deuill,</hi> to attempt the hinderance of that Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which onely hee ought to haue procured, for the quiet of <hi>France,</hi> and the publique good of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> which if it had not ſucceeded, might haue wholly alienated that Kingdome from the <hi>Church,</hi> as the like had done in <hi>England:</hi> They did conſider that it was wide of the purpoſe to feare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny preiudice in the kingdome of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and the County of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> ſeeing the Abſolution did not deriue any more right to <hi>Henry,</hi> then that which any other, which ſhould be King of <hi>France</hi> might haue.</p>
               <p>But aboue all, the pretenſions of the expence made in the warre, did giue them greateſt ſcandall. They diſcourſed; if on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the loue of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Catholique</hi> King had disburſed that money, why was he not content to haue <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor?</hi> But how a <hi>Debtor?</hi> if hee doth enioy of the Patrimony of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> aboue <hi>Three Millions</hi> yearely Reuenue, granted him by the <hi>Vicar</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of <hi>Tenths, Subſidies,</hi> and <hi>Croyſado's,</hi> and other meanes, with condition to employ them againſt the Enemies of <hi>Chriſtendome;</hi> why takes hee nor penne in hand and comes not to a diſtinct Account, of the Receipts and Iſſues, well balancing <hi>il dare, conl'hauere,</hi> and hee ſhall finde himſelfe not Creditor of one <hi>Maranedi,</hi> but certainely <hi>Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> of many and many <hi>Millions,</hi> ſpent, not according to his obligation, for <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but for the intereſt of his owne priuate <hi>Eſtates?</hi> What then doth hee pretend? Why then doth he not lay downe Armes? Vpon what hath hee fixed his thoughts? To what end doth he aſpire? If he proſecute this warre, he proſecuteth an vniuſt warre; How doth that correſpond with the zeale of <hi>Religion,</hi> for which, onely at firſt he vndertooke it? What change is this? Certainely it proceedeth not from the right hand of the moſt <hi>High.</hi> But bee it ſo, let him follow the warre, at his owne pleaſure, there is no remedy, <hi>Henry</hi> ſhall bee abſolued, and ſhall bee King of <hi>France;</hi> Doth the <hi>Catholique King</hi> perhaps hope, with his owne forces, and by ſtrong hand, to depriue him?
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60796:29"/>If he was not able, with the vnion of ſo many other Princes, to hinder him from taking poſſeſſion of his Kingdome, how ſhall he now be able to expell him, hauing ſet ſure footing in his <hi>Throne?</hi> He attempts a dangerous Action. Here they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed with witty and politique Conſideration, that a good iſſue of this warre againſt <hi>Henry,</hi> not enſuing, hee ſhould be ſure to acquire a powerfull, and perpetuall Enemy, that might in time make <hi>Spaine</hi> to tremble within her owne bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els; and the <hi>Propheſie</hi> had well neare beene verified, (the whole world knowes it) if a violent death had not interpoſed to ſtay him. But this yet, which perhaps was foreſeene, they did iudge inſufficient to free <hi>Spaine</hi> of the danger; Seeing the offence of the father, and with the offence, the diſdaine, might deſcend to the Sonne, his Succeſſor, as ſoone as hee came to ripe age, and ſhould fall into conſideration, that the <hi>Catholique</hi> King had done his v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>moſt, to keepe him from being King of <hi>France,</hi> when hee indeauoured to take the Crowne from the head of his father: and that if his father, in deſpight of <hi>Spaine,</hi> mainteined himſelfe King, he alſo in deſpight of <hi>Spaine,</hi> might enioy his fathers Kingdome. But all theſe conſiderations, which certainely were very great, before any other conceiued them, were reſolued by the moſt wiſe King <hi>Phillip,</hi> who by common Iudgement was the <hi>Salomon</hi> of his time; From whence for the ſame reaſons, that others did iudge it requiſite to leaue the warre, hee eſteemed it neceſſary to proſecute it. Seeing he knew he had ſo grieuouſly offended <hi>Henry,</hi> that hee could by no other meanes, ſecure himſelfe from his diſdaine, but onely by oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him to become King of <hi>France:</hi> Wherefore ſeeing the cauſe of <hi>Religion</hi> did ceaſe, it was expedient to faſten vpon ſome other pretence; to reſiſt (with his <hi>Holineſs</hi>) the abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Corenation;</hi> and to proue, if it were poſſible (already reaſon of <hi>State</hi> had inſinuated that <hi>great building</hi> of the <hi>Malicious</hi>) to make a King of his owne faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as he had already cauſed to be propounded in <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tarde ſe deſengana el deſſee de mandar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bauia p. <hi>4.</hi> vita de Clem. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>y ſer Rey; Por este aunque con menos brie, no deſiſtian los pretenſores. Proponia el
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60796:29"/>Duque de Feria al Sereniſſima Infanta de Eſpana Dona Iſabel. Affermaua denerſele el Reyno, porque, hauiendo faltado la linea maſculina de Hugo Capcto, eraquien tenià meior derecho a la Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, como hija de hermana mayor de Eurico III vltimo Rey de Francia Y dezia con eſto, que el Rey Catholico ſu padre, la ca ſarsa con al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>un principe Frances; con que, el nombramiento del tal, quedaſſe en ſu elecion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is.</p>
               <p>The deſire to command, and to bee King, was ſlowly cleared from all doubt: For this cauſe, though with leſſe boldneſſe, the Pretènders gaue not ouer. The Duke of <hi>Feria</hi> did propound her highneſſe <hi>Donna Iſabella, Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spaine.</hi> He did affirme the Kingdom to belong vnto her, becauſe the <hi>Maſculine Line</hi> of <hi>Hugh Capet</hi> being extinct, the beſt title to the <hi>Crowne</hi> was deuolned to her, as daughter of the eldeſt ſiſter of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, laſt King of <hi>France;</hi> And withall, it was ſaid, that the <hi>Catholique</hi> King her father would marry her to ſome Prince of <hi>France;</hi> Prouided, the nomination of that Prince might reſt in his Election.</p>
               <p>Further.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No ſolamente eſtaua prepueſta la Enfanta de Eſpana à la Corona di Francia, ſi no tambien el Archiduque Erneſto de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Auſtria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bauia vbi ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano de Emperader.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is.</p>
               <p>Not only the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> was propoſed to the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> but the Arch-Duke <hi>Erneſtus</hi> alſo, brother of the <hi>Emperour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> Lords did reſt aſtoniſhed at theſe ſo handſom propoſitions, and grew warie of the danger, wherein the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> had entangled them: whilſt hee profeſſed to deſend the <hi>Catholique</hi> Religion in <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Por eſtas razones, yotras, iuntamente con las maquinationes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bauia vbi ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>y negociaciones, que ſe deſcubrian, determinaron en la Aſſemblea, ò Cories, que el Duque de Vmena, como Lugartiniente del Reyno, procuraſſe impedir loſtratos, que y aſe deſcubrian: paraque en nin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guna maneraſe eligieſſe à la Corona Princeſſa ò principe eſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro; anulando qualeſquier tratos, que haſta eſte punto hnuieſſen
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60796:30"/>echo: y que ſe guardaſſen las leyes fundamentales del Reyno, en ls tocante a la elecion de un Rey Chriſtianiſſimo, y Frances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is.</p>
               <p>For theſe and other Reaſons, together with the Machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and practices which were diſcouered, it was determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in their Aſſembly, that the Duke <hi>du Mayne,</hi> as Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Kingdome, ſhould procure to diſſolue the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that already were vnmasked; becauſe by no meanes, a <hi>Princeſſe</hi> or <hi>Prince</hi> Stranger ſhould be elected to the <hi>Crowne,</hi> anulling whatſoeuer Treaty, which to that day had beene begunne; and that the fundamentall lawes of the Kingdom, concerning the <hi>Election</hi> of a moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>French</hi> King ſhould bee obſerued.</p>
               <p>Now, let your Maieſtie ſee, from the contexture of the forementioned matters, to what termes the moſt holy zeale of the King <hi>Don Phillip</hi> your father, was reduced, and how the faire beginnings, for ſincere Religion, were peruerted, onely into an vndue end, of reaſon of <hi>State;</hi> For which alſo, the warre, after the Abſolution of <hi>Henry,</hi> did continue, vntill the moſt bleſſed <hi>Clement</hi> the Eight did introduce the <hi>peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could alledge to your Maieſtie many other examples vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Argument: but I eſteeme theſe three, ſo notable, that they are enough with aduantage.</p>
               <p>There may perhaps bee ſome, who will reprehend me, that I haue onely exemplified in the Kings of <hi>Spaine,</hi> where I might doubtleſſe haue beene furniſhed from Princes of other Nations, and will accuſe me as a man of little Iudgment, and maners, that ſpeaking with your Maieſtie I haue preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to mingle my tongue in the Actions, of the neuer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough praiſed <hi>Don Phillip</hi> the ſecond, your father. I would they ſhould conſider, that domeſtique examples moue much more then forrain; from whence, as noble mindes doe, with all poſſibilitie, endeauour to immitate the Actions worthy, of their famous <hi>Anceſtors;</hi> ſo, by all meanes they doe enduſtriare themſelues, to auoid that, which in their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors was iudged worthy of blame; And, ſeeing that they, though Princes of worth, and eminent vertue, did ſometimes
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60796:30"/>ſtumble vpon vnbeſeeming Actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; they do learne not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume too much vpon themſelues, and to bee very watchfull, not to fall, where others ſlipt; and conſidering, that being their Deſcendents, they ſhould not eſteem themſelues better, but rather worſe, then they; ſeeing in deſcending, nature doth looſe, as vertue doth encreaſe by aſcending. Wherefore, if by nature they are <hi>Deſcendents,</hi> they ſhall grow worſe, and onely aſcending by vertue, they may make them themſelues better. I then, ſpeaking with a <hi>Catholique</hi> King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to admoniſh him of a ſnare, now with ſo much faire and hidden Artifice ſet before him, that eaſily he might fall therein; how could I better doe, then to ſhew him, where his owne Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors, moſt wiſe and <hi>Catholique</hi> Princes, haue fallen head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into like diſorders?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is neceſſary</hi> (ſaid the great <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>France) to ſhew the errors of Princes; that they which ſucceed them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pirre Mathie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: en la vie da M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns: Vill.</note> 
                  <hi>may not erre in the ſame, wherein others did looſe themſelues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I haue then purpoſely taken theſe examples of the Kings of <hi>Spaine,</hi> as more helpefull to your Maieſtie in this preſent matter, then any other, which might haue beene produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and haue euer confirmed them with the Authoritie of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> writers, to auoid the blame, either of falſhood, or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny; And becauſe they may bee of greater credit, and more efficacie, in the ſincere mind of your Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>To whoſe conſideration, I at laſt come to repreſent; That the Riſing of the Gouernour of <hi>Millan</hi> againſt the <hi>Griſons</hi> in the <hi>Valteline,</hi> vnder the like pretence, did apparant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tend to the ſame end though ſhadowed, in the <hi>Manifeſt,</hi> much wide of truth, of which I ſhall now diſcourſe, publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed (as it was voyced) by the people of that Valley, but in truth by the Miniſters of your Maieſtie, of whom, if your Maieſtie be not more then heedfull, you ſhall bee certainly induced to ſuch Actions, that being added to the other three <hi>Narrations</hi> of your Anceſtors, will ſerue for an example to Poſteritie, of an impious and wicked Enterpriſe, vnder a Religious and godly vaile.</p>
               <p>Returning to the Diſcourſe; I ſay, that the cauſes of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60796:31"/>that <hi>Manifeſt,</hi> were <hi>Three.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt, to inſinuate to your Maieſtie and the World, that the People of the <hi>Valteline,</hi> being tyranniſed by the <hi>Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> were of their owne free and voluntary determination, and not by others induced, fallen into <hi>Rebellion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond, to perſwade your Maieſtie and the World, that your Miniſters had iuſtly vndertaken the protection of thoſe miſerably oppreſſed, &amp;, that it was conſonant to the greatneſſe and goodneſſe of a <hi>Catholique</hi> King, not to oban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thoſe,<note place="margin">Sabell. Entad. <hi>9.</hi> li. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> who refuged to his defence; So formerly, <hi>Don Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro</hi> of <hi>Aragon, Non potuiſſe ſe aiebat Siculis indigna fortu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou, opemque ſuppliciter ſuam implorantibus, non auxilio adeſſe;</hi> yet it was hee that ſeduced them into defection.</p>
               <p>The third, to render the poore <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alteliues</hi> by ſo ſhameleſs a writing, ſo odious to their owne Lords, that they ſhould deſpaire, of euer obtayning pardon; whereby they might reſt the more obſtinate in their <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and willing in any ſort to ſubiect themſelues to the Dominion of your Maieſtie, for feare they ſhould returne into the power of the <hi>Griſms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt is cleady expreſſed in the <hi>Manifeſt,</hi> which turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all things to the iuſtification of the rebellion of the <hi>Valtelines:</hi> the other two, which are extracted from the intrinſique thoughts of the heart, might appeare Imaginations of my owne fancy, if the matter it ſelfe did not approue them; But arguing ſecurely, from the effect to the Cauſe, true, and not imaginarie Concluſions may bee deduced: To this then I inuoke, with all my ſpirits, the attentiue mind of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie; for when I ſhall haue demonſtrated, that all the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the <hi>Manifeſt</hi> are ill grounded, and falſe, and what the truth of the buſineſſe is: it ſhall together appeare, that the Cauſes of ſaid <hi>Manifeſt</hi> cannot bee other, then thoſe about ſpecified.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Reaſons</hi> drawne to excuſe the Rebellion of the <hi>Valte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines,</hi> are reduced to two <hi>Heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Tyranny.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vpon theſe are made great Amplifications, but all is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med without prooſe; A manifeſt ſigne, that it is ſpoken without foundation.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:60796:31"/>
               <p>Concerning <hi>Religion,</hi> it is ſaid that the <hi>Griſons</hi> vtterly haue taken from the <hi>Valtelines</hi> the libertie of Conſcience, and haue procured, that all ſhould be infected with <hi>Hereſie,</hi> ſhewing, in euery occaſion, fauour to <hi>Heretiques,</hi> and the contrary to <hi>Catholiques,</hi> vpon ſome of whom, they haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tod moſt cruell and infamous death, onely in hatred of the <hi>Religion.</hi> I repedre not euery particular; It is ſufficient to take this <hi>Maui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> to which all other matters are reduced, and in the <hi>Manifeſt</hi> may be diſtinctly read.</p>
               <p>Conterning <hi>Tyranny,</hi> it goeth painting out a kind of gouernment of the <hi>Griſons</hi> in the <hi>Valteline,</hi> like to that, which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fore <hi>Verres</hi> vſed in <hi>Sirtly</hi> and, to ſpeake more modernly, like to ſome, practiſed as well by the Miniſters of your. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, as of your Predeceſſors in their <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Italys</hi> as by this diſcourſe you ſhall fully vnderſtand; perhaps with ſome notable benefit to your poore Subiects, who are waiting ſome eaſe; from your Roy all hand.</p>
               <p>But before wee diſcourſe particularly in thoſe two points, it is fit to conſider, That the <hi>Griſons,</hi> though diuided in two <hi>Religions, Roman</hi> and <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>golique</hi> (may it pleaſe the diume <hi>Maieſtie</hi> that in time they may all agree in the vaine of the true <hi>Apoſtolique</hi>) yet, in all matters, in reſpect of the publique good of the <hi>State,</hi> thee haue conſtantly ſtood vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the politique Gouernment. With which Concord they haue ſo many yeares maintained themſelues free Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, vndependent of other, and highly eſtemed of all; For which cauſe, wee know with how much diligence and charge many great Priaces haue ſought their friendſhip. But of late yeares, in this part, ſome Miniſters of your Maieſtie, malignant to ſee them colleagued, now with <hi>France,</hi> now with <hi>Venice,</hi> moued with an immoderate zeale of your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice; to which they ſuppoſed that ſuch Confederations might bring ſome preiudice, and iudging it moſt important to your Crowne, that you onely ſhould haue the free paſſage through the ſtraighes of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alreline</hi> into <hi>Germany,</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to all other Princes, they ſhould, at your pleaſure, bee ſhot, haue gone contriuing Inuentions, and inſiduous Artifices, to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60796:32"/>diuide the <hi>Griſons,</hi> as well in the politique gouernment, as in <hi>Religion;</hi> to the end they might eaſily ſtide into vtter ruins.</p>
               <p>To this effect, the late count <hi>de Fuentes,</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Millan</hi> erected that Fort, which to this day beares his name, ſo preiudiciall, as nothing more, to the <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Griſons;</hi> Hauing firſt with money corrupted ſome of the chiefe of that Countrey, to the end, that if the <hi>Lords</hi> would oppoſe themſelues, they ſhould with various Arts be diſturbed; as it came right to paſſe by the labor of <hi>lo: Baptiſta Preueſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peio.</hi> &amp; <hi>Rodolfo Planta, Nichole Ruſea,</hi> and others, noted in the <hi>Manifeſt</hi> of the <hi>Griſons,</hi> of the yeare 1618. Inſtantly after which, <hi>Don Pedro de Toledo,</hi> Gouernor of <hi>Millan,</hi> in the yeare 1617. did attempt to make a perpetuall league with the <hi>Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> vpon Articles molded by the Lord <hi>Alfonſe Caſale,</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of your Maieſtie in that <hi>Republique,</hi> after his owne faſhion; In which there was nothing inſerted in the fauour of the <hi>Griſons,</hi> but a deluſory promiſe to demoliſh the fort of <hi>Fuentes;</hi> where with, it ſeemed to him, that they ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcend to all other things, how contrary ſoeuer to their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettie. The ſame men, who did fauour the building of the Fort, did not faile to aduance alſo this Confederacie, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding many, that by al meanes it ought to be embraced; but the crooked practiſes of theſe Patriots, Enemies of their Countrey, being to the <hi>Griſons</hi> diſcouered, they would not accept theſe <hi>Capitulations;</hi> but forming a Iuridicary, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall Proceſſe, againſt theſe <hi>Rebels,</hi> they found ſo many Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations, treaſons, and other wicked Actions by them wrought, that proceeding to Iuſtice, it was requiſite, with Baniſhments, and death, to giue them deſerued puniſhment: Prom that time, till now, that they remained exiled, aided with money by the Miniſters of your Maieſtie, with which they proceeded, maintayning freſh practices with their friends and adherents, and corrupting many others, they haue ſollicited continually to ſowe diſſention among this people, thereby to raiſe ſome inſurrection, as finally hath ſucceeded in the <hi>Valteline.</hi> The truth of all this is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly collected from the forealleaged <hi>Manifeſt,</hi> of the Actions of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60796:32"/>the <hi>Griſons,</hi> in the yeare 1618. to which Credit cannot bede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied as the Miniſters of your Maieſty deſire, ſeeing the things therein related are matters of fact, and iuridically approued, where theſe affaires haue beene handled without paſſion, or reſpect of perſons; as euery diſpaſſionate mind, by the reading thereof will iudge.</p>
               <p>The intent then of your Maieſties Miniſters was not, to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh a Confederacy with the <hi>Griſons,</hi> which had in bin ſo, they would haue procured by lawfull wayes, &amp; vpon Conditions reaſonable, as other Princes vſed: and not by interuention of particular perſons, corrupted with giſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and vpon Articles, ſo vnſanory, as among them are ſeene. But then purpoſe was, ſo cunningly to frame them, that they ſhould not be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, becauſe being promoued by the factious party of men corrupt, and reiected by the ſound part, diſ-interreſſed, and louers of the publique good, there might ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> a diſcord, ſowed by this art, to caſt theſe people into Confuſion, ſo that from their diuiſion, according to the Goſpell, the deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the <hi>State,</hi> might follow; For the Miniſters of your Maieſtie, fomenting one part againſt the other, did hope to oppreſſe both the one and the other, and highly to merit of you by enlarging, in what way ſoeuer, your <hi>Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Artifice <hi>(O Sacred Catholique Kingh)</hi> to diſunict Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects from their Princes, to ſend them into deſtruction, is moſt proper, and practiſed by the Miniſters of your Crowne; and who would here recount, how often, and in what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, they haue plotted diſunion in the Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> ſhould weaue a large Hiſtorie. The <hi>French</hi> Lords doe well know it, and it is a common opinion amongſt them, who beſt vnderſt and the Affaires of <hi>State,</hi> that if all the <hi>Hugonotts</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> ſhould bee reduced to the <hi>Catholique Religion,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Miniſters would therewith be grieuouſly diſpleaſed; ſeeing that of them they make principall vſe, as of moſt deare friends, to embroile that Kingdome, whenſoeuer they haue any doubt, that the <hi>French</hi> may moue his forces to the dammage of <hi>Spaine.</hi> And they doe glory, not to ſeare at all, the Armes of his moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Maieſtie, not becauſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60796:33"/>the are inualid, but that they know the way to keepeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> buſied, at their pleaſure, in his owne houſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being well conſidered, might produce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>conorary effect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> For, if the moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King ſhall once reſoluo himſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to carry the warne abrond, he ſhall reſt moſt ſcoure, and qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, within his owne Kingdome. The gne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and warlike mindes of the <hi>French</hi> Nobilitio, borne to Armes and Eli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> cannot lie waſting in I dieneſſe; While they haue not elſewhere to bee exerciſed, it is no wonder that at ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they may be eaſily excited to tumults. But if they ſhall bee imployed in fora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Actions, they will ronne greddy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> victorins and glory, of which they are moſt ambitiour. And will deſire, like wiſe men, that their owne Country ſhould roſt in peace, to bee the more able with their Sword to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due others not will they ſuffer themſelues to bee diſturbed by the treacherous ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hinations of them, who affect th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ruine.</p>
               <p>But this is ſpoken by the way, by occaſion of the like ſtratagom at preſent uſed among the <hi>Griſoms;</hi> the which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it hath begunne to take effect in the <hi>Valteline,</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of <hi>Millan</hi> is leapt into the field, not with intent to ſauour, but to opproſſe the party riſen; yet to giue another reliſh, Propoſing ſtill this <hi>axio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> of <hi>Machianell,</hi> that feined Roligion doth much aduantage the Actions of Princer: he would make the world beleaue, that he was moued with <hi>pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio</hi> to take the protection of the miſerable <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>altelines,</hi> oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (as ſaith the <hi>Manifeſt</hi>) in Religion, and politike life. Of which two things, it is now requiſite diſtinctly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Griſons</hi> doe pretend, that if God when hee ereued man, loft him in the ſtate of free will, the Conſcience ought to be free, no man being able to take away that, which is the gift of the <hi>Diuine</hi> Maieſtie. They eſteeme their Condition to be moſt wretched and miſerable, who are violently forced to profeſſe to beleeue that, which their Conſcience truely doth not beleeue: and therefore they require libertie of Religion. They are diuided into <hi>Roman,</hi> and <hi>Euangelique,</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:60796:33"/>euery one follower that part, to which his Conſcience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olineth him. Euery one doth beleeue hee beleeues well, and ſinnes mortally when he doth tranſgreſſe from that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Inſtitution, wherein he was borne and bred: Violence is done to no man. In the publike Gouernment, aſwell the one, as the other, doe participate without any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction.</p>
               <p>Now the Miniſters of your Maieſtie ſay, (as may be need in the Manifect) that the Profeſſers of the <hi>Ramiſh</hi> Religion haue no more libertie to follow their true faith, becauſe the contrary faction doth tyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nouſly oppreſſe them; And h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> they alleage many violent Action<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which if in caſe ſome are true, certainly they are not happened, but for grieuous Iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and offences firſt done by the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> to the <hi>Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques:</hi> but the truth is, that the moſt part of them are falſe, &amp; the effect to this day, hath ſhewed it to be moſt falſe, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the <hi>Euangeliques</hi> did attempt to oppreſſe the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> Vpon which, for better illuſtration, wee will with reaſon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe a little in the fauour of truth.</p>
               <p>Theſe two Factions, <hi>Roman,</hi> and <hi>Euangelique,</hi> either are equall, or the one is ſuperiour to the other, If they are equall &amp; euery one doe perſiſt in their own opinion, (it being certaine that in their <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> called by them <hi>Dritu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> the Miniſters of the one, and the other, equally are aſſiſtant) of neceſſiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it muſt bee ſaid, that when any thing is handled, which doth preiudine the one, or the other, there can noues be any agreement. But ſeeing they doe accord as it appeares by the <hi>Diett</hi> of <hi>Toſana,</hi> in the yeare 1618. in which ſo many <hi>Rebells,</hi> as well <hi>Romans,</hi> as <hi>Euangeliques</hi> without all reſpect were puniſhed; Then it muſt be concluded not to bee true, that they practiſe one to preindice the other Then it is ſalſe, that the <hi>Euangeliques</hi> doe oppreſſe the <hi>Romaniſts.</hi> But who ſhall ſay that the one is too ſtrong, and doth perſecure the other? How is it, that in ſo many, and ſo many yeares, that part hath not vſurped the abſolute dominion? If the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> preuaile, how doe they conſent, that their <hi>Clergia</hi> men ſhould bee chaſtiſed, and as your Maieſties Miniſtem
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60796:34"/>affirme, in deſpight of <hi>Religion?</hi> If the <hi>Euangelique</hi> be ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, how can it ſtand, that putting to death the <hi>Arch Prieſt</hi> of <hi>Sondrie,</hi> and exiling the Biſhop of <hi>Coura</hi> for being of the <hi>Roman Religion,</hi> afterward they admitted another Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and another <hi>Arch-Prieſt</hi> of the ſame <hi>Religion?</hi> And why did they condemne only thoſe two, and not many other good and truely religious men, of which in that <hi>State</hi> there are multitudes? Let it bee then ſaid, not to be a truth, that the <hi>Euangeliques</hi> doe perſecute the <hi>Romaniſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if the aforeſaid Clergie-men haue ſuffered; the treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes by them committed, <hi>in communem patriam,</hi> did cauſe, that, with Common conſent, aſwell of the <hi>Catholique Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> as of the <hi>Euangeliques,</hi> they haue beene puniſhed: as it is notorious by the aforementioned writing of the yeare 1618. And that it was not done in the hatred of <hi>Religion,</hi> may more clearely from this be diſcerned, that amongſt the accuſed and condemned there were many more <hi>Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques</hi> then <hi>Romans.</hi> Whence it is euident, that with all inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie, and without any reſpect, thoſe of the <hi>Euangelique</hi> fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, haue onely aymed, not ſparing themſelues, at the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> And <hi>Rodolfo Planta,</hi> that then was baniſhed, as it knowne to all men, was not onely an <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique,</hi> but a principall <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Heretiques.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With two things about this Subiect the World is greatly amazed and ſcandalized: The one, that the Miniſters of your Maieſtie in the <hi>Manifeſt</hi> printed by them for the <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telines,</hi> haue dared to giue the title of a true <hi>Martyr</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to the <hi>Arch prieſt</hi> of <hi>Sondrio,</hi> a man blood-thirſty, and a Traitor to his Prince; whence it appeares, that onely for being their fauourer, he obtained the merit, to be Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for a <hi>Saint.</hi> The other is, that they haue alwayes held ſo ſtrict Intelligence with <hi>Rodelfo Planta,</hi> and other princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall <hi>Heretiques,</hi> and haue fauoured, and ſtipendiated them, both before and after their Baniſhment, and haue made vſe, and yet doe vſe them continually in matters very inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. Neither doe they make at all ſcruple of Conſcience thereof, though they publikely proclaime themſelues Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60796:34"/>of the <hi>Religion,</hi> and perperuall Enemies of all <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques;</hi> If the wonder and Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>md<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll bee iuſt, I remit it to the Righteous Iudgement, and prudent mind of your Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>I expect, that connicted with the force of theſe reaſons, ſome ſhould ſtep forth, and ſay; That when notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>Euangeliques</hi> doe not leeke to oppreſſe the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> and doe ſuffer euery one to liue to himſelfe, yet by all meane; it is requiſite to extirpate the ill race of <hi>Heretiques,</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to <hi>holy Church.</hi> I vnwillingly enter into this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, but of force the matter requires that ſomewhat therein bee ſpoken. I doe beleeue, and I thinke am not deceiued, that to puniſh <hi>Heretiques,</hi> the Eccleſiaſticall, authoritie is neceſſary; How then will the Miniſters of your Maieſtie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle in that, which to them appertaines not? And who will not ſay, that greedineſſe to vſurpe the <hi>State</hi> of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, doth moue them alſo to vſurp the <hi>Pontiſisall Iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction?</hi> O God if yet they did vſe it well! Holy Church doth continually pray for the extirpation of hereſie; not ſo of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques;</hi> But thoſe Miniſters, with too much exceſſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly zeale, will firſt vſurp the <hi>Eſtates</hi> of <hi>Heretiques,</hi> and deſtroy their perſons, throughly to roote out their hereſies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quidſaeuiunt, vt ſtultitiam ſuam dum minuere volunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lact. ipſt. Diu li. <hi>5</hi> C. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant? longè diuerſa ſunt carnificina, &amp; pietas; nec poteſt, aut veritas cum vi. aut Iuſtitia cum credulitate coniungi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here a Conſideration comes into my head, which makes me aſtoniſhed. The <hi>Euangeliques</hi> among the <hi>Griſons</hi> (ſo your Miniſters affirme, and I beleeue it) are the <hi>ſuperiour</hi> party. Theſe, as wee ſay are <hi>impions, wicked,</hi> and our <hi>Capitall Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> they deſire our harme, and our vtter ruine. They might perhaps, haue beene able, with little difficultie, with their owne force, and with the ayde, of thoſe of <hi>Zurich,</hi> and <hi>Berne,</hi> obliged to them, by loue, by law, and particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federation, vtterly to ruine, deſtroy, and annihilate the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> faction, in their Countrey, and to become <hi>Lords</hi> alone of the whole Dominion: And yet theſe <hi>wicked,</hi> theſe <hi>impious,</hi> theſe <hi>Enemies</hi> of the true ſaith, haue had ſo much humanitie,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60796:35"/>that they haue abſtayned; and haue beene contented, that the <hi>Roman Catholiques</hi> liue freely and quietly among them, and to haue them friends and Companions in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique Gouernment. And thoſe of <hi>Zurich</hi> and <hi>Berne,</hi> no whit better then the <hi>Euangelique Griſons,</hi> haue neuer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, nor counſelled them to Alterations; On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the true Sonnes of the holy <hi>Roman</hi> Church, inſtructed in the meekneſſe, patience, and benignity of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Men charitable, pious, and holy, doe make it lawfull to riſe againſt thoſe, who moleſt them not; to rebell from thoſe, who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them into fellowſhip of Gouernment; to procure the loſſe of <hi>State</hi> to thoſe who being able, haue neuer attempted to expell them out of the <hi>State.</hi> And the Miniſters of your Maieſtie who profeſſe to bee the moſt true <hi>Catholiques</hi> this day liuing in the World, are they, who inſtigate, foment, and ayd, yea who principally doe opperate, in theſe ſo honeſt <hi>Rebellions:</hi> and with warre, fire, and ruines, doe pronounce, that it is requiſite to defend the <hi>holy Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O quam honeſta voluntate miſeri errant;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lactant. vbi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> 
                  <hi>ſentiunt enim nihil eſſe in rebus humanis Religione praeſtantius, eamque ſumma vi opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere defendi; ſed in defenſionis genere falluntur. Defendenda enim Religio eſt, non occidendo, ſed moriendo, non ſaeuitia, ſed patientia, nonſcelare ſed fide; Illa enim malorum ſunt, haec bonorum: &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt, bonum in Religione verſari, non malum; N am ſi ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ſi torment is, ſi malo, Religionem defendere velis, iam non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendetar illa, ſed polluetur, atque violabitur. Nihil eſt enins tam voluntarium, quam Religio; in qua ſi animus Sacrificantis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus eſt, iam ſublata, iam nulla eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Polititians</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">Saluſt. de con. Catil. li. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> that, <hi>Imperium his artibus retinetur, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus initio partum eſt.</hi> So is it conſequent to ſay of our <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> the which was planted, not by killing, but dying, not with crueltie, but patience, not in wickedneſſe, but faith. With theſe Arts <hi>Chriſt</hi> laid the foundation, with theſe the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and thoſe holy fathers of the <hi>Primitiue Church</hi> did build vpon it, and ſince their Succeſſors from theſe wayes haue declined, it is diminiſhed, reſtrayned, and in many places vtterly extinct: <hi>Religion</hi> is more free then the will of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60796:35"/>man, becauſe the forced will, remaines ſtill a will, but enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Religion,</hi> is no more <hi>Religion;</hi> for in the will, the Act is regarded, and in <hi>Religion</hi> the minde: And therefore, <hi>If the mind of the ſacrificer be auerſe, the efficacie is taken away, and annihilated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the Miniſters of your Maieſtie doe erre in theſe their cruell proceedings againſt <hi>Heretiques:</hi> They too farre wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the path in which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath guided them: Let your Maieſtie bee aduiſed, not to ſuffer your ſelfe to bee drawn into the ſame error, by giuing them faculty, &amp; power, to proſecute ſo bloody Enterpriſes. Command them by your <hi>Roiall</hi> authority, to leaue ſo prepoſterouſly to fauour <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion:</hi> For now the world doth know their ends, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe doth hate, deteſt, and abhorre them: And when they ſhall endeauour to perſwade you otherwiſe, bee not eaſie to giue them credit, ſeeing (as I haue already ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) vnder holy pretences, they doe counſell Deuilliſh acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Let your Maieſtie giue full credence to their Aduices, when they ſhall perſwade you to imploy your forces againſt the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> Capitall and continuall Enemies of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie:</hi> when they ſhall ſay, that therein you ought to ſpend thoſe many Millions which you draw from the Church for that holy end, when they ſhall excite you to dreſſe your Fleets and Armies to recouer ſo many Prouinces vſurped by <hi>Infidells</hi> vpon miſerable <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> But why doe I ſay reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them? I tremble (O <hi>Sacred</hi> Maieſtie) to ſpeake it, but it may not be paſſed in ſilence. I feare that they rather will counſell you to take from the <hi>Chriſtians; Arzila</hi> in <hi>Affrica</hi> enforceth me to ſpeake, wreſted from the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Portugalls</hi> by the <hi>King Don Phillip</hi> the ſecond, and giuen to <hi>Muley Achmett,</hi> King of <hi>Marocco.</hi> I well know what they will anſwer, that he gaue it becauſe he could not defend it. But if a King of <hi>Portugall</hi> did keepe it, how can it be, that a <hi>Monarch</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> of the new <hi>World,</hi> and of ſo many other Kingdomes and Prouinces ſhould be vnable? No, no, wee are not deceined: how matters did then paſſe with the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugalls</hi> doth too clearely ſhew the truth, <hi>Phillip</hi> did feare that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60796:36"/>
                  <hi>Muley</hi> might ſuccour <hi>Don Antonio,</hi> who did claime the Kingdome of <hi>Portugall,</hi> wherfore to extinguiſh that <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> King, the Miniſters did perſwade King <hi>Phillip,</hi> with the price of that Citie, to buy the friendſhip of that <hi>Infidell:</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider now your Maieſtie this perfidious Counſell; the which drew King <hi>Phillip</hi> into ſo euill conſiderations, (though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe an excellent Prince) that hee became publikely reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched;<note place="margin">Giou. Hiſt. li. <hi>34.</hi>
                  </note> and it was ſaid, that he had learned this liberalitie to <hi>Barbarians</hi> of the moſt famous <hi>Emperour</hi> his father, <hi>Charles</hi> the ſift:<note place="margin">Iglies. vita de Paolo. <hi>3</hi> lib. <hi>6.</hi> C. <hi>27</hi> ſect. <hi>1.</hi> Giou. li. <hi>37.</hi> Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſ. nel Capit. preditto. ſect. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> who after the Conqueſt of the Citie of <hi>Tunis</hi> in <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barie,</hi> did preſently tender it to the King <hi>Muleaſſes,</hi> which he would not haue done, if it had bin taken from any <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Prince; As he refuſed to reſtore <hi>Caſtelnouo</hi> to the <hi>Republique</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> recouered from the <hi>Turkes,</hi> at the inſtance of that <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and with the ayde of their owne <hi>Armado,</hi> although by particular conuention thereunto obliged. Then againe I ſay, let your Maieſtie take heed of the falſe Counſels of your <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Miniſters; who, where reaſon of <hi>State</hi> is in queſtion, would haue Princes vtterly depriued of Conſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antonio de Leua</hi> diſcourſing,<note place="margin">Gie. Boteras detti memorabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li. l. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> by occaſion, with <hi>Charles</hi> the ſift <hi>Emperour,</hi> concerning the Affaires of <hi>Italy,</hi> did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him to put to death this, and that Prince, and to take poſſeſſion of their <hi>States,</hi> and to make himſelfe Lord of all. The <hi>Soule?</hi> anſwered the <hi>Emperour;</hi> What? replied <hi>Leua,</hi> hath your Maieſtie a ſoule? then renounce your <hi>Empiro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was truly too ſhameleſſe an Impietie of <hi>Leua:</hi> ſuch, I am ſure as none of your Miniſters would dare to propound to your Maieſtie; for knowing the great goodneſſe of your moſt <hi>Catholique</hi> minde, they ſhould be ſure to incurre your Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all Indignation. But it doth not therefore follow, that they preſerue not in their heads the ſame rules, and that they doe not thereby gouerne all their Actions, and thereunto conformable, addreſſe all their Counſells, the which are ſo much more dangerous, in as much as they couer them vnder holy pretences, as at preſent in the warre againſt the <hi>Griſons.</hi> Wherefore your Maieſtie hath ſo much more cauſe to feare,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60796:36"/>and to take heed, and ſo much more reaſon to accept in good part this Aduertiſement.</p>
               <p>But to returne to our Matter; Let your Maieſtie conſider that to puniſh <hi>Heretiques</hi> (as already I haue ſaid) is not the office of a ſecular Prince; And therefore your Miniſters doe ill to put their Sickle into anothers harueſt, and ſo much the worſe be cauſe they know it. And to deceiue the world, they make it lawfull without the <hi>Pontificall</hi> authority, to aduance he ſtandard of the high Prieſt, to iuſtifie a warre which they know to be vniuſt; Wherefore his <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> whoſe Iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is directly offended, ought not, and cannot beare it. And if hee haue, and doe ſuffer many other things; in the end a long abuſed patience is conuerted into a iuſt anger. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, let your Maieſtie be aduiſed, that all <hi>Heretiques</hi> are not to be treated as <hi>Rebells,</hi> with extreame rigour, but onely thoſe, who borne within the wornbe of the <hi>Church,</hi> by their owne malice haue reuolted; theſe which are borne, nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and brought vp in the Sect of their Parents, it is true, they erre, but vnder an excuſe of well doing; they erre it is true, but they knowe not their errour: they are more worthie of Compaſſion then of penalty, they deſerue helpe, and not puniſhment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Multum enim intereſt inter illos qui in ignorantia ſunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſoſt. <hi>1.</hi> Math. Homil. <hi>49</hi> C.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; in ignorantia perierunt; &amp; inter cos, qui in veritate quidem nati ſunt, propter aliquod autem mundiale, ſcientes, ad mendacia tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fierunt, &amp; perierunt in eis, &amp; pereunt. Illi enim forſitan aliquo modo habebunt remiſſionem, iſti antem nullam remiſſionem habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt, neque in hoc ſaeculo, neque in futuro; quoniam ipſi ſunt qui blaſphemauerunt in Spiritum Sanctum; Illi enim iudicandi ſunt, quia veritatem non quaeſierunt, iſti autem condemnandi, quia ſpreuerunt. Leuior enim culpa eſt, veritatem non apprehendere, quam contemnere apprehenſam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let Preachers then be ſent to inſtruct them, let gentle meanes be vſed, that they may hearken vnto them; Let prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be continually made for them, and after leaue the caſe to God, to illuminate them, in the holy faith; ſeeing that faith is the onely guift of God, which he freely giues, not giuen by
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60796:37"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:60796:37"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:60796:38"/>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> nor by the meanes of warre.</p>
               <p>God did command that the Foxes, which deſtroyed the Vines ſhould be taken,<note place="margin">Cant. c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> not ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine; <hi>Capite nobis Vulpes paruulas quae demoliuntur Vineas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Et ſiiuxta allegoriam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Bernard tom. <hi>1.</hi> In Cant. ſer. <hi>46.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Eccleſias, Vineas; Vulpes, Hereſes, ſeu potius Haereticos ipſos intelligamus, ſimplex eſt ſenſus; vt H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci capiantur potius quam effugentur; capiantur dico, non armis, ſed argumentis, quibus reffellantur eorum errores: Ipſi vero, ſi fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eri poteſt, Eccleſiae Catholicaereconcilientur, reuocentur ad veram fidem; haec eſt enim voluntas eius, qui vult omnes homines ſalnos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; ad agnitionem veritatis peruenire:</hi> And a little after; <hi>Quod ſi reuerti noluerit; nec conuictus poſt primamiam, &amp; ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam admonitionem (vtpote qui omninò ſubuerſus eſt) erit ſeeun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Apoſtolum deuitandus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the way <hi>(ô Sacred Maieſtie)</hi> to proceed againſt <hi>Heretiques,</hi> which this holy man doth teach, and not that by the rigor of Armes which your Miniſters practice. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme it a truth, that to vſe crueltie againſt <hi>Heretiques,</hi> doth euer make them more peruerſe; And if this in no place ſhould be done, much leſſe there where <hi>Heretiques</hi> and <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques</hi> are together mingled, with libertie of <hi>Religion;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them for <hi>Religion,</hi> doth teach them to do the like, as well for preſeruation of their own, which they eſteeme as good as we doe ours, as for the ſecuritie of their <hi>States &amp; liues.</hi> From which ſo many loſſes haue hapned to the <hi>Church</hi> of God, that it is a conſideratition worthy of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny teares. <hi>Poore Germany,</hi> into what ſtate is it reduced by this occaſion? which perhaps (but why do I ſay perhaps) cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, certainly, had bin in much better eſtate, if therewith, other proceedings had been vſed. I call not <hi>England</hi> to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the ſtorie is too notorious. What hath rained <hi>Flanders</hi> but a will to introduce with too much rigor, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition? And the Citie of <hi>Naples,</hi> for the ſame cauſe hath it not fallen into generall tumult? which, if it had further proceeded, to day, by Gods grace, it remaines <hi>Catholique,</hi> that perhaps we had found, with all that noble Kingdome, full of hereſie. May it pleaſe the <hi>Diuine Maieſtie</hi> that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60796:38"/>warre againſt the <hi>Griſons</hi> proue not a fire of faith and <hi>Religion,</hi> in all <hi>Italy.</hi> The Deuall hath prepared the wood, the Miniſters of your Maieſtie haue kindled the flame. If preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there be not ſome ready to extinguiſh it, this paper (God make me a liar) which ſome will eſteem fooliſhnes, &amp; others call malignitie, will perhaps be found a Propheſie from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. But of this enough hath beene ſaid; let vs proceed to the reſt.</p>
               <p>The ſecond head of <hi>Tyranny</hi> doth follow: Great matters are related in the <hi>Manifeſt,</hi> printed in the name of the <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telines;</hi> But ſeeing there is not one particular caſe obiected, nor any thing proued, it might be ſaid the whole is falſe; but wee will not vſe that aduantage, becauſe wee know many things are moſt true.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lucio da Monte,</hi> with the money of forraine Princes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied him by <hi>Pompeio Planta,</hi> to the ſumme of two thouſand florens diſtributed among particulars, did procure the office of ſupreme Prouinciall Iudge of the <hi>Griſon League,</hi> bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelfe to adminiſter that charge, not according to right and Iuſtice, and the libertie of his Country, but conformable to the will of the ſaid <hi>Planta.</hi> Whence it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed for truth, that the Gouernment was conferred vpon him, who did offer the greateſt price; that from thence a thouſand <hi>Tyrannies</hi> did proceed againſt the goods and liues of the Subiects, there is no cauſe to doubt: ſeeing this is the way to riches, and he that buyes an office, pretends to haue right to ſell it, in felling Iuſtice; as it was once ſaid of that good <hi>Spaniſh Pope,</hi> who by force of money aſcended to the Chaire, did diſpence for moneyes all <hi>Rights</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Emerat ille prius, vendere iure poroſt.</q>
               <p>Here I could open the eies of your Maieſty with a like abuſe in your own Court, and tell you, that <hi>los Alguaziles,</hi> or as we call them <hi>Marſhals,</hi> or Captaines of <hi>Serieants,</hi> pay for that charge fiue or ſix thouſand <hi>Ducats; Los Eſcriuanos,</hi> or Nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> pay, ſome eighteene, ſome twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60796:39"/>Crownes; <hi>los Alcaldes,</hi> or ſpeaking in our owne Idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oms, the Criminall or Ciuill Iudges doe not pay a certaine ſumme, but they neuer climbe to that degree without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing large donations vpon the Fauorits of your Maieſtie. What may then be ſaid of Gonernours, and <hi>Vice-Kings,</hi> which you ſend into remo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Prouinces? All the Court doth know, and the Prouinces are not ignorant, that no man, <hi>gratis,</hi> doth obtaine theſe honours, but they all paſſe in the Common way. Your Maieſtie may well beleeue, that your Miniſters are not ſo zealous of the <hi>weale publique,</hi> profuſely to expend their owne, to goe and wearie themſelues, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne others, though in the moſt eminent dignitie. Whence you may firmely collect, that they propoſe to disburſe at In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and ſo prouide that the poore Subiects pay them an annuall Tribure, not of fiue, tenne, or twenty, but of a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred for a hundred, and ſometimes a thouſand; and that at the end of their Gouernment, they doe leuell the <hi>Capitall.</hi> I could read in <hi>Cathedra</hi> vpon this matter, as that which I haue ſeene with mine owne eyes, and whereof in part to my great loſſe, haue had experience. But being a publique thing, it behooues not that I wearie my ſelfe therein. I returne then to the <hi>Tyranny</hi> of the <hi>Griſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pompeio Planta</hi> aboue mentioned, did vſurpe the power of Magiſtracie in the <hi>Praefecture of Forſtenau:</hi> binding all the officers not to intermeddle in any Cauſe of Importance without his knowledge, or of <hi>Rodolpho Planta,</hi> his Brother.</p>
               <p>This man, who was <hi>Prouinciall Captaine</hi> of the <hi>Valteline</hi> &amp; <hi>Criminall</hi> Iudg of <hi>Zernez,</hi> &amp; of the bordering Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, did vſurp the power of Magiſtracy of the three <hi>Leagues,</hi> exerciſing therein moſt great <hi>Tyranny</hi> in generall, and againſt particular men, and did arrogate to himſelfe, to iudge the lawes, and to chooſe them onely Iudges, who to him were pleaſing, and whoſoeuer would not concurre with him, was ſodainly depriued; In which courſe, attempting to doe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in the vpper <hi>Agnadina</hi> hee was the cauſe, that ſix per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons did looſe their liues.</p>
               <p>He did falſifie the <hi>Statutes</hi> and ordinances of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60796:39"/>in his Iuriſdiction, adding and diminiſhing them, as to him it turned beſt to accompt.</p>
               <p>He did binde the Subiects in many Communities and free Prouinces with various corruptions and preſents to elect into many offices, men vpon him dependant. Of which his followers, he after made vſe to breake the lawes, to excite Commotions againſt honeſt men, and to gouerne all with violent <hi>Tyranny</hi> at his owne diſpoſition.</p>
               <p>Vpon delicts of little conſideration, hee gaue moſt rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſentences, Conuerting them after into great Ranſoms, to whoſoeuer would redeeme his vexations.</p>
               <p>When he had puniſhed ſome <hi>Delinquent,</hi> he found occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to entangle many Innocents, ſaying, that the guilty had accuſed them of <hi>Confederacy,</hi> or ſomewhat elſe, and enforced them, if they would anoide his perſecution, to compound with him in great ſummes of money.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Agnadina</hi> he did ſharpen the qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrells and factions, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen amongſt Kindred, fomenting them with men and Armes, where of followed many wounds and many deaths.</p>
               <p>What aua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gth it particularly to recount, the <hi>Tyrannies</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for many yeares by him and his Brother in <hi>Agnadina, Valteline,</hi> and other places: And who is able to ſearch the truth of infinite others, practiſed by their adherents and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers? In ſumme <hi>Pompeio,</hi> and <hi>Rodolfo Planta</hi> haue beene Tyrants themſelues, and <hi>Heads</hi> of Tyrants; From them, and by them, all thoſe Cruelties of the people, which in the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt</hi> written in the name of the <hi>Valtelines</hi> are exaggerated, haue proceeded: without contradiction they are too true, we doe not deny them.</p>
               <p>But let it availe to ſpeake the <hi>Truth,</hi> and who, by your fauour, are thoſe but factious men, and Dependents vpon the Miniſters of your Maieſtie? From whom haue they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the monies to ſupport their <hi>Tyrannicall</hi> Authoritie, but of the Miniſters of your Maieſtie? who hath conſtandy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted them in their wicked Actions, but the Miniſters of your Maieſtie? Then it muſt neceſſitily bee concluded that the Miniſters of your Maieſtie are they who haue ſeated <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:60796:40"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:60796:40"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:60796:41"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:60796:41"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:60796:42"/>in the <hi>Valieline,</hi> and in other parts of the <hi>Griſons,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the ſame deſigne aboue mentioned, to breed <hi>Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Diſunion,</hi> and <hi>finall</hi> deſtruction of choſe People, to the enlargement of the <hi>States</hi> of your Maieſtie; and all theſe workings haue beene carried in a manner ſo artificiall, that though the <hi>Griſons</hi> did ſee many things ill done, they could not apply a remedie, becauſe they knew not from whence the euill did ariſe. So great was the <hi>Tyrants</hi> power, that there was none found who once durſt witneſſe a truth. But at laſt when it pleaſed God to bring it to light, the <hi>Griſons</hi> did not neglect to vſe all diligence to dig vp the euill by the Roote. The Brethren <hi>Planta's,</hi> fled, <hi>Conſcions</hi> of their owne Iniquitie, whereby not being able to apprehend them, they were puniſhed in ſuch ſort as was poſſible, by moſt ſharpe exile. Looke vpon the writing ſo often allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, of the Acts of the <hi>Griſons;</hi> where more diſtinctly euery particular may be read.</p>
               <p>But for a domonſtratiue proofe of the aforeſaid matters, all the world doth know, how theſe Brothers <hi>Plantds,</hi> after their baniſhmont, were alwaies ſauoured and ſuſtained by the Miniſters of your Maieſtie; how at their Inſtigation, and with their helpe, they wrought the inſurrection of the <hi>Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teline,</hi> and how, as yet, they negotiate worſe actions.</p>
               <p>Here are three things, fit to be aduiſed your Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>The one, the <hi>Detript,</hi> which is obtruded by your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtera.</p>
               <p>The other, the <hi>Repreach</hi> which they bring to your Roiall name by inſidious Complots, which they alway extend to other Potentates.</p>
               <p>The laſt, is the <hi>Impudonce</hi> wherewith they ſeeke vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily to wound the name and reputation of good Princes, againſt whom they haue often prouoked the Predeceſſors of your Maieſtie, and ſometime your ſelfe, and ſtill doe attempt earneſtly to induce you to actions little reaſonable, making you beleeue, not that they are only luſt, but holy.</p>
               <p>Vpon this firſt we ſhall haue little cauſe of diſcourſe, ſeeing from the fore alleaged matters it is euidently collected, that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60796:42"/>the <hi>Griſons</hi> doe not, nor haue not tyranniſed their Subiects, neither concerning Religion, nor in the politike life.</p>
               <p>That all the <hi>Tyranny</hi> which was vſed in their <hi>State,</hi> was treacherouſly induced by the Miniſters of your Maieſtie, and that the Rebellion of the <hi>Valtelines</hi> was not free and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary in them, but practiſed, procured, and in a manner en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced by thoſe wicked Arts, I haue fully demonſtrated. If then your Miniſters, to promoue your pious and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious minde, to embrace the protection of the <hi>Valtelines,</hi> and to depriue the <hi>Griſons</hi> of their Dominions, would make you otherwiſe beleeue, who knowes not the fraud? who ſees not the deceipt? It is ſuperfluous to enlarge, becauſe it is too manifeſt.</p>
               <p>I come to the ſecond: It is certaine that the actions of Miniſters are attributed to their Princes, and with reaſon, ſeeing it is ſuppoſed that they dare not, cannot, as they ought not, to dee any thing which is not to them either commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or permitted; eſpecially to contriue any great practice, either ſecret, or open againſt other Princes. If then a <hi>Vice-King</hi> of <hi>Naples</hi> hath once ſurpriſed ſome Caſtles of the <hi>Pope,</hi> which after with difficultie were reſtored: If another did rob the <hi>Merchant Gallies</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice,</hi> which yet they haue not reſtored; If a Gouernour of <hi>Millan</hi> did once attempt to take <hi>Caſall</hi> of <hi>Montferat,</hi> a Citie of the Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> by trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the Caſtle of <hi>Breſſe</hi> from the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice;</hi> If ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did leape out to ranſack the land of <hi>Cremaſce;</hi> Another did procure to betray the Citie of <hi>Crema</hi> ſubiect to the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate:</hi> If one of your Ambaſſadours, with intelligence of the <hi>Viee-Roy</hi> of <hi>Naples,</hi> and the Gouernour of <hi>Millan,</hi> did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinate a moſt deteſtable conſpiracie againſt the Citie of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> it ſelfe: If now the preſent Gouernour of <hi>Millan</hi> hath cauſed the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>altelines</hi> to rebell from the <hi>Griſons:</hi> And if all theſe things haue beene done, with the Armes, the men, and the money of your Maleſtie, and in times that you haue profeſſed to bee a good friend both to the <hi>Griſons, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians, Duke</hi> of <hi>Mantua,</hi> and the <hi>Pope,</hi> the world cannot imagine other, but that your Maieſtie hath giuen theſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60796:43"/>From whence it is publikely ſpoken, that the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> doth attend to nothing elſe, but to raiſe <hi>Rebellions,</hi> to contriue Conſpiracies, to ſollicite <hi>treaſons,</hi> to ranſack, rob, &amp; aſſaſſinate his friends. Thus by the meanes of his Miniſters, his <hi>Royall</hi> name, without any his owne fault, is ſtayned with Infamy. I call God to witneſſe, that I thus ſpeake, becauſe I ſo certainly beleeue of your Maieſtie; who deriuing your birth from the moſt noble <hi>German</hi> Nation, which by nature is free, ſingle, and of a minde farre eſtranged from frauds, deceipts, and treaſons, and are deſcended from the moſt famous houſe of <hi>Auftria,</hi> which hath ſtill produced Princes magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, adorned with high valour, and true vertue: It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible that you ſhould euer encline the greatneſſe of your minde to Actions ſo vnworthy. But all men are not able to diſtinguiſh of Nations, nor to know the qualities of Princes; whence the greateſt part, hearing the name of a King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> doe beleene, that it is ſpoken of a <hi>Spauiſh</hi> King, and doe iudge that he alſo is ſuch, or rather worſe, then are his Miniſters. This is an ordinarie forme of Argument. Thus ſpake the <hi>Indians,</hi> when thoſe firſt Conquerours entred among them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Diziendoles, que ſe ſubiect aſſen à elles, hombres tam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanos, iniuſtos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Veſcoue de Chiappa li, de deſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, dellas Indias.</note> 
                  <hi>y crueles en nombre del Rey de Eſpa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognito, y nunca jamas delles oyde, eſtimauan, ſer muy mas iniuſto, y cruel, que elles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is,</p>
               <p>Saying, if they ſhould be ſubiected to them, men ſo inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, vniuſt and cruell, in the name of a King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to them vnknowne, of whom they had neuer heard: they did iudge, that he was much more vniuſt and cruell then they.</p>
               <p>The ſame Argument they made againſt <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> our God;<note place="margin">Veſe. de Chia p. nel. pr. 23.</note> becauſe finding the <hi>Spanyards,</hi> who called themſelues <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to vſe Iniuſtice, and horrible <hi>Tyranny,</hi> they did draw a conſequence, that the God of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (as was formerly ſaid) was the moſt crull, and the moſt vniuſt of all other Gods. Let not your Maieſtie then wonder that your Royall name is, without your fault, but not without cauſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60796:43"/>proiched: neither be troubled, or diſpleaſed againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who haue reaſon much too great, and to the world too too appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, to blaſpheme it. But be grieued and angry at your own Miniſters, who by their euill demeanour giue ſubiect to all, to ſcandalize and abhor it. And in as much as your Maieſtie liues iealous of your reputation, bee pleaſed gratefully to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue this Aduertiſement, which you will know to be moſt important, and may bee vnto you not a little auaylable.</p>
               <p>I paſſe to the third: It is a thing almoſt ordinary with them who practice euill, vnder the ſhew of goodneſſe to make the world beleeue, that others alſo, when they doe good, worke in quitie. For the Actions of the one and the other, being in themſelues contrary, thoſe of wicked men cannot be approued for good, vnleſſe thoſe of good men be condemned for wicked; whence, vpon their reproach, they pretend to build their owne glory.</p>
               <p>The Miniſters of your Maieſtie blame the <hi>Griſons</hi> for pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the Brothers <hi>Planta's,</hi> and other <hi>Rebels,</hi> and calls this chaſtiſement, <hi>Tyranny:</hi> becauſe they would haue it ſaid, that they hauing ſtill ſauoured and ſupported them, had done a iuſt and compaſſionate action; which certainely the graue <hi>Peet</hi> would not haue approued, who wiſely ſaid,<note place="margin">Ennius.</note>
               </p>
               <q>Benefacta malè locata, malefacta arbitror.</q>
               <p>Rather to ſpeake truth, this is the height of iniquitie. <hi>Totius enim iniuſtitiae nulla capitalior eſt, quam eorum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cicer. oſſ. li. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>qui eum maximè fallunt, id tamen agunt, vt viri boni eſſe videantur.</hi> Among Tyrants, to puniſh the good, and reward the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, are acts of iuſtice and pietie: as contrarily to puniſh euill, and reward good men, is eſteemed Tyranny and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Theſe are iuſt the termes, which the Miniſters of your Maieſtie ſpeake, and vſe in this occaſion; while they would make ſhow to doe well in cheriſhing the <hi>Rebels</hi> of the <hi>Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and that theſe haue done euill to puniſh them.</p>
               <p>Now what may the world ſay?</p>
               <p>To this they adde, that the <hi>Griſons</hi> haue exerciſed this Tyranny by the practiſe and money of that neighbour <hi>Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:60796:44"/>who for reaſon of <hi>State</hi> doth make any thing lawfull, how contrary ſoeuer to the honor of God, and the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his holy <hi>faith;</hi> and who is the principall Inſtrument of inſinite euills to the <hi>Chriſtian Common-weale;</hi> Now, who doth not laugh at this ſo fooliſh Calumny? Doubt leſſe the <hi>Griſons</hi> had great need of the practices and moneys of ſome great <hi>Potentate</hi> to puniſh halfe a doren <hi>Rebells</hi> and Traitors, part in priſon, and part fled. And who doth not wonder at ſo much ſhameleſneſſe? It had beene enough, if that <hi>Potemate</hi> vnder the pretence of <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> had done any of thoſe many Villanies which were committed in <hi>India,</hi> to deſcribe him in ſo handſome colours; But who will not praiſe that great modeſty, which would not by name declare that <hi>Potentate?</hi> Truely it deſerned great praiſe, if it were not knowne, that extreame hatred did abhorre to name him.</p>
               <p>But who doth not vnderſtand it? This is that <hi>Potentate,</hi> which was borne in the wombe of the <hi>Holy Catholique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Religion;</hi> This is that <hi>Potentate,</hi> that in twelue hundred yeares hath neuer embraced other faith, other law, then that of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> This is that <hi>Potentate,</hi> who ſince the <hi>Roman</hi> libertie was loft, hath euer maintained libertie aliue in <hi>Italy;</hi> This is that <hi>Potentate,</hi> which alone, with iuſt an honourable titles both by land and Sea, hath largely and gloriouſly extended his <hi>Empire.</hi> This is that <hi>Potentate,</hi> who hath made with his blood, a Counterſcarfe to <hi>Italy,</hi> and with his treaſure ſo many ages, hath and doth defend it from the Rapine of the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Enemies of <hi>holy faith.</hi> This is that <hi>Potentate,</hi> which hates and perſecutes all Tyrants, and loues and protects with all his power, lawfull, and iuſt Princes; for which onely, it ſeemes he is ſo much hated and perſecuted, by the Miniſters of your Maieſtie; <hi>A glorious,</hi> and <hi>renouned Potentate,</hi> whoſe moſt noble Actions, exalted to the <hi>Heauens</hi> with immortall praiſe of the hiſtories of all <hi>Nations</hi> (I doe not decline thoſe of <hi>Spaine</hi>) who diſpaſſionately honor Vertue with Truth, are abundantly known to your Maieſty. From whence you may well comprehend, that if your Miniſters doe ſeck vnworthily
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60796:44"/>to blemiſh that their glorie with defamations, they doe it out of inteſtine hatred, which by naturall inſtinct they beare to all, who are not to them conformable; in one thing onely iuſt, vpright, and ſincere: that they are no Accepters of Perſons, but without any partiality deale alike with all men. And if the <hi>Pope,</hi> the true <hi>Supporter,</hi> vpon whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> our God hath founded his <hi>holy Church,</hi> ſhall not to their will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, they will ſay, that hee is an <hi>Apoſtate</hi> and an <hi>Heretique;</hi> and when yet htey dare not ſo much, vnder other pretences they will call him vniuſt, wicked, Diſturber of the publique peace; they will eſteeme him Enemy, inuade his <hi>State,</hi> ſacke <hi>Rome,</hi> beſeige him in his Caſtle, take him priſoner, impoſe vpon him a grieuous ranſome, as if hee were Slaue and they <hi>Turkes;</hi> They will by neceſſity force him to ſell <hi>Chdlices</hi> and <hi>Groſſes,</hi> to redeeme himſelfe: and not there with content, they will haue Cardinalls in hoſtage, the Caſtle in their power, <hi>Indulgences</hi> for the purſe; and yet more, if more were to be found.</p>
               <p>I durſt not certainly ſay theſe things to your Maieſtie, if in times paſt they had not happened: They did thus han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in the Reigne of <hi>Charles</hi> the fiſt, much againſt the will of that <hi>Religious Emperour, Clement</hi> the ſeuenth and would readily haue done the like vnder King <hi>Phillip</hi> the ſecond,<note place="margin">Iglies. lib. <hi>2.</hi> C: <hi>26.</hi> Sect. <hi>8.</hi> C. <hi>30.</hi> Sect. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of your Maieſtie, when they raiped warre againſt <hi>Paul</hi> the fourth, and tooke from him <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eletri, Tiuoli,</hi> and <hi>Oſtia,</hi> if the King of <hi>France,</hi> truely moſt <hi>Chriſtiun,</hi> had not diuerted their fury, and the <hi>Catholiks</hi> King apprehended a conuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, ſuddenly to accommodate his differences.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sacred Catholike Maieſtie,</hi> if theſe things are all true, as ſurely they are; reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bly it may be doubled, that like acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will proceed from like perſons; wherefore, to the end you eaſilie may, as you earneſtly deſire, vndece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> your ſelfe, and free your name from ſcandall, and other Prinees from cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>moy, and the vnworthy iniuries of your Miniſters, which are the three Aduertiſements by me propoſed, it will not be one of the purpoſe, to ſet before your eyes ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, which vnder your <hi>Empire</hi> are done as lawfull, which
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60796:45"/>by all good <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are held abominable. I implore from a benigne Prince attention, and in attention, benignie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e; ſo that my words may paſſe without moleſtation of your <hi>Royall</hi> mind, that receiuing them with a righteous temper, as they are by mee vttered with hearty affection, I am aſſured they ſhall not end without ſome profit.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Anceſtors</hi> of your Maieſtie haue eſtabliſhed in the kingdome of <hi>Sicily</hi> a ſupreame Monarchy, both in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and ſpirituall; ſo that your <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice-Royes</hi> diſpenſe not onely Offices and Benefices, but alſo Excommunications and Indulgences; and who will then wonder that the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Seſſa</hi> doth publiſh <hi>Iubilies?</hi> The great Cardmall <hi>Baronius</hi> hath fully written vpon this Subiect, and with Euidences in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible ſhewed the vniuſt poſſeſſion of that Kingdome; and that neither your Maieſtie can hold, nor the Pope grant it.<note place="margin">Baron. To. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> If your Miniſters had found the leaſt apparant reaſons, to anſwer and confute the doctrine of <hi>Baronius,</hi> as they did of the paſſage of St. <hi>Iames</hi> into <hi>Galitia,</hi> they willingly would haue done it,<note place="margin">An. Chriſt. <hi>1097.</hi> Vrb. <hi>2.10.</hi>
                  </note> but failing therof, they had recourſe to the fire, and cauſed the E euenth of the <hi>Baronian Annalls</hi> to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely burnt, &amp; did prohibite it vpon grieuous paines, to all your ſubiects: ſo dexterouſly working, that your Maieſtie beleeuing your ſelfe lawfull <hi>Lora,</hi> or at leſt poſſeſſor <hi>bana fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei,</hi> might as you yet continue to vſurpe the ſpirituall iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in that Kingdome; as if betwixt you and the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtecique</hi> iuriſdiction were equallie diuided: What this action may be called, let others iudge.</p>
               <p>But proceeding further, they haue alſo induced your Maieſtie to arrogate, not an equality, but a Supremacy vpon the high Prieſt. So that in the <hi>Cenſunes</hi> which his <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> or his <hi>Nuncio,</hi> or others with his authoritie doe ſend againſt particular perſons into <hi>Caſtile,</hi> theſe men refuge to the Royall Conncell, aggrauating the cauſe of violence, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell doth vſurpe cognition ouer ſuch <hi>Cenſures,</hi> and doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand <hi>defacte,</hi> their ſuſpenſion, vntill the alleadged violence be determined, and vnder this pretence, oftentimes cauſeth an abſolute Reuocation, that in them there is no further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60796:45"/>In <hi>Spaine,</hi> not many yeares ſince were publikely printed bookes of Lawyers that your Maieſtie,<note place="margin">Hieron. Cruelles Tract de Cognit. per viam vie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in cauſ Eccl. &amp; int. perſon Eccl.</note> &amp; your <hi>Royall</hi> Councell hath this authoritie, and may iuſtly vſe it: Which doctrine hath greatly ſcandalized the world, as well for the perſon that wrote it, who profeſſeth to bee <hi>Chriſtian Dector,</hi> as for your Maieſtie, which doth admit and ſerue your ſelfe by it, and yet are the <hi>Gatholique King:</hi> but much more, in reſpect of the higheſt Biſhop, who ſometime decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by ſinifter Informations, &amp; malignant ſuggeſtions of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine wicked <hi>Hypocrits,</hi> is ſeene to fulminate moſt heauy <hi>Cenſures</hi> &amp; to threaten horrible war againſt great <hi>Potentates,</hi> who rightly vnderſtood, haue not at all offended his repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, nor his <hi>Eccleſiaſtique Iuriſdiction:</hi> Neuertheleſſe hee doth at preſent beare theſe high iniuries, with ſo much ſcandall of <hi>Chriſtianitie,</hi> and ſo great diminution of his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. Some iudge that this is not done without a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry but let him declare it that vnderſtands it. I will diuine no more.</p>
               <p>This ſufferance of the <hi>Pope,</hi> &amp; greedineſſe of the Miniſters of your Maieſty who preſume to do alwayes abſolutely wel, when they amplifie in any ſort <hi>perfas, &amp; nefas,</hi> the <hi>Roiall</hi> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, hath cauſed, that after hauing made you equall to his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> in diſpenſing <hi>Eccleſiaſtique</hi> Affaires in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and ſuperiour in cenſuring the <hi>Pontiſiciall Cenſures</hi> in that of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> they haue alſo claimed, that you may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the authoritie of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> in the <hi>Conclaue</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> for the election of the high Prieſt; ſo it comes to paſſe, that <hi>Abiſſus abiſſum inuocat</hi> Let it preuaile to ſpeak truth, <hi>ô ſacred Catholique King;</hi> and what elſe are thoſe great <hi>Penſions,</hi> I will not ſay that your Maieſtie giues, but which your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters make you giue (becauſe you giue not but according to their Counſell and perſwaſion) to ſo many <hi>Cardinalls,</hi> but <hi>Simoniacall</hi> bribes, wherwith they intend to buy their voices to elect <hi>Popes</hi> to their Content, and to exclude thoſe who are not of their humour? And although this is not done by way of Contract, yet enough for aduantage to him, who lookes vpon the intention, though cloaked, yet too well
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60796:46"/>knowne to the world; And I am aſſured, that when they counſell you to giue a <hi>penſion</hi> to any <hi>Cardinall</hi> (here I call to witneſſe of truth the inward Conſcience of your Maieſtie) they doe not bring to your Conſideration, that hee is a man of good life, and poore fortune, or that he well vſeth Riches, diſpenſing them to the poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that hee builds <hi>Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls</hi> and <hi>Monaſteries</hi> for needy, and religious perſons; but they ſet on the <hi>frontiſpice,</hi> that he is a <hi>Prince Cardinall,</hi> great in blood, great in authoritie, great in dependance, that he is a Subiect capable of the <hi>Papacy,</hi> that hee is affectionate to your <hi>Crowne,</hi> that he will euer remaine your deuored ſeruant, and obſequious to your will, and ſuch other like; None of which concerne the good of the <hi>Church,</hi> the honor of God, nor the fruit of <hi>Chriſtianitie,</hi> but all addreſſed to the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Intereſt of your Maieſtie. I ſay not now, you doe ill to giue <hi>penſions</hi> to <hi>Cardinalls;</hi> rather, it is well done, you ought to doe it, ſeeing you giue them nothing of your <hi>Royall</hi> Patrimonie, but <hi>Eccleſiaſtique</hi> goods, which are the Parrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and cannot better bee diſpenſed then to thoſe, who are the Pillars of <hi>holy Church;</hi> The euill is, that with this Intereſt it is purpoſed, to oblige them to your wil, ſo that, at your pleaſure, and not according to their <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and Inſpiration of the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> they ſhould giue their <hi>ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> for the Election of the <hi>Pope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer, it is known in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; though Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it not, yet the memories of men preſcrue what was practiced with the <hi>Cardinalls</hi> their <hi>Conſederates,</hi> in the choice of <hi>Vrban</hi> the Seauenth, &amp; <hi>Grogorte</hi> the Fourteenth, by the Miniſters of the King <hi>Don Phillip,</hi> father of your Maiſtie; who glad of the death of the moſt holy Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fiſt (a death deſired, and by common opinion alſo, by them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured) and fearefull of the danger, that another of like thoughts ſhould ſucceed him, they did embroile the whole <hi>Conclaue,</hi> leaſt my ſhould aſcend to the <hi>Papacy</hi> who was not truſty, and fauourable to the <hi>Crowne</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> as if to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the good of <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> ought not to be preſerred.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:60796:46"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vrban</hi> the Seauenth did ſucceed <hi>Sixtus,</hi> who in thirteene dayes died. After <hi>Vrban</hi> thoſe of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> faction by all meanes would haue the <hi>Cardinall Palieto</hi> Pope; But God did ordaine, that <hi>Sfondrato,</hi> called <hi>Gregorie</hi> the fourteenth was choſen.</p>
               <p>This Election made vpon the fift of <hi>December,</hi> 1590. (your Maieſtie may obſerue a moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and wiſe Act of your <hi>Catholique</hi> father) the King <hi>Don Phillip</hi> who was conſenting to the Negociations of his Miniſters, diſpatched in the Moneth of Iune following, 1591. to the feet of his <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> to aske pardon and abſolution of the Cenſures into which he was fallen, by intermedling of his Miniſters in matters of the <hi>holy Conclaue.</hi> An Act as I haue ſaid, moſt <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was an amends of the error committed, and moſt <hi>wiſe,</hi> becauſe it ſerued as an inſinuation by that humilitie, to be reduced to the grace of the new Pope, who could not but bee diſtaſted, as hee was, with the workings which he had ſeene, ſcandalized.</p>
               <p>Thus the Miniſters of your Crowne <hi>(O ſacred Catholique King)</hi> dee negociate in <hi>Rome,</hi> onely preſuming by meanes of Penſions, to hold the <hi>Cardinalls</hi> in bonds; With which pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices the vrtitie of the <hi>Chureh</hi> ſeemes almoſt to bee diuided, from whence there is nothing elſe heard of, to the great ſhame and deſtruction of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but factions of <hi>French,</hi> and factions of <hi>Spaniſh Cardinalls.</hi> And although the <hi>French Lords,</hi> doe not intend particularly to oblige any <hi>Cardinall</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, but leaue all in their libertie; Neuertheleſſe thoſe are called of the <hi>French</hi> faction, who by Penſions, or other Intereſts, are not tyed to depend on the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and for them to make a faction; And therefore there is nothing elſe done, but <hi>ſcrutiny,</hi> which of thoſe parties are like to preuaile in the <hi>Couelaue,</hi> at the <hi>Election</hi> of a new <hi>Pope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſpeake ſo clearely, and ſo truely, that I am bound to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it by their owne <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Hiſtories. Of the Election of <hi>Innocent</hi> the eighth, who ſucceeded <hi>Gregory</hi> the fourteenth, it is recorded that it paſſed without any contradiction,<note place="margin">Bau. p. <hi>3.</hi> vita de Innoc. <hi>9.</hi> C. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> faction (ſaith <hi>Bauia,</hi>) which conſiſted of 29
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60796:47"/>
                  <hi>Cardinalls,</hi> and that of <hi>Montalte</hi> which exceeded 20, did eaſilie vnite together; But what ſhall we ſay of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gociations made in the <hi>Conclaue,</hi> after the death of <hi>Innocent?</hi> I will alleage the formal words of the Hiſtory to obtaine the more credit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Por hallarſe muy poce conformes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bau. p. <hi>4.</hi> uitade clem. <hi>8.</hi> C. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>las dos principales promin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias de Europa, Eſpa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na, y Francia, à las quales, come à cabecas ſellegan las demas, eſta miſma diuiſion auia en el ſacro Collegis; queriendo cadauno faborecer à la parte, que la razon, ò aficion le obligauae:</hi> That is,</p>
               <p>By the great inconformity of the two principall Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Europe, Spaine,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> to which, as <hi>Heads,</hi> the reſt doe adhere; the ſame Diuiſion was in the ſacred <hi>Colledge,</hi> euery one deſiring to fauour that part, to which reaſon or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection did oblige him.</p>
               <p>Behold a confeſſion of the factions, which I mentioned of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh Cardinalls;</hi> But becauſe at this time <hi>France</hi> was without a King, and the warre was made againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, the French faction had little credit, whece it was iudged, that the contrary part was eaſilie able to create a <hi>Pope</hi> dependant vpon the <hi>Catholike King,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> much impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the perfection of his affaires. That which makes mee aſtoniſhed, is, that his Maieſtie who had acknowledged his error to haue buſied himſelfe in the former Election of <hi>Popes,</hi> and had with ſo great ſubmiſſion demanded pardon of <hi>Gregory</hi> the 14. ſhould in this occaſion ſuffer himſelfe to be drawne anew into the ſame error; And if the Hiſtorie lye not, your Maieſtie alſo who was then Prince of <hi>Spaine,</hi> did therem concurre; The Cardinall <hi>Santa Seuerina</hi> a Neapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litan, who,<note place="margin">Bauia vbi ſupra.</note> ſaith the Author,</p>
               <q>Era vaſſallo del Rey Catholico, y tan querido de los dos Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos padre y hijo, que ſiempre procuraron ponelle en la ſilla de S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro; come lo haz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a aora el gran Filipo II per medio de ſu Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baxador:</q>
               <p>That is:</p>
               <p>Was a Vaſſall of the Catholique King, and ſo greatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued of the two <hi>Phillips</hi> father and ſonne, that they alwayes
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60796:47"/>ſollicited to place him in St. <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire, as at this preſent the great <hi>Phillip</hi> the ſecond did, by meanes of his Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour.</p>
               <p>And it followes in the Hiſtory, that the Ambaſſadour, which then was the Duke of <hi>Seſſa,</hi> was the laſt that went out of the <hi>Conclaus,</hi> when it was ſhut vp; and that if hee had ſtayed within, as he was perſwaded, hee had ſecured the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of <hi>Santa Seuerina:</hi> But in reſpect of modeſty, hee would depart, left it ſhould be beleeued, that it was managed with little libertie; a modeſtie (well obſeruing the Hiſtorie) which was no vertue, but a warineſſe proceeding of feare, and confidence: of feare, that other Princes would accuſe the Election of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> violence; and of confidence, to haue ſo well diſpoſed all matters, that his abſence could not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall. For theſe reſpects then, hee came out, but within the <hi>Conclaue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hazia en eſte intente Madruccie con elfabor de Espana,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bauia vbi ſupra, Ca. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des diligentias penſande ganar alguno de les Eccluyentes, para ſanta Senerina,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is:</p>
               <p>To this end <hi>Madruccio,</hi> with the fauour of <hi>Spaine,</hi> vſed great diligence, hoping to gaine ſome of the <hi>Excluſiues</hi> for <hi>Santa Seuerina.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus was it negociated by the Ambaſſador and Cardinals partiall, as the Catholike King pleaſed: But Diuine diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition preuailed, which wrought the Aſſumption of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Aldobrandine</hi> to the Popedome, called <hi>Clement</hi> the Eight: a Biſhop truely holy, ſuch as the ſeruice of holy Church required, and happily giuen by God, and not by any Prince of this world.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Conclaue</hi> was long, diſunited, contencious, full of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſts, and iuſt ſuch as muſt be, where <hi>humane,</hi> accompanied with <hi>Deuilliſh</hi> power, doth oppoſe the <hi>Diuine</hi> will; and in ſome other Coniuncture might eaſily haue cauſed a <hi>Schiſme</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of God, onely by the extraordinarie and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Negociations, which for <hi>Santa Seuerina</hi> were vſed. Of which it ſeems the new Pope <hi>Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> was not free of ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60796:48"/>who would that that Cardinall ſhould reſigne all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion which he might haue to the <hi>Papacy;</hi> A diligence eſteemed important,<note place="margin">Bauia vbi ſupra.</note> though <hi>Bauia</hi> call it ſuperfluous.</p>
               <p>From all theſe premiſſes <hi>(O Catholike &amp; moſt mighty Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch)</hi> the world doth draw one of theſe two moſt neceſſary conſequences, which are, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> either beleeue not in God, or preſume to bee able to doe more then God. Becauſe, if they beleeue in God, they ought to know, and hold for faith, that the <hi>Election</hi> of a <hi>Pope,</hi> although made by mediation of men, is the worke of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt:</hi> And if they ſo beleeue, and neuertheleſſe attempt, that the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould be choſen according to their will, then they preſume to be able to depriue the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> of that authority, which onely to him appertaines; who can finde a meane to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile theſe extreames? firſt the fire ſhall be reconciled to lee; <hi>Light</hi> to <hi>Darkneſſe, Hell</hi> to <hi>Heauen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sacred Maieſtie,</hi> I can doe no leſſe then ſpeake clearly, and if God be <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelfe, God now doth ſpeake by my penne; This is one of thoſe things which deſtroy the <hi>Holy Church;</hi> And a <hi>Catholike King,</hi> who is obliged to ſuccour it, ought not, in ſuch a manner, concurre to ruine it; I could add many other things, but becauſe truth produceth hatred, a curſed ſonne of a bleſſed Mother, I doubt that euen theſe few glanced at, will be ill vnderſtood. And now I forwarne this my writing, that for ſpeaking truth, it ſhall be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Be it as it will, I by ſo much more ſhall eſteeme to haue done my duty, by how much others ſhall doe againſt their dutie. And God ſhall be the Iudge.</p>
               <p>But I am too farre wandred, tranſported with a iuſt and holy zeale from my purpoſe, though not beſide the purpoſe; And I pray God, it be not fruitleſſe. I returne then to the principall matter of the <hi>Valteline.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it ſhould be lawfull for ſubiects to rebell from their naturall Prince, to depriue them of their Eſtates, vnder colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red pretences, while for iuſt cauſe, they haue not intimated a warre; I doe beleeue there is no man of honeſtie, who is not aſhamed to affirme it.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:60796:48"/>
               <p>That it is lawfull to Subiects, though ill entreated,<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell, onely ſome <hi>Heretique,</hi> who denyes the holy Scripture, can ſpeake it; St. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle manifeſtly ſaying; <hi>Serui ſubditi eſtote in omni timere Dominis, non tantum bonis er mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtis, ſed etiam dyſcolis; Hac eſt enim gratia, ſipropter Deicon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuntiam, ſuſtinet quis triſtitias, patiens iniuſtè.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that it may be lawfull to embrace them, when it ſhall happen through the occaſion of ill vſage, that they of their owne will doe rebell, there are yet ſome dare maintaine it; abſolutely profeſſing that all good Princes are bound to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour the oppreſſed, and that the condition of the miſerable ſhould be too wretched, if they might of no ſide hope of aide; But to vnderſtand this caſe with Iudgement, it muſt not be diſcuſſed with theſe vniuerſal propoſitions, which only ſhew a certaine Equity; but it is requiſite to reduce it to particular and proper termes of Iuſtice. Diſtinguiſhing then; wee ſay, that that Prince, to whoſe pretection the rebelled people of another Prince haue recourſe, either hee hath right of ſome action ouer them, as the Subiects of the vaſſalls of his <hi>Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datory,</hi> or he hath no right of action whatſoeuer. If he hath no Action, neither can hereceiue them into protection: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, if People (though ill handled) doe contrary to the Diuine Law, to rebell; againſt the ſame Law he ſinnes, who doth fauour and protect their Rebellion. If a Thiefe doe ill to robbe, it cannot be ſaid that he doth well, who doth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, to ſhare in the theft. If a murther doe ill to kill, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net be ſaid, that he doth well who receiues him, that Iuſtice may not puniſh him; And who can then ſay, that a Prince doth well, to entertaine the Rebells of another: If theſe in rebelling, abſolutely doe euill?</p>
               <p>Vniuſtly then haue the Miniſters of your Maieſtie done to intermeddle in the <hi>Valteline,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet it were true, that of themſelues they had rebelled; much worſe, when euen they, at is demonſtrated, haue with wicked Arts induced them to Rebellion; But it ſhall be the worſt of wichedneſſe, if, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all Iuſtice, they will now poſſeſſe it by may neforce, as they ſhow to deſire to doe, ſeeing therein already they
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60796:49"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:60796:49"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:60796:50"/>haue built forts, and that your Maieſtie doth conſent and approue it; of which the World will iudge that you more eſteeme your owne Intereſt, then all humane and Diume lawes; which God forbid.</p>
               <p>Onely the <hi>ſupreame</hi> Prince can hold in himſelfe ſuch ſort of Dominion, ouer the Countries rebelled from his <hi>fondate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> But when yet they haue not rebelled; and were ill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned, he may, and ought to depriue the Prince his Vaſſall: becauſe the inueſtiture of the <hi>fee</hi> is not granted for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ruine, but that they ſhould bee gouerned with luſtice; wherefore if the <hi>feudatory</hi> vſe iniuſtice, and ill entreatment, he falls from his Iuriſdiction, and the Soueraigne Prince may thereof depriue him; and not doing it, beeing able, hee ſhall bee a wicked Prince, and no leſſe guiltie of the euill before God, which he ſuffered his <hi>feudatory</hi> to doe, then hee the <hi>feudatory</hi> himſelfe is, who acts it.</p>
               <p>Now let your Maieſtie apply this doctrine, which is wholy conformable to reaſon and law, to the Actions of your Miniſters, to the condition of your Subiects, and to the right of other Princes ouer your <hi>Eſtates</hi> in <hi>Italy;</hi> and you ſhall clearely ſee, how your Miniſters are damnable, your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects miſerable, and how much other Princes are obliged to releeue them; My words perhaps will ſeeme bitter, but I beſeech your Maieſtie to conſider if they be true, and finding them ſo, to take them in good part, as bitter medicines, fiery <hi>Canteries,</hi> &amp; ſharp lances vſe to be gratefully receiued from the hands of Phyſitians &amp; Chirurgions, to procure health; &amp; be aſſured you ſhall find them moſt profitable; becauſe your Maieſtie fully informed of the truth, will correct your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, comfort your Subiects, and eaſe other Princes of the neceſſitie to vſe their ſupreame Iuriſdiction.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cauſe</hi> of Subiects and of Miniſters are together vnited, becauſe thoſe are gouerned, and theſe Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; whence, as <hi>Correlatiues,</hi> they goe <hi>paripaſſe;</hi> I will then briefly repreſent to you Maieſtie the Gouernment of your <hi>States</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> ſo farre as is expedient to the preſent matter.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:60796:50"/>
               <p>The <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Milun</hi> in the time of the <hi>Emperour Charles</hi> the ſift, began to bee ill intreated; from whence that ſad, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable, and deſpairefull Ambaſſage, which they ſent by <hi>Baptiſta Archinto</hi> to <hi>Nazan</hi> is recorded, who onely becauſe he did lament, in the name of his afflicted Countrey, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with an ill eye, ſent back without remedy, and by the <hi>Imperiall</hi> Miniſters, at his returne, ſharply reprehended; which might haue occaſioned the Rebellion of that people, if they had found any better Prince who would haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hac vbi ſub ipſum Caeſaris à Nicea diſceſſum ex legatione ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; per vrbas Ciſalpinae Galliae svulgate ſunt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iouius Hiſt. lib. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>vſque adtò tamum ex vei indignitate odium Caeſaricr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uit, vt omnes, ex rarum deſperations fuciſe defect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> upoareret, ſi mitior &amp; clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otr, qui d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dentes reeiperet, Dominus offereretur; immoderatis ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dem, puoe, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llbque rributis upproſſi, nonn etiam, tum mmſtruae exactionis oner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> periut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rant; quae nunquam deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aboni mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ales <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, donoe vincret C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſar, atque Italiae Imperis poteretur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A feet alſo, a ſecond time, when <hi>Strozz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Palla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icino Viſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti,</hi> who made warre for the King of <hi>France;</hi> approached to <hi>Millan,</hi> all the <hi>Imperiall</hi> Miniſters held that Citie as bad as loft, onely becauſe it did feele the yoake of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too violent and heavy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aſſiduis at que intollerandis trubutis alienata,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jouius lib. <hi>45.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>parata, credi poterat, ad nouandas res, vt inuictum, &amp; pergraue Hispanici Regm ingum excuteret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If from that time to this, their grieuances are diminiſhed, or augmented, your Maieſtie beſt knowes.</p>
               <p>To what termes that <hi>State</hi> is at this day reduced, who doth not know, let him conſider this, that already many and many year as it hath ſuffered great numbers of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers lodged in the houſes of poore particular men, at diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Diſcretion of Souldiers, and Tyranny, are one and the ſame thing; who hath not proued it, let him pray to God fuſt to die, and hee ſhall die happier, then euer to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it. And let him be content to beleeue for faith, that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60796:51"/>vnder ſuch diſcretion, goods and honour are diſpatched, and hardly is life ſecure.</p>
               <p>I paſſe ouer the burthen of new Tributes, I leaue the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine of Miniſters, who like blood-ſuckers haue exhauſted the veines of that plentifull bodie, becauſe in compariſon of lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Souldiers at diſcretion, I eſteeme all to bee nothing; and he who is able to endure to ſee them eate the ſuſtenance of his poore family, and that which exceeds all other Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, to grow familiar with his wife, daughters, and Siſters, it may be ſaid, that he is growne inſenſible of any iniury. I remember to haue read in the warres which were ſo ſharpe betweene the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians</hi> and <hi>Genoueſes,</hi> that theſe did take a Citie of their Enemies, and held it the ſpace of tenne yeares ſubiected to diſcretion: whence it is credible, that beſides other matters, they did diſpoſe of their wiues, according to their pleaſures; for which cauſe, to this day, though now two hundred and fifty yeares are ouerpaſt, there cannot bee done a greater Inuiry to thoſe people, then to call them <hi>Genoueſes Baſtards:</hi> and notwithſtanding that ſtaine, with length of time, and the continued peace of that Citie, which neuer ſince felt the offence of Enemie, hath beene oftentimes worne out and waſhed away, yet vpon euery occaſion they reſent the onely memory of that ancient Iniury done to the honour of their women, which ſeemes indelible, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. If I then ſay that the greateſt of all the <hi>Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> which the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Millan</hi> doth now ſuffer, is to haue their wiues at the Souldiers diſcretion, I ſhall not ſpeak much wide of the purpoſe, becauſe it is a matter very likely, that in times to come, the <hi>Millaneſes</hi> may bee called <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards; If this be tolerable, let your Maieſtie conſider.</p>
               <p>Wee proceed to <hi>Sicily;</hi> Let it not be grieuous to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie that I ſpeake this truth; that if this day, there were any other Prince as ready to ſolicit the deſtruction of <hi>Spanyards,</hi> as there was once a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King to procure that of the <hi>French;</hi> ſodainly and eaſily wee ſhould ſee another <hi>Scicilian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſper:</hi> the cauſes are the ſame, and are not newly begunne; Let the Inſurrection of <hi>Meſſina,</hi> bee remembred,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60796:51"/>then when the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice King Don Iuan de Cardona,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſeph: Bonfigl. Hiſt. Sicil. p. <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> would op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe that Kingdome with intolerable Tributes. And let it bee conſidered, with what pride, and with how great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine he vſed the <hi>Meſſineſi,</hi> becauſe they defended the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of their Kingdome. For which cauſe, iuſtly prouoked, they did generouſly to his face, vpbraid him, that he acted another <hi>Phallaris,</hi> another <hi>Dioniſius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Vgo de Moncada</hi> (who would not ſtart,<note place="margin">Bonfigl. p. <hi>2.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> onely to heare this name? this was that impious man, that ſacked <hi>Rome</hi>) was alſo <hi>Vice-Roy;</hi> how can it bee thought, that hee handled them? Let vs obſerue the words of the <hi>Hiſtory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee was by Nation a <hi>Catalonian,</hi> by birth a <hi>Barcelloneſe,</hi> a man moſt ambitious, greedy of Riches, and immoderately enclined to diſhoneſt Luxury; Hee gouerned <hi>Sicily</hi> with <hi>Crueltie, Auarice,</hi> and <hi>Impudent</hi> Iuſt; Hee neglected ſo farre to puniſh the falſifiers of money, vntill depriuing it of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, hee impoueriſhed that Kingdome; and that which more imported, he made publike Mechandiſe of <hi>Graine,</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that hee exhauſted <hi>Sicily,</hi> and of a moſt fruitfull Countrey, reduced it to the want of bread. Couetouſneſſe was accompanied with other notorious vices, ſo that hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came to the nobilitie and people hatefull; which being knowne vnto him, when the death of the <hi>Catholique</hi> King was publiſhed, hee durſt not appeare abroad for feare of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing ſome notable afront.</p>
               <p>Here the Author proceedeth to the Inſurrection of that Kingdome againſt ſo ſtrange a <hi>Monſter:</hi> who diſguiſed in the habit of a Seruant, ſaued himſelfe by flight, and after got away to his King in <hi>Flanders.</hi> In whoſe place was ſent <hi>Hector Pinatello Earle</hi> of <hi>Monteleone,</hi> who by publique <hi>Decree</hi> would ratifie all the Acts of <hi>Don <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>go,</hi> how tyrannicall ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Whereupon the People (who inſteed of remedy, ſaw the miſchiefe confirmed) made a new Commotion in the Citie of <hi>Palermo,</hi> and the new <hi>Vice-King</hi> was inforced to eſcape to <hi>Meſſina,</hi> vntill the Commons by the Nobility appeaſed, and many <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Souldiers ſupplied him from the King, he became ſtrong, and was able to vent his rage, as
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60796:52"/>he did, with extreame rigor, vpon the mutined. And <hi>Don Vgo de Moncada,</hi> who had ſo ill entreated the poore <hi>Sicili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> in ſtead of puniſhment, was rewarded with great riches, and honored with the ſtandard of Captaine Generall of the Sea.</p>
               <p>They, who at preſent liue, by tradition of their old men, and for as much as themſelues haue proued, doe teſtifie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, that that kingdome hath continually ſuffered grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uances, &amp; cruel extortions, but that the people had almoſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forgotten them, when they felt the heauy yoake of the Duke of <hi>Oſſuna,</hi> becauſe in reſpect of extreame euills, moderate may be called goodneſſe. They exclaime to the Heauens, that he hath left the wretched <hi>Sicily,</hi> deſolate, and rooted vp. They complaine with miſerable outcryes, to haue more then once ſent into <hi>Spaine</hi> to lament to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and alwaies without fruit: And ſince, they remaine wholly confuſed, and aſtoniſhed with the conſideration how he, like another <hi>Don Vgo,</hi> in ſtead of receiuing puniſhment, ſhould be honored, and recompenced with the charge of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice-King</hi> of <hi>Naples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now it is time to diſcourſe of <hi>Naples</hi> it ſelfe: I ſhould vndertake a great worke, to recount that which I haue ſeene and tryed, and perhaps I might ſeeme as paſſionate, I will then mention onely that, which I haue found in Hiſtories, &amp; that which the kingdome, with full voice doth proclaime.</p>
               <p>It was practiced lately in <hi>Naples</hi> to introduce the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition <hi>al vſo de Spania:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Igles p. <hi>2</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>27</hi> Sect. vlt. Bonfigl p. <hi>2</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> The people cryed out, there was no need of ſo great rigour, becauſe (by Gods grace) that Kingdome was not full of Moores, and <hi>Spaudo, Chriſtians.</hi> The <hi>Vice-King</hi> inſiſting on his purpoſe, began to vſe force: the people inſtructed by nature, armed to oppoſe againſt ſuch violence. The <hi>Pope,</hi> informed of the buſineſs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded the <hi>Vice Roy,</hi> in vertue of holy obedience, to be quiet, and he well may doe it, both as Prince of the <hi>Church</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Eaele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Iuriſdiction,</hi> and as temporall. Prince, that Kingdome being the proper <hi>faude</hi> of the <hi>Sea Apoſtolique:</hi> yet for this the <hi>Vice-King</hi> would not deſiſt, but with ſmall and great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillary
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60796:52"/>attempted to bring his purpoſe to effect. All the Citie roſe in vptore, Many houſes were loueiled with the ground, and men not a few ſlaine. But ſooner hee might deſtroy all, then thoſe generous mindes be ſubiected to his will ſo that he did great harme, and obtained nothing. Who ſhall well conſider theſe Actions cannot be perſwaded that Chriſtian zeale tranſported the Vice-King to intermeddle in Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique Iuriſdiction, and to deſire to burden that people with a yoake, little needfull, and leſſe reaſonable, againſt the will of the <hi>Vicar of Chriſt,</hi> Soueraigne Prince as well in Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals as Spiritualls in the Kingdome of <hi>Naples.</hi> From whence it muſt be concluded, that vnder that pretence the <hi>Vice-Roy</hi> had ſome other end, which certainly could not be, but little for the good of the Subiect.</p>
               <p>I know not how to excuſe of Tyranny that Action in the yeare 1585,<note place="margin">Bau. Pontiſ. p. <hi>3.</hi> vita Siſte. <hi>5</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> when the officers drew out of that kingdome ſo great a quantitie of Corne, to ſend into <hi>Spaine,</hi> that although the yeare were moſt abundant, the poore Citie of <hi>Naples</hi> did periſh of famine. A Crueltie, indeed horrible, to take from the <hi>Neapolitans</hi> their owne broad, to feed their <hi>Spaniards.</hi> Therefore not without cauſe, that people, conducted by neceſſitie to deſparation, roſe all in tumult; from whence the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice-King,</hi> (this alſo was a <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Oſſuna</hi>) tooke after, occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to vent his ſury, putting to death forty, ſending to the <hi>Gallies</hi> a hundred, and exiling infinite numbers.</p>
               <p>The preſent <hi>State</hi> thereof imitates that of <hi>Sicily,</hi> as the Duke of <hi>Oſſuna</hi> ſucceeded in that Gouernment, after <hi>Sicily;</hi> To performe my promiſe, I will ſay no more, let that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription no leſſe true then compaſſionate, by the <hi>Kingdome</hi> it ſelfe publiſhed to the World, ſpeake; which ſhall remaine of that Duke a perpetuall, and famous <hi>Elogte.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:60796:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:60796:53"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <list>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:60796:54"/>
                  <item>Miſereſcite. Exteri. Exhorreſcite. Poſteri.</item>
                  <item>Petrus. Gironus. Dux. Oſſcinenſium</item>
                  <item>Natione. Hiſpanus. Genere. Perduellis. Religione. Turcicus</item>
                  <item>Italici. Dalmatici. Germanici</item>
                  <item>Fax. Cruenta. Bellorum</item>
                  <item>Non. Vnius. Sicilia. Verres</item>
                  <item>Neapoli. Pollutis. Templis</item>
                  <item>Conſpurata. Nobilitate</item>
                  <item>Depredato. Aerario</item>
                  <item>Monito. Mauro. Accerſito. Trace</item>
                  <item>Veneta. Vrbe. Per. Inſidias. Ad. Excidium. Tenta</item>
                  <item>Regis. Simplicitate. Per. Corruptos. Aulicos. Diu. Multum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>. Deluſa</item>
                  <item>Hoſpitum. Manubiis. Per. Triennium. Ditato. Milite.</item>
                  <item>Compulſiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>. Populis. Ad. Eorum. Stationes. Redimendas</item>
                  <item>Foedata. Infandis. Exemplis. Ah. Nimis. Ad. Infandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Prona. Ciuitate</item>
                  <item>Nobilibus. Aliquot. Adſe. Vario. Quà. Munere. Quà. Vaframenta. Pellectis</item>
                  <item>Largitionibus. Et. Vanis. Spebus. Plebe. Deluſa</item>
                  <item>Atque. Eorum. Seditioſiſsimo. Bis. Extra. Sortem. Renunciato. Tribuno</item>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:60796:54"/>
                  <item>Denique</item>
                  <item>Fruſtra. Vetatis. Armis</item>
                  <item>Tentatis. Arcibus</item>
                  <item>Et. In. Armatos. Ciues. Per. Triduum. Circumducta. Acie. Sceleſtoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </item>
                  <item>Opportune. Succeſſoris. Aduentu</item>
                  <item>Cedere. Solo. Et. Salo. Compulſus</item>
                  <item>Aurum. Noſtrum</item>
                  <item>Quod. Hic. Corraſit. Nequiter. Alibi. Laſciue. Sparſurus</item>
                  <item>Prouinciae. Neapolitani. Heu. Quondam. Regni</item>
                  <item>Inermes. Enerues</item>
                  <item>Populorum. Deglubiti. Greges</item>
                  <item>Palantes. Balantes</item>
                  <item>Teterrimas. Suas. Clades</item>
                  <item>Ignotas. Regi. Longirquo</item>
                  <item>Et. Torpenti. Faſcino. Sandonallico</item>
                  <item>Pagella. Et. Calamo</item>
                  <item>Quae. Sola. Sunt. Reliqua</item>
                  <item>Repreſentant. Vrbi. Et. Orbi</item>
                  <item>Miſereſcite. Exteri. Exhorreſcite. Poſteri.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:60796:55"/>
               <p>In ſo wofull manner <hi>(ſacred Maieſtie) Naples</hi> doth la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; No leſſe doth <hi>Sicily</hi> grieue, and <hi>Millan</hi> equally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine. But of all their vexations, the vnhappy people are afraid to ſpeake; All their iniuries, with open voice, it is not lawfull to expreiſe. Scarcely they dare publikely bewaile their extreame miſeries; whence their hearts are more corroded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tacitus moeror,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">luſt. lib. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; luctus; verentibus ne ipſae lachrymae pro contumacia hubeantur; Creſcit diſſimulatione ipſa, dolor; hoc alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us dimiſſus, quo minùs profiteri licet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of theſe three principall Prouinces of <hi>Italy</hi> vnder the gouernment of the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, I find recorded in Hiſtorie, that,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſubres ex opulentiſſimis ad egeſtatem redacti,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iov. Hiſt. lib. <hi>39.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>diuque, vel in paee inaniter vexati, fruſtra apud ſurdas Caeſaris aures praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum acerbitatem querebantur. Neapolitanum verò Regnum quo uihil ſpoliatius vnquam fuit, euerſum exutumque omni pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina dignitate conciderat. Et in Sicilia, cum annuis Tributis, tum nouis rei frumentariae vectigalibus, &amp; frequentibus Hiſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum aſtiuis, hyberniſque euaſtatn, occaſio potius rebellandi, quam conſenſus, deeſſe videbatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, certainly, certainly, they are in much worſe eſtate at this preſent. I beleeue not <hi>(O ſacred Catholique Maieſtie)</hi> that there is any Prince in this world, who, for reaſon of <hi>State,</hi> doth not ſometimes ſlip into ſome indecent Action, becauſe it may happen, that the Iudgement and the will are ſurpriſed; the one peruerted, the other blinded with paſſion and intereſt.</p>
               <p>To the conditions of Princes their Miniſters ordinarily do conforme; for theſe are their eyes, eares, hands, and feet; and therefore, as is formerly ſaid, the Actions of Miniſters are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to themſelues the Princes; Let vs then ſay, that Miniſters as well as Princes, may, and doe alſo erre, either by ignorance, or paſſion, or of pure malice; But in all <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> I certainly beleeue, that there haue not beene, nor are found, any Miniſters, of any Prince, or <hi>Rapublike</hi> whatſoeuer, who haue committed ſo great errors, nor vſed ſo many wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60796:55"/>dealings as the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> Let your Maieſtie conſider the few in this diſcourſe alleaged, which are ſcarce the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand part of thoſe in hiſtory recorded, and bee pleaſed with attention to read what they haue done in <hi>India,</hi> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deſcribed by the aforementioned Biſhop of <hi>Chiappa;</hi> And you ſhall clearly ſee, that to this truth there is no reply; and with great griefe of heart, you will compaſſionate the condition of your miſerable Subiects; you will abhorre the execrable Actions of your Miniſters; and as a true Catholike Prince, will prouide to the whole conuenient remedie: which if you ſhall not doe, then that right of other Princes, which I haue pointed at, will take place.</p>
               <p>Your Maieſtie doth know that <hi>Millan</hi> is a <hi>feud</hi> of the Empire; <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> Therefore the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Emporer,</hi> when their Subiects in theſe <hi>States</hi> are not gouerned with vpright Iuſtice, are bound in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God, either to reſume the immediate Dominion, as they haue the Supreme, or to prouide another Prince, that rightly and iuſtly may gouerne; depriuing your Maieſtie of the Inueſtiture of thoſe <hi>feudes,</hi> which will bee eſcheated by the Iniuſtice of your Miniſters, by you tollerated. And if at preſent it may ſeeme, that the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Millan</hi> is ſecure, the Emperour being of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and your neare kinſman, and that you feare not <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> knowing the high Biſhop moſt inclinable to your fauour; yet in many reſpects, there remaines much whereof to doubt; The affection of the minde, and the alliance of blood, with ſome other intereſt ioyned to the one, and the other, are conſiderations that can doe much; But the loue of Heauen, and the feare of Hell, and the infallible Iudgement of God, which will giue the one, or the other, as I beleeue, may much more preuaile: So that at laſt, the Pope, and the <hi>Emperour</hi> will haue more care of their owne ſoules, then of your Maieſties ſatisfaction; I adde, that the <hi>Empire,</hi> &amp; <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> are Electiue <hi>Principalities,</hi> and not hereditarie, whence if the preſent Biſhop bee obſequious to your Maieſties will, perhaps his ſucceſſor will bee contrary. And though now
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60796:56"/>the <hi>Emperour</hi> bee an <hi>Auſtrian;</hi> in ſhort time an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> may ſuccead him; who finding ſo loſt occaſion, will certainty bereaue your Maieſtie of your <hi>feudes</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and when neither of theſe would, I may ſay, God will doe it, and might alleadg the authoritie of holy men, and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of <hi>Sacred Scripture,</hi> but I will o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>it them as ſuperfluous, onely this I will adde, that when all other danger ſhould faile, you ought greatly to feare the heauy diſlike of all your owne Subiects:<note place="margin">Senec. Thabai. Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>3.</hi> ſce. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> becauſe <hi>inniſae nunquam Imperia r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="7 letters">
                        <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
                     </gap> di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let your Maieſly then conſider (to cloſe vp this Diſcount) how your Miniſters bring your <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Italy</hi> into extreame peril, both in reſpect of your Subiects, by their manor of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, &amp; with the machinations which they continually weaue againſt other Princes; And if ouer <hi>Emperor</hi> or <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould take Armes againſt you, you may bee aſſured to haue all the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> and perhaps of <hi>Europe,</hi> your <hi>Oppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites,</hi> becauſe the intereſt of <hi>State</hi> hath opened their eyes.</p>
               <p>Let your Maieſtie imagine to ouer-heare all the <hi>Italian Potentates,</hi> after this manner to diſcourſe among themſelues.</p>
               <p>Now what doe we doe? Why doe we not oppoſe him, who with a thouſand frauds doth aſpire our ruine? The <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyards</hi> poſſeſſe in <hi>Italy, Millan, Naples,</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> beſides many lands wreſted from poore particular Lords, at <hi>Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>, Piombino, Corregio,</hi> and others, and yet are not content; If now they become Maſters of the <hi>Valteline,</hi> whereby they proiect to ſhut vp the paſſage of ſtranger Nations called to our ſeruice, and to keepe it at pleaſure, open to ioyne with theirs, the <hi>German</hi> forces of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this vnion they promiſe themſelues vtterly to bring to nothing the power of the <hi>Republique</hi> of <hi>Venice,</hi> the which being remoued, they hope in <hi>Italy</hi> to finde no other reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: ſo that thereof they will ſoone acquire the abſolute Monarchy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vt ſunt impotentia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iou. Hiſt. lib. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>at que imperandi auida ingenia Hiſpanorum, qui quum ſemelirrepſerint, ad ſummans ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>per potentiam cunctis artibus contendunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:60796:56"/>
               <p>Then would they expect, that the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould bee <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyne</hi> of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and we inferiour Seruants of his <hi>Royall</hi> houſe; wee are too ſure, that this is the In tention of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Miniſters: Already wee ſee, in what treacherous manner they ſeeke to effect it, and wee ſtand ſtill, with our thumbs vnder our girdles: too late we ſhall repent, if ſoone wee doe not reſolue. Here, returning their thoughts vpon your Maieſtie, in whoſe name your Miniſters worke, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, meditating the ſame conceit in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phillip King</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who alwaies with ſnares, with treacheries, with ſacriledge, attentiue to enlarge his <hi>Empire,</hi> being by the <hi>Thebans</hi> choſen Captain of their Army againſt the <hi>Phacians,</hi> who robbing the <hi>Temple</hi> of <hi>Apollo,</hi> with ſacred treaſures had armed to make warre on <hi>Thebes,</hi> vnder the ſhow of <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> readily accepted the charge and Enterpriſe, and at the firſt Encounter, ouercame the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, whence hee was celebrated with Immortoll glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Incredibile, quantum eares apud omnes nationes Philippe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am dedit. Illum vindicene ſacrilegij; illum vltorem religionum.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iuſt. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quod orbis viribus expiari debuit, ſolum, qui piacula exigoret extitiſſe dignum. Itaque Diis proximus habetur, per quem Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Maieſtas vindicataſit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But finding himſelfe victorious and powerfull, hee diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered his diſſembled <hi>piety,</hi> and feined <hi>Religion,</hi> breaking his faith with thoſe, who had made him their <hi>Head,</hi> and ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting that friendly Citie, like an enemy, which had made him a Conquerour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Veluti timens, ne ab hoſtibus ſacrilegii vineeretur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iuſt. paulò infra.</note> 
                  <hi>Ciuitates quarum paulò anto D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>fuerat, qua ſub anſpic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> eius militaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, quae gratulatae illi ſibique victorians nactae fuerant, hoſtiliter occupatas, diripuit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By degrees diſcord among the <hi>Grecians</hi> alway encreaſing, hee faining to helpe, now one, now the other ſide, in the end deceiuing all, vſurped to himſelfe the whole <hi>Dominion</hi> of <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold now (ſay the <hi>Italian Princes</hi>) behold another <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> wholly like to that of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditates
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60796:57"/>nothing elſe but to ſubdue <hi>Italy,</hi> as the other had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected <hi>Greece;</hi> and entring with the ſame pretences of Piety and of Religion, vſing the ſame Arts of Deceit, and Treaſon, doth propoſe the ſame ends of abſolute <hi>Monarchy,</hi> whereby he may, in time, be celebrated with the ſame <hi>Ence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium</hi> as was the other, and it ſhall be ſaid:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philippus Rex Hispaniarum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Juſt. ubi ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>veluti è ſpecula quadam libertati It aliae inſidiatus, dum contentiones Ciuitatum alit, auxilium in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer toribus ſerendo, victos par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter victoreſque ſubire Regiam ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitutem coegit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They conclude the blow is foreſeene, we ſhall be very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if we be not able to defend it.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Engliſh, French, Germanes,</hi> and other Nations, doe noe thinke themſelues free of the danger, rather they hold for certaine that the progreſſes of the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> are preambles to their ruine, and they remember, that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> after the conqueſt of <hi>Italy,</hi> did ſubdue the world; Wherefore our defence is their intereſt, and wee and they for this common intereſt, are bound, by common conſent, and with vnited forces, to reſiſt, yea to ſuppreſſe the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armies,<note place="margin">Va. Max. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quae oppreſſurae ſunt, niſi opprimamur.</hi> And if perhaps ſome doe not beleeue that the <hi>Catholique</hi> King can haue ſo greedy deſires, let him well conſider that which his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors haue done to thoſe many <hi>Kings,</hi> and mighty <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>India,</hi> and from example of others, let him learne to looke vnto him, <hi>Foelix quem faciunt aliena pericula cantum.</hi> Theſe <hi>(O ſacred Catholique Maieſtie)</hi> are the diſcourſes of the <hi>Italian Princes,</hi> not <hi>Chimeru's</hi> of ſubtill wits<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but extracted from the firme foundation of <hi>Hiſtories,</hi> and from the Actions diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered of your Miniſters.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> is knowne,<note place="margin">Saluſt. de coniur. Catel. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> they are diſguiſes to make the vnitiſt vſurpation of the Eſtate of others to appeare faire and honeſt, and that, in truth, <hi>Libido dominandi, cauſa belli habetur.</hi> So <hi>Don Petro</hi> of <hi>Aragon</hi> vſſirped <hi>Sicily,</hi> the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique</hi> Kings <hi>India,</hi> and <hi>Don Phillip</hi> the ſecond attempted to get <hi>France;</hi> vnder the like pretence the Miniſters of your Maieſtie haue now ſurpriſed the <hi>Valteline,</hi> the which was not
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60796:57"/>otherwiſe rebelled of their owne will, becauſe it was tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized in Religion, and in the publique gouernement, as is ſpread abroad, but induced to Rebellion by the Diſſentions inſidiouſly ſowed by the Miniſters of your Maieſtie, and by the tyranny which themſelues haue introduced, by meanes of thoſe Traitors <hi>Pompeio</hi> and <hi>Rodolfo Planta,</hi> and others on them dependant. Your Maieſtie becomes deceiued by ſuch as make you otherwiſe beleeue, &amp; in ſtead of perſwading you to a iuſt warre againſt the Turkes, who are your perpetuall enemies, and worke ſo great ſpoiles to <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in your owne Eſtates, doe from that diuert you, vrging you with termes of Religion, cruelly to deſtroy with force of Armes the <hi>Griſons,</hi> as <hi>Heretiques;</hi> whole Conuerſion ſhould benignely be produced, by the ſweetneſſe of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching; With this and other euill actions your Miniſters with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any your fault, doe bring great reproach to your Royall name; Wherefore you ought iuſtly with them to bee enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and the more, ſeeing they practizing ſo wicked actions, ſeeke to defame all good Princes with detracting words; And if your Maieſtie doth not refraine the tongues, and hands of your Miniſters, they will yet ſay, and doe much worſe; not onely againſt <hi>Secular Princes,</hi> but againſt himſelfe the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> to whom they deſire your Maieſtie ſhould be equall &amp; ſuperiour and that alſo you ſhould vſurpe the authority of the Holy Ghoſt in Election of <hi>Popes,</hi> that they may on you depend. In briefe, they pretend that your Maieſty ſhould be ſole and ſupreame <hi>Monarch</hi> of all <hi>Italy,</hi> and doe beleeue, that thereunto the Dominion of the <hi>Valteline</hi> is the direct way, the which cannot by you iuſtly bee kept, though it were true, which is not, that of themſelues thoſe people had rebelled; but you are obliged to reſtore it to their owne <hi>Lords,</hi> hauing no action in any kind vpon them, as a ſupreame Prince ſhould haue ouor his <hi>feudatory.</hi> The which if it ſhall be well conſidered of your Maieſtie, you will know not onely the Iniuſtice, which your Miniſters deſire to doe, in ſnatching againſt equity, the Eſtates of others, but alſo the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60796:58"/>danger whereinto they thruſt your owne Eſtates in <hi>Italy</hi> the which being continually gouerned with violence, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortions, and manifeſt Tyrannies of your Miniſters, doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a neceſſitie (if they loue their ſoules health) in the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Emperour,</hi> their ſupreame Princes, to depriue your Maieſtie of the Inueſtiture, and to transferre it to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who may iuſtly and mildly gouerne them: And if euer it ſhall bee thus reſolued, your Maieſtie ſhall finde all the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian</hi> Princet your oppoſites, who from the ſurpriſe of the <hi>Valteline,</hi> are confirmed in this opinion, that the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> proiect, ſuddenly to ſubdue all <hi>Italy;</hi> and referring the actions of Miniſters to your Maieſtie, doe conclude, that you certainly aſpire, to make your ſelfe thereof ſole <hi>Monarch,</hi> as in times paſt <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> did of <hi>Greece;</hi> and after the Conqueſt of <hi>Italy,</hi> that you haue fixed your thoughts vpon the <hi>Monarchy</hi> of the World, as did once the <hi>Romans.</hi> Wherefore it is the Common Intereſt of all the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> to oppoſe your Armes, that they doe not in this our World, that which your Anceſtors haue done in the new world of <hi>India.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe matters I haue hitherto diſcourſed, and fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to your Maieſtie, not with intent, as others haue done, detractingly to inueigh, to ſtaine your Reputation, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite againſt you vniuerſall hatred: but with purpoſe freely to diſcouer that truth, which neuer or rarely is brought pure, ſincere, and chaſt, to the eares of Princes; but viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, corrupted, and adulterated, by thoſe, who by indirect wayes, without merit, ſeeke to acquire Grace.</p>
               <p>I know that your Maieſtie feares God, loues Iuſtice, hates Tyrannie, is content with your owne, doth not couer the goods of others, doth prize your owne name; deſires Peace, abhorres Warre, wiſhes the good of your ſubiects, the quier of your neighbours, and the concord of <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> Whence I am ſecure, that taking in good part my words, and weighing them in the iuſt ballance of your great prudence, you will not, that <hi>Truth,</hi> who is the Daughter of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60796:58"/>God, ſent from God, and ſpeakes in the name of God, ſhould returne backe without any fruit; Let your Maieſtie then command your Miniſters, to change their works, and thoughts, that the Affaires of <hi>Italy</hi> may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to quiet and tranquility, and that the World, from the effects, may know, that your Maieſtie is a iuſt Prince, and a true <hi>Catholique King.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:60796:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:60796:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
